<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title >eldh.co</title><link href="undefinedatom.xml" rel="self"> </link><link href="undefined"> </link><updated >2015-07-22T23:20:26+02:00</updated><id >undefined</id><author ><name >Andreas Eldh</name><email >undefined</email></author><entry ><title >React Europe 2015</title><id >areacteurope20152015-07-04t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/react-europe-2015"></link><updated >2015-07-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After three full days of talks and chats on the topic of one specific javascript framework you would perhaps expect to have a feeling that you have covered every possible aspect of this certain framework, it&amp;apos;s present, past and future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the feeling I have after the first React Europe conference. Not at all. I&amp;apos;m leaving Paris after one hackathon and 19 very interesting talks, which covered a surprisingly wide range of topics, still leaving quite a few very relevant interesting areas completely untouched. There was simply not time to cover it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was no talk on testing. There was no talk on module management. There was no talk on team workflow. There was no talk on deployment challenges. There was no talk on functional programming. Styling and design was touched only briefly. Etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had more pressing issues to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we best structure universal apps, which gains do we get from using immutable data and single data stores, how do we handle server communication and data persistence, how do we write server api:s that make the app development and maintainability easier, how can we improve our tooling with hot loading, linting, static code analysis and transpilation, how do we best target multiple platforms, how do we handle complex interactions (touch) and state changes (animation)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that React and the popularity that it has gained in the last year has brought with it fundamental changes to almost every part of the application development lifecycle. From styling to server structure, from mobile to web to text interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;React promotes ways of working that have not been mainstream. React changes the best practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;apos;s only just started. The pace of innovation on the technologies that surrounds React is simply mind-blowing, and has so far shown no sign of slowing down. It&amp;apos;s telling that in several areas, there aren&amp;apos;t even any publicly available implementation of the principles that are considered to be best practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The React community is vibrant, the willingness to tackle hard problems is impressive to say the least and the progress that is being made is staggering. I feel confident that many other parts of the programming world will be influenced by the advancements being done around React.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, was there anything specifically exciting in this great cluster of innovation? GraphQL, Relay and React Native are all interesting, but I&amp;apos;m actually most excited about two other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, Redux by Dan Abramov is a framework that significantly raises the bar when it comes to developer ergonomics without sacrificing anything in terms of performance or maintainability. It&amp;apos;s simply the new benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the work being done around different rendering targets for React shows just how versatile this technology is. The promise of being able to create apps for any target (DOM, iOS, Android, WebGL, wearables, OS X, Windows&amp;#x2026; yes, anything) is just extremely exciting to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;React is everywhere. Everything is changing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in exciting times.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >The Zone</title><id >athezone2015-01-25t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/the-zone"></link><updated >2015-01-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have always worked in offices. For most part, I&amp;apos;ve appreciated the benefits of being at the same physical location as the rest of your team. But this winter has forced me to work from home quite a bit and it has been quite an eye-opener.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started working from the couch, I thought I would have trouble keeping focused with all the distractions around me. I thought it would be hard to keep the dicipline. I had made sure to load up a bunch of tasks that I could take care of without interacting too much with my team, but still my expectations were pretty low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to find that the days just flew by, and I felt really productive. Apparently I didn&amp;apos;t suck as much at concentrating as I did when I was trying to write my thesis. And with no one there to pull me into meetings, ask questions or just talk loudly I could really focus on what I was supposed to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I came back it became more obvious that I wasn&amp;apos;t as productive at work as I was at home. Of course, I&amp;apos;m not the first to experience this (I bought Rework when it came out). And I still think there is a lot of benefits to working in an office. Getting a lot of work done is not one of them though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought it shouldn&amp;apos;t be impossible to change that so I gave it some thought and I realised that it in order to reduce distractions, we would have to have some formal guidelines in place. I call it &amp;#x201C;The Zone&amp;#x201D;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-rules&quot;&gt;The rules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A person decides if and when he is in the zone, and responsible for letting others know.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No one engages in a conversation with someone who is in the Zone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People in the Zone are online and responsive on Hipchat/Slack/Hangouts/Whatever.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emails are responded to at least twice daily, morning and afternoon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone can join the Zone, but the whole company has to respect the rules of the Zone when communicating with its members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;faq&quot;&gt;FAQ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Should The Zone a physical area?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;No. The thought behind the zone is that it should work wherever you are, and in teams where only a few people are in The Zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you know who is in the zone?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;We use headphones. You could try signs, stickers or funny hats. The important thing is the rules are agreed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Should we communicate less?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;No! The goal of The Zone is to enable communication that minimizes disturbances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&amp;apos;t mind being disturbed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;I do. I will try to disturb you from time to time and you can try not to disturb me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does it work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;We&amp;apos;ve done this for a couple of weeks and it&amp;apos;s been working out pretty well. Only a few team members wanted to be in the Zone, but everyone knows and respects the rules. It&amp;apos;s still harder to stay focused than it is at home, but our current office setup really is the worst ever &amp;#x2014; our team is in the middle of an open space with prople running by all the time. I expect things to improve a lot when we move to a new space next month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;feedback&quot;&gt;Feedback&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;apos;d like to hear thoughts on how other people have solved this problem. Talk to me on &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/eldh&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Women in tech</title><id >awomenintech2014-09-19t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/women-in-tech"></link><updated >2014-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A pretty common topic in the tech industry is &amp;quot;women&amp;quot;. I think it&amp;apos;s necessary to talk about women in tech and I was really glad that &lt;a href=&quot;https://nordicjs.com&quot;&gt;Nordic.js&lt;/a&gt; had &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Bougie&quot;&gt;Caroline Drucker&lt;/a&gt; give a kinda Feminism 101 talk at the conference (&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@bougie/notes-on-im-a-feminist-and-so-can-you-7b9c278a0b7c&quot;&gt;Here are Caroline&amp;apos;s notes from the talk, together with a video recording.&lt;/a&gt;). It was a really good talk, and I think we need to continue the conversation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;apos;s get one thing out of the way first: I don&amp;apos;t consider myself a feminist. Not because I oppose women&amp;#x2019;s rights or don&amp;apos;t believe our society has a lot of problems when it comes to gender equality. I don&amp;apos;t. We do. But. I believe in equal rights and equal opportunities but I don&amp;apos;t believe that achieving those will mean that we always get equal outcome. Also, in Sweden the feminist movement has largely become synonymous with far-left socialists that I just don&amp;apos;t want to get associated with. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that is not important. Let&amp;apos;s not let labels draw our eyes from the problem at hand. Actually, I think we are facing two different problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women don&amp;apos;t get into the tech industry. They choose other paths in life and the tech industry becomes male dominated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women and other minorities in tech are treated badly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first of these problems will take years to tackle, and is much bigger than just our little industry. We can do a lot of stuff now to get girls and women interested in tech. But we can&amp;apos;t expect to fix it overnight, since any real solution requires women to choose different paths early in life than they do today and have been doing for some time. The tech industry will continue to be male dominated for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still want to list some things that we should try to do in order to, eventually, make the situation better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get coding into schools. Estonian kids start coding in first grade. So should kids in all countries. Being able to talk to computers is going to be an essential skill in the twenty-first century and it&amp;apos;s going to make kids understand more about what the tech industry is about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make it easier to tell computers how to do advanced things (what we now know as &amp;quot;coding&amp;quot;). We need to make creative tools that are easier to use so that we can lower the barrier to get into the tech industry and make it accessible to more people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a role model, and help showcase other role models. We need to show what we can do and why we love it, to help young people realise that you don&amp;apos;t have to be in one specific way to work in tech. We need to show our diversity, both in terms of gender, race, skill sets and personality. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second problem should be possible to fix much sooner. And much of what Drucker mentioned during her talk is stuff that addresses the second problem. Specifically, she mentioned 10 steps we can take to make things better:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Listen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amplify&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chose your words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use your voice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Question your culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demand adult HR&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be an example&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be human&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these I find somewhat problematic. Not because they are wrong per se, but for two other reasons. First, because they because I think they are vague and easy to misunderstand. Secondly, I think we should focus not on counteraction but on elimination of discrimination and underrepresentation. I believe affirmative action is counter-productive and gives a false sense of acheivment. Those are just minor comments. Do these things and you&amp;apos;ll be fine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do however have a couple of guidelines of my own that I try to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep things professional. Work is work. The fantastic thing about our industry is that pretty much all of us love what we do. We have chosen to do THIS among the many other things we could have done. Treat people as professionals who share your love for tech and keep it at that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be curious. Don&amp;apos;t be afraid to ask if you don&amp;apos;t know or don&amp;apos;t understand. Asking and listening will help you understand people and become more empathic. Let people tell their story.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are all individuals. We have all done different journeys and we all have different experiences, interests and skill sets. Don&amp;apos;t treat everyone the same, but treat everyone as adults, and treat them with respect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speak up. When people make mistakes, initiate a discussion about how to do things in a better way. I think nobody wants to be an asshole, and in every other aspect our industry takes pride in learning from our mistakes. This should be no different. Embrace mistakes and help the people around you improve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would love to see more thoughts on this subject. Ideas need to be bounced. I don&amp;apos;t think there&amp;apos;s a quick fix. Utopia doesn&amp;apos;t exist and we&amp;apos;re only human. But almost all of us want the same thing here. Let&amp;apos;s make try to make it better together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok. So when are we done? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will never be done. We won&amp;apos;t wake up one day having fixed all the problems. We&amp;apos;re going to have to make this, the constant struggle to improve, a part of what we do. Just like we do with most of the problems we face on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Redefining design</title><id >aredefiningdesign2014-07-16t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/redefining-design"></link><updated >2014-07-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;apos;ve long felt that the &lt;a href=&quot;/who-is-a-designer/&quot;&gt;seperation between design and development&lt;/a&gt; has existed mainly because creating &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; things was too hard. Digital things used to be so hard to make that we had to make blueprints, sketches, prototypes, mockups and all these other things to communicate what we wanted to build, before we even started writing code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only did that approach come with a whole set of problems, but our tools has radically improved so building things has become easier. And the things we build have become more complex, making it harder to create designs for them. The cost of design has gone up and the cost of development has gone down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, last week I stumbled across &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@trevorconnolly/the-post-psd-era-doesnt-want-to-kill-designers-4281d505fd9a&quot;&gt;another post&lt;/a&gt; about the &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bradfrostweb.com/blog/post/the-post-psd-era/&quot;&gt;Post-PSD era of design&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, the term that Brad Frost popularized last year, and something that &lt;a href=&quot;http://eldh.co/slutet-p-photoshop-eran/&quot;&gt;I wrote about back in 2011&lt;/a&gt; (in Swedish, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/translate?hl=en&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;sl=auto&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Feldh.co%2Fslutet-p-photoshop-eran%2F&quot;&gt;google translation here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post contained Google&amp;apos;s definition of design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;A plan or drawing produced to show the look and function or workings of a building, garment, or other object before it is made.&amp;quot;
&lt;em&gt;&amp;#x2014; Google&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Before.&lt;/em&gt; That&amp;apos;s the word that struck me as odd. I&amp;apos;ve been working the last six months creating a new system and &lt;a href=&quot;http://eldh.co/finding-a-process&quot;&gt;trying to find a process&lt;/a&gt; that allows us to work in a nice agile way. We build by iterating. Build, improve, refine. Build, improve, refine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if all we do is a continuous &lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt; cycle and design is what&amp;apos;s done before we build, what in our process is actually &lt;em&gt;design&lt;/em&gt;? What is it that we need to do &lt;em&gt;before we make&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, agile works because in the digital world changing things is cheap. But of course some things are more expensive than others. To minimize the risk of having to change expensive things, we need to identify which parts are expensive and then we need to make sure we get them right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My view is that for anyone who is creating a non-trivial system, domain modeling is the most expensive part of the creation process. For others, information architecture might be the most expensive part. Things that we perhaps usually think of as &lt;em&gt;requirements&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is that the expensive part, the part you really should do &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; you build, is probably not what you think of as design. Layout, interactions, copy, typography, iconography, graphics and motion are all important parts of what the final product will be and we cannot do without them. But for any project that&amp;apos;s bigger than a marketing page, those things are relatively cheap, and more importantly they are easier and more natural to integrate into the normal build cycle of the agile process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question we really need to ask before we start building is not &lt;em&gt;What should it look like?&lt;/em&gt; but rather &lt;em&gt;What is it and which things does it represent?&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For us, design as defined by Google, is something quite different from what we normally think of as design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not just a question of semantics. It&amp;apos;s a matter of knowing where we should spend our time, what we should make sure to get right on the first pass and which things we can iteratively improve. It&amp;apos;s about defining a workflow and a process that helps us create better things.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Finding a process</title><id >afindingaprocess2014-01-06t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/finding-a-process"></link><updated >2014-01-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think a lot about process these days. Since we started making stuff for screens, design and development have pretty much been seperate diciplines. &lt;a href=&quot;http://eldh.co/who-is-a-designer&quot;&gt;I&amp;apos;ve talked about this before&lt;/a&gt; and I have been thinking a lot on how to evolve the modern development process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most processes I&amp;apos;ve seen have more or less completely seperated &amp;quot;design&amp;quot; from the rest of the development. Now I am a part of the organization for development of frontend stuff at Quinyx and we want to take a different approach. Our team is growing, so our process will likely gradually become more formalized and stale than it has been so far. I have set up a few principles to guide us on our journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design is how it works&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; We care about design. But we have a holistic view of what design is. The things we often refer to as design &amp;#x2013; layout, interactions and graphics &amp;#x2013; are important. But so is performance, reliability, accessability and copy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Design is not how it looks on paper, how it is simulated in a prototype or how it is explained in a breif. Design is how it works for the user. This means we avoid using deliverables that might give a false picture of how the product will look and work. We prefer usable prototypes over static mockups, real implementations over Photoshop comps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We want to be agile&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Doing &amp;quot;design&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;development&amp;quot; in seperate steps means it&amp;apos;s hard to be agile. It means you create deliverables and lead times between the different stages. When you work on a short project, that approach might make sense and when you work in an agancy/client setup, there might be business reasons for such way of working. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; But if you are building a complex product that is going to live for a long time and continuously evolve, being able to &lt;em&gt;improve what already exists&lt;/em&gt; in an efficient way is really smart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; This means we want to have a process where the time between an idea and a tested implementation of that idea is really short. If that means skipping steps like detailed wireframes and graphical mockups &amp;#x2013; so be it. If we like how it works, we can take more time to polish it afterwards. If we don&amp;apos;t, we just try the next idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Our only deliverable is a working product. Anything else that we produce in the process needs to be properly motivated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good domain understanding is the key to taking the right decisions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; A good understanding our users and the problems that they face is essential in helping us take the right design decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; We work in a pretty complex domain, and dogfooding isn&amp;apos;t really a way to gain real insight for us (even though we do use our own product to some extent). This means we have to spend a good deal of time on making sure we have a &lt;em&gt;shared&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt; understanding and vocabulary to describe the domain. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short feedback loops are essential&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Design is about understanding the problem, but it&amp;apos;s also about exploring solutions, about discovery. It&amp;apos;s about trying things to see how they work. We try to make it easy to explore new ideas, to be creative. This echoes both in our choice of tools and in the culture we try to build, where we focus on communication, collaboration and good feedback. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope these guidelines will make things a bit easier for us when making decisions about how we do things. We&amp;apos;re pretty happy with it so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a later post, I will share some details on how the process works and on the tools we use.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >A year of progress</title><id >aayearofprogress2014-01-01t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/2013-a-year-of-progress"></link><updated >2014-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You know all those profile and presentation texts you have to write. For every new service you write another one. Somewhere, I don&amp;apos;t remember where, I wrote &amp;quot;I live for progress&amp;quot;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year was a year of progress for me. During the last 12 months I have had the fortune of working with a lot of fun stuff and learn from amazing people. For that I am truly grateful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After working on a couple of projects that never made it to the public during 2012 I was lucky enough to build real stuff last year; stuff that people use and enjoy, now and hopefully for many years to come. I&amp;apos;ve learnt so much from this and I hope it has prepared me for what&amp;apos;s to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new year will incredibly exciting. I am building new things with new colleagues, and I think we can accomplish some pretty great things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last couple of years of my career has been mostly about writing code and I&amp;apos;ve never really been comfortable with that. Code is never more than means to an end. I don&amp;apos;t care about code. I care about making stuff that help people. Tools that are better than the ones we use today. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think people need progress. We are constantly improving everything around us, like we have been since the dawn of time. The history of mankind is one of trying to make things better. Progress is a natural thing, something we take for granted. But it doesn&amp;apos;t just happen. It requires people to put their hard work, focus, patience and talent to good use. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making things is exciting. Let&amp;apos;s make some awesome things this year.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Moving on</title><id >amovingon2013-11-14t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/moving-on"></link><updated >2013-11-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow is my last day as a consultant. On Monday I will start working as a designer for &lt;a href=&quot;http://quinyx.com&quot;&gt;Quinyx&lt;/a&gt;, a company that makes Workforce Management software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My career began at a tech startup in Stockholm. We made advanced storage and backup software and I learned so much from my time there. I got the chance to do everything from interaction design to testing, from sales to web development, and I really enjoyed the process of building something. However, the company failed and I decided to start working as a consultant. After all, that&amp;apos;s what most of my friends from university was doing and they seemed to like it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then I&amp;apos;ve been working as a consultant, getting thrown into different projects, mostly doing code monkey stuff, producing the kind of horrible enterprise software that I was pretty sure every user was going to hate. Actually I still don&amp;apos;t know what any of the users think &amp;#x2013; user feedback never made it all the way back to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a consultant, I&amp;apos;ve been in all sorts of projects in all sorts of organizations and I&amp;apos;ve learned from all of them. Some projects have been fun, some have been boring. But none of them have been mine. I have always been building someone else&amp;apos;s thing. I have never been responsible, and I&amp;apos;ve never been on a project long enough to see it through. You rarely get bored as a consultant, but you never become attached to something either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might be na&amp;#xEF;ve, but I hope working at a product company will give me a chance to do something about that. I&amp;apos;m hoping to get an opportunity to build something great, iterate on it and live with it. And more than that, I hope to help make peoples lives a bit easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am really excited about the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Pencils and oil paintings</title><id >apencilsandoilpaintings2013-10-26t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/pencils-and-oil-paintings"></link><updated >2013-10-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Imagine drawing with a pencil and instead of the lines on the paper appearing instantly as you drew them you had to wait five seconds, put away the pencil and flip your sketchbook to see the result of what you just drew. If you wanted to change or add something you would have to flip the sketchbook back again, pick up the pencil and draw some more. Then repeat the whole thing agian. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That would be frustrating, right? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, that&amp;apos;s pretty much what working with web coding has been like. Write some code, save the code, switch to the browser, reload the browser, look at the page, switch back to the editor, write more code&amp;#x2026;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web sites we used to make were like pencil sketches. And there are tools (Photoshop for example) that are really great for creating sketches like these. It&amp;apos;s like using a real pencil. After you had made a sketch you just needed someone to copy it using the time-shifted code pencil so that it became a website. And for someone with the coding chops that&amp;apos;s not too difficult, if you know exactly how it should look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But these days, the web sites we are building are more like oil paintings. Much more complex than pencil sketches, with color and structure that you can&amp;apos;t communicate through a pencil sketch. So no matter how nice that Photoshop pencil sketch is, there&amp;apos;s still plenty of work left for the guy making the oil painting. And he still only has time-shifted brushes and pencils to work with. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing with code is hard. You basically have to become &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3vAnuBtyEYE&quot;&gt;Cypher from The Matrix&lt;/a&gt; to be able to design properly &amp;quot;in the browser&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously that&amp;apos;s ridiculous and quite naturally people have been working hard to make better tools for us struggling front-end artists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there are two ways we can improve the tool set here. Either we can make the switch out the pencil for something more like real paint and brushes and we can make the time-shifted code brushes less time shifted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-tools&quot;&gt;New tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adobe are with their &lt;a href=&quot;http://html.adobe.com/edge/&quot;&gt;Edge&lt;/a&gt; line of tools doing both of these things. &lt;a href=&quot;http://html.adobe.com/edge/code&quot;&gt;Edge Code&lt;/a&gt;, built from the open source editor Brackets, aims to connect the code editor to your browser. Changes made to CSS are instantly updated in the browser, without you even having to save. HTML changes requires a file save, but the page is still automatically updated. Edge Code still has some way to go but it&amp;apos;s a promising project. And still, for someone who doesn&amp;apos;t know their code already, using it as a design tool will be like drawing with blindfolds on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://html.adobe.com/edge/reflow&quot;&gt;Edge Reflow&lt;/a&gt; comes from the other direction, aiming to extend Photoshop and to help create responsive web designs. It allows you to make responsive layouts pretty quickly if you have a Photoshop file to start from, and it will keep assets created in Photoshop in sync with the Edge Reflow layout. You can also export a &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; web page to view in the browser. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it&amp;apos;s not more than a set of colored pencils. There&amp;apos;s no support for interactivity. No hover states, no touch feedback, nothing at all more than just static layouts. It adds another dimension to Photoshop mockups&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other tools, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.divshot.com/&quot;&gt;Divshot&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://webflow.com/&quot;&gt;Webflow&lt;/a&gt;, are attempts to remove the coding blindfolds and make the web pages as editable as the code itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of projects that aim to improve the coding workflow as well. &lt;a href=&quot;http://mixture.io/&quot;&gt;Mixture&lt;/a&gt; for example provides a toolkit to help fix many of the problems with coding, for example it automatically loads all your saved changes into any connected browser (on any device). Neat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;future&quot;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is the holy grail of web design tools? Well, to go back to the painting metaphor, we want brushes and colors that are not time-shifted, that give us immediate feedback without limiting what we can produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter how good tools like Edge Reflow become, we still have to translate their output to &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; web stuff. We would &amp;#x2013; at best &amp;#x2013; be back where we were in the &amp;quot;good old days&amp;quot;. But I think it&amp;apos;s unrealistic to expect them to do anything but play catch-up with web technologies, and that means they will always be limiting what we can create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coding tools on the other hand will always be able to produce whatever the underlying technologies allow. That&amp;apos;s where the potential is. If we can make coding tools that give us good enough feedback on what we are doing then they can be used to create things in a whole new way.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Immediate feedback</title><id >aimmediatefeedback2013-10-14t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/immediate-feedback"></link><updated >2013-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I re-watched &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/36579366&quot;&gt;Bret Victor&amp;apos;s talk &amp;quot;Invention on principle&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; last night. And it got me thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not yet familiar with &lt;a href=&quot;http://worrydream.com&quot;&gt;Bret Victor&lt;/a&gt; I envy you, because you have a couple of really mind-blowing moments ahead of you as you look through his work. He is one of the greatest minds of our time. (By the way, dont&amp;apos; miss &lt;a href=&quot;http://worrydream.com/cv/bret_victor_resume.pdf&quot;&gt;his CV&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;apos;s unreal.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principle he lives by is that &lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;creators need imediate connection to what they create&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;, and based on this principle he has come up with a number of tools that create that kind of connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hated Java development because the connection between the tool (the code) and what I created (the system) was too slow This makes creating things hard, unless you already know what you are doing, which would mean all of the creativity was gone from the creation process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web front-end development is nicer in that way. There&amp;apos;s still not an immediate connection between the coding and the output but at least there are no 20 minute compiles to sit through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the lack of tools that give us that sought after immediate connection to what we make have helped create the divide between designers and developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we think of design as &amp;quot;deciding how thinks should work&amp;quot; and development as &amp;quot;making things work as they should&amp;quot; then having design and development as two seperate roles makes it impossible to have an immediate connection between the creator and the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the creative parts in the process of making stuff, deciding as you make is the only real way produce good results. Having that immediate connection makes you try things you wouldn&amp;apos;t have tried and think thoughts you wouldn&amp;apos;t have thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a utopic process the feedback loop is infinitely short. We&amp;apos;ll never get to that point but I think fully merging the design tasks into the development process will be a natural next step in improving how we create digital products. This will require different processe and better tools, but I think we have been going in the right direction for quite some time now. Both our processes and our tools are improving in a direction towards more immediate feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as our &lt;a href=&quot;http://sokolovstas.github.io/SublimeWebInspector/&quot;&gt;tools keep improving&lt;/a&gt; and we start using more agile ways of working, more and more people will become able to take on both the developer and designer roles. I think that&amp;apos;s a really good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Smashing Conference</title><id >asmashingconference2013-09-17t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/smashing-conference"></link><updated >2013-09-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was at this year&amp;apos;s Smashing Conference in Freiburg, Germany. I had an amazing couple of days listening and talking to some of the worlds best web people. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some of the things that stuck with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;performance-as-design&quot;&gt;Performance as design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big topic was performance. Websites are growing, and the average site is now around 1.5 MB. We are also seeing increasing use of JavaScript on scroll and touch events, which comes at a performance cost and can result in a bad experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performance really matters. It&amp;apos;s one of the key factors that determine how people use and experience the thing you are building, which of course also has a big business impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;death-to-comps&quot;&gt;Death to comps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The design process was a big talking point. The rise of responsive design has led to new ways of leading the design process. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One technique more commonly used is &amp;quot;designing in the browser&amp;quot; (or &amp;quot;deciding in the browser&amp;quot;), meaning more of the design process takes place in the browser rather than in Photoshop or in sketch books. This is because of the increasing complexity of web layouts, with fluid, responsive layouts, animations and more interactivity makes it hard to test in a meaningful and efficient way using traditional tools. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another talking point was &amp;quot;atomic design&amp;quot;, and the trend towards designing smaller elements and modules rather then designing full pages. For agencies this might be a significant change, since it means the deliverables will change from being some sort of full page comp (either hi-fidelity made in Photoshop or a low-fidelity wireframe) to being something like style tiles, design guide or a fully coded site. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;process-people-design&quot;&gt;Process/people design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building on these changes to the design process, a lot or focus was put on the communication during the process, where it is becoming more common to deliberately create assets that steer the conversations with clients and stakeholders in the most productive direction. It&amp;apos;s simply put about having the right conversations at the right moment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make this happen it is important to have the right kinds of design assets as a base for discussion &amp;#x2013; and often the right choice is to use something more lo-fi than you would usually do. Sometimes it might be a good idea to base the discussion on something other than the thing you are working on, to be able to focus more on feel and inspirations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Microsoft launched their new responsive &lt;a href=&quot;http://microsoft.com&quot;&gt;microsoft.com&lt;/a&gt; many people were surprised that a company like that could pull that kind of project. Obviously it had required impressive communication skills from the design team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;details-of-responsive-design&quot;&gt;Details of responsive design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last years&amp;apos; conference focused a lot on responsive design. This year the focus partly shifted towards other topics, and partly moved to the finer details of designing responsive sites, such as responsive images, modular design and responsive typography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-things-that-were-not-there&quot;&gt;The things that were not there&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some things were, surprisingly or not, absent from the discussions at Smashing Conf. First of all, there was &amp;#x2013; thankfully &amp;#x2013; almost no talk about the battle between flat and skeumorphic design that has been raging in the design community. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was also surprisingly little talk about animations and movement in design. I am thinking this is still a small topic, but one that will continue to gain momentum as the web becomes a more advanced application environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-about-the-conference&quot;&gt;More about the conference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke Wroblewski took notes during most of the talks. &lt;a href=&quot;https://kippt.com/eldh/smashing-conference-lukes-notes&quot;&gt;Check them out here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elisabeth Irgens also did some amazing sketch notes, which you can find &lt;a href=&quot;https://kippt.com/eldh/smashing-conference-sketchnotes&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least: Many thanks to my travel companions David, Hj&amp;#xF6;rtur and Anders for making this trip so much better than I could have hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >The future of photography</title><id >athefutureofphotography2013-08-11t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/photography"></link><updated >2013-08-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I label myself an &amp;quot;enthusiast&amp;quot; photographer. I know basic things about optics and how a camera works, I understand the concepts of aperture, ISO and shutter speed and I spend some time and some on my interest. I enjoy the art of photography, and I admire those who master it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago I got my hands on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://camerapedia.wikia.com/wiki/Contax_RTS&quot;&gt;Contax RTS&lt;/a&gt; that my grandfather used, and I&amp;apos;ve been using it this summer. It&amp;apos;s a magnificant camera, with a couple of very nice lenses to go with it (Zeiss 50/1.7, Zeiss 28/2.8 and Yashica 135/2.8 are the ones I&amp;apos;ve used most). Compared to the old Canon 450d the photos I took with the Contax, on real film, just had so much more soul. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;apos;m also a smartphone and internet junkie. I use VSCO Cam, Instagram, Facebook, Twitter, Path and I will probably use whatever the hot new thing is six months from now. Naturally I want to post photos now and again. Preferrably beautiful photos that give life to the moments I want to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And shooting with film is kinda slow. The time from shutter to screen is at least one week. As much as I love shooting on film, I realized I needed a proper digital camera. So I bought the Sony NEX-7 and a couple of lenses &amp;#x2013; 50mm, 16mm, fisheye adapter and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mirrorlessworld.com/?p=6265&quot;&gt;Lens Turbo&lt;/a&gt; to fit my old Contax Lenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the NEX-7 is a great camera. It&amp;apos;s light and small, controls are pretty great, build quality is good and it looks nice. It takes great photos, and even though they don&amp;apos;t quite have the character you get from film, they still have plenty of life in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;apos;m not completely satisfied. Digital photography should be so much simpler than this. I don&amp;apos;t want to pop out my SD card to transfer pictures to my computer, I don&amp;apos;t want to be stuck in Aperture just to share photos, and I don&amp;apos;t want to &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smartphone cameras will never completely replace real cameras. Most people won&amp;apos;t need a dedicated camera, but some people like to take really good photos, and for that they will always need cameras. But the photos need to be set free. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;apos;s how I would like my photo workflow to be: Take photo -&amp;gt; unlock iPhone -&amp;gt; open photo app -&amp;gt; select photo -&amp;gt; make adjustments/apply filters -&amp;gt; post. If I don&amp;apos;t want to post it directly it should end up in my photo stream so I can process it later, on any device. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;apos;s cameras still come from a pre-2007 world where people &lt;em&gt;don&amp;apos;t&lt;/em&gt; carry around a high-end computing device. The Galaxy cameras from Samsung are an interesting idea, but I think you don&amp;apos;t need to slap a phone on the back of every camera, because every camera user has a phone in thier pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/sony-alpha-nex-6&quot;&gt;NEX-6&lt;/a&gt;, Sony has at least added wi-fi and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eye.fi/products/mobi&quot;&gt;Eye-fi Mobi&lt;/a&gt; is an interesting concept, but both these seem a bit too clunky for me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These baby-steps are in the right direction. But I want to see better integration with photo services, and I think the winner in the digital camera race is whoever decides to become king of the cloud. &lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Theming with SASS</title><id >athemingwithsass2013-06-20t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/theming-with-sass"></link><updated >2013-06-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At my current project I&amp;apos;m helping &lt;a href=&quot;http://kambi.com&quot;&gt;Kambi&lt;/a&gt; build their responsive sports betting client (an in-depth look at the project can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.14islands.com/post/52546836134/betting-on-responsive&quot;&gt;in this post&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a whole bunch of different themes for different customers of the app. As functionality (and associated styles) were added to the app and the number of customers grew, we wanted to find an efficient way of structuring our themes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me just say, before I get more into the specifics of our app, that we pretty much follow the tips about SASS theming outlined in &lt;a href=&quot;http://mikefowler.me/thoughts/efficient-theming-with-sass/&quot;&gt;this post by Mike Folwer&lt;/a&gt;. My main focus will be on the problems facing a large app, with many themes and a lot of styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-old-stuff&quot;&gt;The old stuff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The codebase had recently been converted to &lt;em&gt;Sass&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;LESS&lt;/em&gt;. The code structure was based on a &amp;quot;css mindset&amp;quot;. We hardly used variables, mixins, extends or functions, and all of the theming was done with normal css overrides. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the file structure we had (some things are ommited for clarity):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;common
- module1.scss
- module2.scss
- &amp;#x2026;etc
theme
- overwrite.scss
- paint.scss
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;All the base styling was divided by module in the &lt;em&gt;common&lt;/em&gt; folder and each theme had overrides for all color declarations &amp;#x2013; background color, text color, shadows etc. &amp;#x2013; in &lt;em&gt;paint.scss&lt;/em&gt; and any non-color overrides was put in &lt;em&gt;overwrite.scss&lt;/em&gt;. The downside of this was that we had to overwrite most of the color declarations in the app for each new theme. It was also very hard to maintain. When we added a new feature or changed the structure of the html, every theme had to be seperately updated. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall structure of the css was also really bad, with selectors that was way too specific and complicated and a lot of redundant code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had to get away from this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-thinking&quot;&gt;New thinking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all we had to set up some ground rules. In order to keep the theming process from becoming to complicated we needed to limit &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; theming could be done. This is a tricky decision. If you limit theming too much all themes will look pretty much the same, which will not sit well with our customers. If you allow the theming to be too loose you will end up with a hard-to-maintain mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SASS has some awesome features to use for theming, like variables, mixins and color functions. We decided to go full-on with variables. All the colors used in the css should be set using variables. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new structure is pretty close to what we had before, but with a few notable changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;common
- variables.scss
- module1.scss
- module2.scss
- &amp;#x2026;etc
theme
- variables.scss
- overwrite.scss
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;commons/variables.scss&lt;/em&gt; uses the !default keyword for every variable, whichmeans we can overwrite variables anywhere without causing problems with inherited values. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if this is in our common &lt;em&gt;variables.scss&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$some-color: #fff !&lt;span class=&quot;hljs-keyword&quot;&gt;default&lt;/span&gt;;
$some-other-color: $some-color !&lt;span class=&quot;hljs-keyword&quot;&gt;default&lt;/span&gt;;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then we can put the following in our theme &lt;em&gt;variables.scss&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$some-color: #aaa;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which will give the value &lt;strong&gt;#aaa&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;$some-other-color&lt;/strong&gt;, just like we want to. But we can also set &lt;strong&gt;$some-other-color&lt;/strong&gt; to something else in the theme variables file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This allows us to set a few brand specific colors that cascade through our theming files and have all colors used in the app to be calculated via Sass functions. Pretty neat, and this is probably more or less how we will make themes in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existing themes were not easily translated into the new format and we have spent &lt;em&gt;A LOT&lt;/em&gt; of time setting variable values. There are some 700 variables in the main variables file, and each theme overrides between ten and thirty variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this setup, we have a much more scalable architecture, refactoring is a lot easier, and it&amp;apos;s easier to make the themes consistant. If we want to make changes to the html or selectors we just have to update stuff in one place. When we add something new we make sure to inherit variable values so that no theme-specific updates will have to be made. And all this without actually sacrificing any theming flexibility. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will help us a lot when we add functionality to the app and making new themes will be as easy as setting a handfull of variable values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The app is live on a bunch of places, for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://mobile.888sport.com/en/offering.htm&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://touch.unibet.com/client-start/sportsbook&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any questions or suggestions are more than welcome. Just contact me on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/eldh&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Buying things</title><id >abuyingthings2013-06-01t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/buying-things"></link><updated >2013-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We live in a society built around buying things. This is a good thing, since it allows us to specialize, to do something that we like and that we are good at. But it also means that we have to decide what to buy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am price aware. I dislike spending too much money on things. I buy a lot of used things, and I get most of my clothes from the outlet section on &lt;a href=&quot;http://asos.com&quot;&gt;ASOS&lt;/a&gt;. However, I&amp;apos;ve recently come to realize something:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I have never regretted buying something that was really expensive.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I don&amp;apos;t mean that last beer on the overpriced club. I mean those things where you actually take time to consider the options and in the end decide on the pricier, better, alternative. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You won&amp;apos;t miss money you have spent on something good. You will, however, miss money you spent on something that&amp;apos;s not good. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a philosophy to this. Dustin Curtis &lt;a href=&quot;http://dcurt.is/the-best&quot;&gt;wrote about&lt;/a&gt; how he, after selling all his belongings, decided to only buy the very best things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem, of course, is that it takes a lot of time and effort to find the best things. Cutting though endless layers of marketing speak and misguiding information to find that golden nugget is not something everyone can do all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think it&amp;apos;s a good thing to try to buy things of great quality, things made with love, things that will last. If they feel expensive, it&amp;apos;s hopefully because they are that much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If whatever you are buying is important to you, then buying the best will be worth it. If it&amp;apos;s not that important, don&amp;apos;t buy it at all.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Why you can&apos;t be agile</title><id >awhyyoucan39tbeagile2013-05-11t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/why-you-cant-be-agile"></link><updated >2013-05-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I work as a consultant. It&amp;apos;s been a really good way for me to try different kinds of roles and get to know different organizations. I&amp;apos;ve learned a great deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;apos;ve never really been happy with the way we work in the projects I&amp;apos;ve been in. Even though we have tried to work in an agile way within the team, the organization as a whole hasn&amp;apos;t shared our philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago I joined a new project, and it is quite different from what I&amp;apos;ve experienced before. Pretty much the entire development organization is a textbook example of how to work agile. My team work in a kanban-style way, with little focus on sprints and with continuous integration and deployment. When we have implemented a feature, we release it. When we run out of tasks we estimate new tasks from the backlog and put them up on our board. The team has all the functions needed to take a story from nothing to release &amp;#x2013; back end devs, front end devs, designers and testers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;apos;s pretty great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;apos;m not going to go into detail about why working this way is so great, more than to say that we are really productive and we produce high-quality software. That&amp;apos;s for another post. What I want to talk about is what it takes to work this way, and why so many organizations fail in doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;agile-starts-with-sales-&quot;&gt;Agile starts with sales.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sales people like to promise things. I know, I have been there, and I have made promises to customers without knowing if our developers could commit to them. If you work with B2B at all, you have probably experienced this. Sales guys committing to delivering a fixed set of features on a fixed date. And thus preventing the organization from being agile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same thing often happen with internal projects, because of the way most companies are organized &amp;#x2013; separate units with separate budgets. This effectively makes internal projects equivalent to any other B2B project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, why is &amp;apos;fixed scope, fixed time&amp;apos; so hard to combine with agile?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, being agile is being adaptive to change. And when things change in a project with fixed scope and timeframe, the only variable you have left is quality. And there are few things creative people like designers and developers hate more than being forced to produce crappy things. Things will change in the project. Requirements will be misunderstood or conflicting. The scope you agree to is never what the customer wants in the end. The more you try to specify things, the more problems you will face when implementing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, by setting fixed scope and time you take ownership of the development process. You have committed to things that are not in your hands, but in the hands of the development teams. And a development team without a sense of ownership will have no motivation to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to think of it this way: Bugs exists not just in code, but also in requirement documents, in wireframes, in graphic design specifications and every other artifact you produce. Agile is about producing less of these bug-ridden artifacts and minimize impact of errors that occur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way to making your organization more agile starts with letting go of the detailed specifications. Agree to high level goals, and agree to a process where the development teams have control, where changes can be made easily and where a working system is most valued. Don&amp;apos;t fool yourself into thinking that you are agile just because your teams have scrum boards. You&amp;apos;re agile when you can easily adapt to change and when you allow your organization to constantly improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People love to make great things, and they will if they are given the means.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Check republic</title><id >acheckrepublic2013-05-06t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/check-republic"></link><updated >2013-05-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I heard about this really cool app framework that was supposed to change the way we make web apps. It is called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meteor.com&quot;&gt;Meteor&lt;/a&gt;, and when I started reading up on it I felt I needed to try it. So I decided to make this little app I&amp;apos;ve had in my head for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I almost never use todo apps for organizing my work. I use them for shopping lists, packing lists, reminders and to store ideas for blog posts. And one thing that annoys me about todo apps is that they assume that I want to do each thing just once. For a lot of use cases, that&amp;apos;s not true. Often you want to do a list of things many time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a href=&quot;http://checkrepublic.meteor.com&quot;&gt;Check Republic&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;apos;s a simple app for making check lists. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;apos;s really minimalistic, and it&amp;apos;s not feature complete yet, but I like it. I&amp;apos;d love for you to try it and tell me what you think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway. The reason I did this thing was mainly to see if Meteor is anywhere near as awesome as I hoped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meteor is in its early stages, and there are bugs. But it feels like the future. Having the same language for front-end and server is one thing (node will give you that), but with Meteor you have the same API throughout your app, both front-end and server. Meteor handles all the client-server communtication for you, it handles routing, resource bundling and a hell of a lot more. Templating is painless, so is deployment. It feels pretty much like magic. If you&amp;apos;re into web development at all, you should at least look at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://meteor.com/screencast&quot;&gt;screencast&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Who is a designer?</title><id >awhoisadesigner2013-03-26t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/who-is-a-designer"></link><updated >2013-03-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;It&amp;apos;s not just what it looks like and feels like. Design is how it works.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;&amp;#x2014; Steve Jobs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;apos;s a bit of a clich&amp;#xE9; to start a blog post with a Steve Jobs quote, but this quote really is a good starting point for what I want to say with this post. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design is how it works. That should mean anyone who takes decisions on how it should work is a designer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spend most of my time writing HTML, CSS and Javascript, so I am what most people refer to as a &amp;quot;web developer&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;front-end developer&amp;quot;. I really don&amp;apos;t like those titles. They imply that what I do is seperate from the work of designers. Well, it&amp;apos;s not. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a designer. I decide how things work, I decide how they feel and how they are percieved. Even when I don&amp;apos;t do graphical design or interaction design (sometimes I do that too), many of the decisions I make influence how the user will experience the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;The design/development divide is artifical.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;&amp;#x2014; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/aral/status/315032456644419584&quot;&gt;Aral Balkan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the manufacturing world, the designers would make sketches, then prototypes, then more prototypes. Then production would start. Not many decisions that influenced the outcome was left to be made after the designer had delivered a final prototype. In print design, the designer makes a design and leaves it to the printer. Not many desicions left there either. If there were details in the production stage that would impact the end product, the designer would have to become familiar with these and make the appropriate decisions beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In digital design, things now work a bit differently. First, what we do is highly interactive, responsive and fluid. &amp;quot;How it works&amp;quot; is just so much more than &amp;quot;how it looks&amp;quot;. Second, we now produce one thing instead a million items based on the same design. We don&amp;apos;t have to decide everything before production starts. So we&amp;apos;re working &amp;quot;agile&amp;quot;, meaning we do things in iterations where we improve our product one small part at the time. It&amp;apos;s a continuous effort where building and designing are intertwined and unseperable. There is no digital equivalent of manufacturing or printing. It&amp;apos;s all just building things. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another part of this artificial divide between design and development is that many of today&amp;apos;s designers have very little knowledge of the building blocks of what s/he is designing. Any designer sholuld know the tools of his trade. A web designer who doesn&amp;apos;t know how CSS and Javascript works is like a furniture designer who doesn&amp;apos;t know the properties of different materials or a clothing designer who doesn&amp;apos;t know about fabrics. They will all have a hard time making good design decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The divide exists because we have not adapted the designer role to the digital medium. We need to accept the fact that digital design it a much wider dicipline than it has been in the past. Again, a designer is anyone who makes decisions on how the product should work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This distinction is important, because only when we have decided who can make design desicions can we forcefully pevent the wrong people from doing so. The client&amp;apos;s wife is not a designer. Neither is the project manager, the requirements analyst, the DBA or the test engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are the designers.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Nexus 4 &amp; switching from iPhone to Android</title><id >anexus4ampswitchingfromiphonetoandroid2013-01-03t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/nexus-4"></link><updated >2013-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;apos;ve been a happy iPhone owner since I got an iPhone 3GS back in 2009. I did switch to Android and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samsung.com/galaxyace/ace_overview.html&quot;&gt;Samsung Galaxy Ace&lt;/a&gt; (running Android 2.3) for a short while, but switched back when the iPhone 4S came out. So, I&amp;apos;m familiar with what Android was a year and a half ago, but I&amp;apos;m heavily invested in the Apple/iOS ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three things has kept me from considering switching to Android so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I hate what handset makers do to the OS, with custom skins, crappy apps that can&amp;apos;t be uninstalled and delayed OS updated. I still would not consider getting any other Android phone than a Nexus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hardware has been far from Apple&amp;apos;s standards. Phones have been too big, too ugly, and felt too cheap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A smooth interface without lag is extremely important on touch devices. Much more so than on normal computers. Android has always had major issues with laggy animations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, I&amp;apos;m been curious of the state of Android and since I&amp;apos;ve had major issues with battery life on my iPhone, when the upportunity came along to try the brand new Nexus 4 with Android 4.2 I was more than happy to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hardware&quot;&gt;Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nexus 4 is really good looking. And more importantly, it feels good. It&amp;apos;s nice to hold, with a rubber edge running along the side of the device and a glass back to feels solid. There are no removable parts except for the micro-sim tray, which has a similar construction to that of an iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The front is basically just a big (1280x768, 4.7&amp;quot;) display. A gorgeous display, definitely on par with the iPhone. The speaker is barely visible at the top of the device and there are no hardware buttons. And this has actually been a problem for me. Many times when I pick the device out of my pocket it takes me a while to realize I&amp;apos;m holding it upside down. I suppose I&amp;apos;ll learn eventually to feel the side for the power button, but it has been a bit of an annoyance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot has already been written about the hologram-ish finish on the back. It&amp;apos;s good looking, it feel nice to hold and will probably break if you drop the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;apos;s one physical button on each side of the phone. The one on the left controls volume and the right one is a power switch. On the bottom there&amp;apos;s a micro USB slot, which is quite horrible to use. I really see why Apple went with the reversible Lightning connector instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nexus 4 doesn&amp;apos;t feel as big as I would have expected, probably because it&amp;apos;s a bit slimmer than the iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, a 4.7&amp;quot; screen is too big for me, as I have normal size hands. Reaching the top corners without changing the grip is impossible. I can&amp;apos;t understand why there are no high-end Android phones with smaller screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/nexus/nexus5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nexus 4&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;software&quot;&gt;Software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android has come a long way since 2.3, which is the last version I had used. Everything in the OS runs smooth, even though the touch response isn&amp;apos;t as good as on iOS. It&amp;apos;s pretty easy to get stuff on the home screens arranged the way I want it, though I did replace the default launcher with &lt;a href=&quot;http://novalauncher.com&quot;&gt;Nova Launcher&lt;/a&gt;, which provides some more customization options. I also promptly installed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.swiftkey.net/en/&quot;&gt;SwiftKey&lt;/a&gt;, which was the one thing I&amp;apos;ve probably missed the most from Android when I was on iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notification drawer is much better than the one on iOS. I really like the &amp;quot;swipe to dismiss/remove&amp;quot; gesture that is becoming a standard at least on Android. Widgets are also nice, even though I don&amp;apos;t use more than a few, and easy access to common settings is very convenient. But I think I like the most about Android is the possiblity to choose your own default apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I do miss though is the rubber band effect when scrolling at the end of lists, but I suppose the ommision of that is due to Apple&amp;apos;s patents in the area (even though their validity are disputed). Another thing that really bothers me are that the button bar (with home, back and multitasking buttons) move to the other side of the phone when you rotate the screen. There are some other small annoyances, but overall Android feels as good as iOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/nexus/nexus11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nexus 4&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-app-problem&quot;&gt;The App problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a phone is nothing without apps. The default apps are nice, and I haven&amp;apos;t replaced that many. Some of them, like Gmail &amp;amp; Chrome, are better than their iOS counterparts. Play Store is quite nice, and it&amp;apos;s awesome to be able to install stuff onto the phone straight from the computer. Also, the new guidelines that came with Android 4.0 are pretty nice, and apps that use them are often a pleasure to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, most apps are laggy and downright ugly. This starts already at the home screen, where a lot of apps (even &amp;quot;big&amp;quot; ones like Path, Flickr and Runkeeper) don&amp;apos;t have icons in the right resolution which leaves them blurry. And even if they have the right resolution many of them are smaller than they should be, and a lot of them are pretty ugly. In general, app icons would benefit from some solid guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And although most of the apps I use frequently on my iPhone have counterparts that are as good (or even better), there are a couple of apps I&amp;apos;ve really come to miss. The most important is Tweetbot. And although there are a bunch of &amp;quot;ok&amp;quot; Android Twitter clients, none of them are even close to being as solid as Tweetbot. Reeder is another app that has no solid replacement. &lt;a href=&quot;http://twentyfivesquares.com/press/&quot;&gt;Press&lt;/a&gt; is beautiful, but lacks some crucial features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so it goes. Some &amp;quot;smaller&amp;quot; apps that I really like, Timehop, Want/Svpply, Skala are iOS only, and some, like Ruzzle, are pretty much unusable on Android.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/nexus/nexus7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nexus 4 &amp;amp; iPhone 4S&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android has caught up with iOS. Maybe it&amp;apos;s already passed it. The problem is neither the apps nor the hardware that comes with it has. The hardware is close, the people that like huge diplays might even prefer the Nexus 4 hardware over an iPhone. But the app ecosystem still has a pretty long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will probably go back to using my iPhone in a couple of weeks, and my next phone will probably be an iPhone, but I&amp;apos;ve come to like the Nexus 4 for its gorgeous display, solid build quality and some of the nice things in Android.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two things are still keeping me from becoming a full-time Android user:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of great apps. The only app I &amp;quot;love&amp;quot; on Android is Chrome. A lot of apps are good, but too many are crap or not availible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want a high-end phone with a smaller display. The 4.7&amp;quot; size which has become standard on Android is simply too big for most people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Apple needs to be on their toes. As mobile OS:es are expected to manage more and more of the things we now do on our computers, the flexibility of Android will be an advantage, and Windows is lurking around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mobile war is still very much ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >64 mn, 17 kvinnor och ett kilo mjl. </title><id >a64man17kvinnorochettkilomjol2012-10-20t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/64-mn-17-kvinnor-och-ett-kilo-mjl"></link><updated >2012-10-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Isobel Hadley-Kamptz twittrade ig&amp;#xE5;r om k&amp;#xE4;nsf&amp;#xF6;rdelningen p&amp;#xE5; de som talar p&amp;#xE5; internetdagarna. J&amp;#xE4;mf&amp;#xF6;rt med f&amp;#xF6;rdelningen bland alla som jobbar inom it-branschen s&amp;#xE5; &amp;#xE4;r andelen kvinnor p&amp;#xE5; Internetdagarnas scen ungef&amp;#xE4;r som man kan f&amp;#xF6;rv&amp;#xE4;nta sig, allts&amp;#xE5; en ganska stor &amp;#xF6;vervikt m&amp;#xE4;n.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hadley-Kamptz &amp;#xE4;r vanligtvis r&amp;#xE4;tt klipsk och smart, men begr&amp;#xE4;nsar &amp;#xE4;nd&amp;#xE5; sin rapportering vid att r&amp;#xE4;kna k&amp;#xF6;nsorgan. N&amp;#xE5;, den analysmetoden i sig &amp;#xE4;r ju inte ovanlig och man kanske inte ska beg&amp;#xE4;ra mer i 140-teckensv&amp;#xE4;rlden. Men det &amp;#xE4;r s&amp;#xE5; det funkar: Ska man unders&amp;#xF6;ka j&amp;#xE4;mst&amp;#xE4;lldhet s&amp;#xE5; r&amp;#xE4;knar man k&amp;#xF6;nsf&amp;#xF6;rdelning. S&amp;#xE5; &amp;#xE4;r det bara. F&amp;#xF6;r oss som har jobbat inom it ett tag och faktiskt intresserar oss f&amp;#xF6;r fr&amp;#xE5;gan om varf&amp;#xF6;r s&amp;#xE5; f&amp;#xE5; kvinnor s&amp;#xF6;ker sig till branschen blir dock en s&amp;#xE5;dan analys bara tr&amp;#xF6;ttsamt ytlig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Min f&amp;#xF6;rsta tanke var att det kanske finns n&amp;#xE5;got implicit meddelande i den statistiken. En osynlig handlingsplan som &amp;#xE4;r uppenbar f&amp;#xF6;r den som r&amp;#xE4;knar. Doktor J&amp;#xE4;mst&amp;#xE4;lldhet preskriberar: &amp;quot;Jaha, 20% kvinnor s&amp;#xE4;ger du, d&amp;#xE5; f&amp;#xF6;reskriver vi 20ml tjejer kan-kurser, 4 tabletter l&amp;#xF6;nelyft och 1 rej&amp;#xE4;l dos positiv s&amp;#xE4;rbehandling s&amp;#xE5; ska det d&amp;#xE4;r vara l&amp;#xF6;st inom 2 till 3 &amp;#xE5;r.&amp;quot; &amp;#xC4;r det en kritik av Internetdagarna f&amp;#xF6;r att de inte sl&amp;#xE4;pper fram tillr&amp;#xE4;ckligt med kvinnor? Jag k&amp;#xE4;nner att jag borde veta vad som menas men inte s&amp;#xE4;gs. Lika outtalat men, f&amp;#xE5;r jag f&amp;#xF6;r mig, sj&amp;#xE4;lvklart &amp;#xE4;r orsakerna till det r&amp;#xE5;dande l&amp;#xE4;get. Sexism, grabbig st&amp;#xE4;mning och klanmentalitet. Eller n&amp;#xE5;got.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men diskussionen inom branschen har kommit l&amp;#xE4;ngre och &amp;#xE4;r tack och lov oftast mer explicit. Inte s&amp;#xE4;llan l&amp;#xE4;ggs f&amp;#xF6;rslag om positiv s&amp;#xE4;rbehandling (senast diskuterades det om man skulle vika ett antal platser &amp;#xE5;t kvinnor innan sthlm.js senaste m&amp;#xF6;te). Och varje g&amp;#xE5;ng kommer n&amp;#xE5;gon tjej in i diskussionen &amp;#xE4;r s&amp;#xE4;ger att hon skulle bli ytterst f&amp;#xF6;rol&amp;#xE4;mpad av att f&amp;#xE5; annorlunda behandling p&amp;#xE5; grund av sitt k&amp;#xF6;n. Ofta ansluter folk till b&amp;#xE4;gge l&amp;#xE4;gren, men n&amp;#xE5;gon konsensus har jag inte sett tecken p&amp;#xE5;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oavsett diskussioner, s&amp;#xE4;rbehandling anv&amp;#xE4;nds mycket flitigt, s&amp;#xE5;v&amp;#xE4;l vid rekrytering som i andra sammanhang - i f&amp;#xE5; branscher l&amp;#xE4;r det finnas s&amp;#xE5; m&amp;#xE5;nga &amp;quot;tjejklubbar&amp;quot; som i it-branschen. Jag v&amp;#xE5;gar p&amp;#xE5;st&amp;#xE5; att en tjej som programmerar kommer alltid g&amp;#xE5; f&amp;#xF6;re en kille med samma, och ofta till och med h&amp;#xF6;gre, kompetens i rekryteringssituationer. M&amp;#xE5;nga f&amp;#xF6;retag har uttalade m&amp;#xE5;l om att &amp;#xF6;ka andelen kvinnor, vilket f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5;s g&amp;#xF6;r att det blir lite av en huggsexa om de kvinnor som finns i branschen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men det kanske beh&amp;#xF6;vs, f&amp;#xF6;r att kompensera f&amp;#xF6;r all grabbighet som skr&amp;#xE4;mmer bort tjejer. Jag vet inte. Men jag har sv&amp;#xE5;rt att tro att tjejer v&amp;#xE4;ljer bort programmering p&amp;#xE5; grund av att risken att beh&amp;#xF6;va &amp;#xE5;ka gokart med sina kollegor ist&amp;#xE4;llet f&amp;#xF6;r att ha sing-a-long med Martin Stenmark, eller vad man nu g&amp;#xF6;r p&amp;#xE5; f&amp;#xF6;retagsfester i andra brancher. Kanske &amp;#xE4;r det flipperspelet p&amp;#xE5; kontoret som skr&amp;#xE4;mmer bort kvinnorna?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sexism finns inom IT. Absolut. Men v&amp;#xE4;rre &amp;#xE4;n i n&amp;#xE5;gon annan bransch? Tveksamt. &lt;a href=&quot;http://laurasanders.net/a-primer-on-sexism-in-the-tech-industry-by-an-actual-girl/&quot;&gt;Vissa upplever inget s&amp;#xE5;dant&lt;/a&gt;, andra st&amp;#xF6;ter p&amp;#xE5; s&amp;#xE5;v&amp;#xE4;l gubbfasoner som f&amp;#xF6;rutfattade meningar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag tror knappt att det finns n&amp;#xE5;gon i it-branschen som inte vill se att fler tjejer s&amp;#xF6;ker sig hit, och jag tror ocks&amp;#xE5; att f&amp;#xF6;retag s&amp;#xE5;v&amp;#xE4;l som individer &amp;#xE4;r mer v&amp;#xE4;lkomnande mot kvinnor &amp;#xE4;n i andra branscher. F&amp;#xF6;retagen skriker efter arbetskraft och v&amp;#xE4;ldigt f&amp;#xE5; g&amp;#xE5;r arbetsl&amp;#xF6;sa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#xD6;verlag tycker jag att de saker som g&amp;#xF6;rs f&amp;#xF6;r att locka kvinnor till it-branschen &amp;#xE4;r bra och jag tror att vi &amp;#xE4;r p&amp;#xE5; r&amp;#xE4;tt v&amp;#xE4;g. Det g&amp;#xE4;ller dock att vara f&amp;#xF6;rsiktig s&amp;#xE5; att man inte stirrar sig blind p&amp;#xE5; vad folk har mellan benen. Om andra saker &amp;#xE4;n folks kompetens f&amp;#xE5;r styra har vi tappat det b&amp;#xE4;sta med it-branschen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det h&amp;#xE4;r &amp;#xE4;r ett j&amp;#xE4;ttespretigt inl&amp;#xE4;gg. N&amp;#xE5;gon annan g&amp;#xE5;ng kanske jag kommer skriva mer strukturerat i &amp;#xE4;mnet. Det jag egentligen ville ha sagt var att det &amp;#xE4;r h&amp;#xF6;g tid att &amp;#xF6;verge ytliga analyser. Vi kan b&amp;#xE4;ttre.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >En gammal mobildesign</title><id >aengammalmobildesign2012-08-13t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/en-gammal-mobildesign"></link><updated >2012-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;N&amp;#xE4;r jag gick p&amp;#xE5; gymnasiet fick vi i uppgift att designa en mobiltelefon. De flesta designade mer eller mindre fantasifulla rymdskepp. Detta var &amp;#xE5;r 2002, jag hade precis k&amp;#xF6;pt en &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gsmarena.com/nokia_8210-19.php&quot;&gt;Nokia 8210&lt;/a&gt;, som d&amp;#xE5; var bland det coolaste som fanns. Personligen dr&amp;#xF6;mde jag &amp;#xE4;nnu mer om den kromblanka &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gsmarena.com/nokia_8810-20.php&quot;&gt;Nokia 8810&lt;/a&gt; och &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gsmarena.com/sony_cmd_j5-201.php&quot;&gt;Sonys CMD J5&lt;/a&gt; (det h&amp;#xE4;r var allts&amp;#xE5; innan SonyEricsson-tiden).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men jag var redan d&amp;#xE5; en riktig sucker f&amp;#xF6;r minimalism och ville designa n&amp;#xE5;got v&amp;#xE4;ldigt enkelt. Min design blev n&amp;#xE4;stan helt fyrkantig, i matt metall (se bilden ovan). Magistern s&amp;#xE5;gade den totalt, och sa att en mobil m&amp;#xE5;ste ha former. Han tyckte ocks&amp;#xE5; att det var att &amp;quot;smita undan&amp;quot; att g&amp;#xF6;ra n&amp;#xE5;got med en s&amp;#xE5; enkel design. Jag f&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xF6;kte k&amp;#xE4;fta emot men jag ins&amp;#xE5;g snart att det bara skulle leda till ett IG, s&amp;#xE5; jag &amp;#xE4;ndrade mitt f&amp;#xF6;rslag, ritade till en liten bulle runt sk&amp;#xE4;rmen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kommer ih&amp;#xE5;g att jag hoppades att n&amp;#xE5;got f&amp;#xF6;retag skulle sl&amp;#xE4;ppa en s&amp;#xE5;dan telefon som den jag hade gjort ursprungligen, n&amp;#xE5;got v&amp;#xE4;ldigt enkelt och avskalat, f&amp;#xF6;r att jag trodde den skule vara v&amp;#xE4;ldigt trevlig att anv&amp;#xE4;nda och f&amp;#xF6;r att det skulle ge mig r&amp;#xE4;tt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Av n&amp;#xE5;gon anledning b&amp;#xF6;rjar jag t&amp;#xE4;nka p&amp;#xE5; den h&amp;#xE4;r lilla episoden varje g&amp;#xE5;ng jag l&amp;#xE4;ser om Apple vs. Samsung. Inte f&amp;#xF6;r att min design p&amp;#xE5; n&amp;#xE5;got s&amp;#xE4;tt liknar det som Apple skulle komma att sl&amp;#xE4;ppa fyra &amp;#xE5;r senare, utan f&amp;#xF6;r att det enklaste jag kunde t&amp;#xE4;nka mig, det som var alldeles f&amp;#xF6;r simplistiskt f&amp;#xF6;r min l&amp;#xE4;rare, var s&amp;#xE5; otroligt mycket mer komplicerat &amp;#xE4;n vad det beh&amp;#xF6;vde vara. Och f&amp;#xF6;r att vi alla var s&amp;#xE5; fast i f&amp;#xF6;rest&amp;#xE4;llningen av vad en mobiltelefon var.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Det r ngot skevt med nyheter p ntet.</title><id >adetarnagotskevtmednyheterpanatet2012-04-22t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/det-r-ngot-skevt-med-nyheter-p-ntet"></link><updated >2012-04-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;F&amp;#xF6;r n&amp;#xE5;gra m&amp;#xE5;nader sedan startade gruppbloggen Ajour, efter att en hyfsat stor twitterhype hade byggts upp. Det &amp;#xE4;r v&amp;#xE4;l synd att s&amp;#xE4;ga att Ajour har levt upp till de stora orden som ackompanjerade lanseringen. Men det som faktiskt h&amp;#xE4;nde var att en liten diskussion om journalisters och nyhetsmediers f&amp;#xF6;r&amp;#xE4;ndrade roll br&amp;#xF6;t ut. Och jag b&amp;#xF6;rjade fundera p&amp;#xE5; hur mediekonsumtion p&amp;#xE5; internet har sett ut, och hur den kan komma att se ut fram&amp;#xF6;ver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I begynnelsen.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionella dagstidningar var tidiga med att starta webbplatser. F&amp;#xF6;rst var Aftonbladet, &amp;#xE5;r 1996. D&amp;#xE5; s&amp;#xE5;g deras hemsida ut &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/19961023235430/http://www.aftonbladet.se/&quot;&gt;s&amp;#xE5; h&amp;#xE4;r&lt;/a&gt;. Den observante noterar att det faktiskt inte har h&amp;#xE4;nt s&amp;#xE4;rskilt mycket i sajtens struktur eller funktionalitet. Den har v&amp;#xE4;xt p&amp;#xE5; bredden i takt med att den normala datorsk&amp;#xE4;rmen har blivit st&amp;#xF6;rre, och nu finns ett kommentarsf&amp;#xE4;lt och kanske lite bloggl&amp;#xE4;nkar ist&amp;#xE4;llet f&amp;#xF6;r en g&amp;#xE4;stbok. &amp;#xC4;ven annonserna har v&amp;#xE4;xt, s&amp;#xE5;v&amp;#xE4;l till storlek som till antal. Har vi tur f&amp;#xE5;r vi nu f&amp;#xF6;r tiden med ett bildspel eller kanske en filmsnutt i anslutning till artikeln. Men i grunden presenteras nyheterna p&amp;#xE5; samma s&amp;#xE4;tt idag som f&amp;#xF6;r sexton &amp;#xE5;r sedan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artikeln, omsluten av stora m&amp;#xE4;ngder annonser och puffar f&amp;#xF6;r annat material, det mesta helt orelaterat till artikeln jag l&amp;#xE4;ser. Det &amp;#xE4;r konceptet som har varit oomstridd standard p&amp;#xE5; webbtidningar de senaste sexton &amp;#xE5;ren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sexton &amp;#xE5;r &amp;#xE4;r v&amp;#xE4;ldigt l&amp;#xE5;ng tid p&amp;#xE5; internet. F&amp;#xF6;r sexton &amp;#xE5;r sedan fanns inte Facebook, Youtube, Google, Twitter, iPhone, Napster, Skype, Blocket&amp;#x2026; Inget av det vi idag tar f&amp;#xF6;r givet p&amp;#xE5; internet var tillg&amp;#xE4;ngligt, och m&amp;#xE5;nga tj&amp;#xE4;nster har kommit och g&amp;#xE5;tt. Utvecklingen har g&amp;#xE5;tt i en rasande fart. Men nyhetssajterna best&amp;#xE5;r. Of&amp;#xF6;r&amp;#xE4;ndrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Betyder det att webbtidningarna gjorde allt r&amp;#xE4;tt fr&amp;#xE5;n b&amp;#xF6;rjan? Njae. Till&amp;#xE5;t mig att tvivla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Varf&amp;#xF6;r ser det ut som det g&amp;#xF6;r?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sin st&amp;#xE4;llning som ledande medier p&amp;#xE5; internet har de f&amp;#xE5;tt till sk&amp;#xE4;nks, av urminnes h&amp;#xE4;vd. De har varit &amp;#xF6;verl&amp;#xE4;gsna p&amp;#xE5; inneh&amp;#xE5;ll och har haft ensamr&amp;#xE4;tt p&amp;#xE5; presentationen av sitt inneh&amp;#xE5;ll De har aldrig beh&amp;#xF6;vt konkurrera med struktur. S&amp;#xE5; l&amp;#xE4;nge de uppdaterar detaljer p&amp;#xE5; designen n&amp;#xE5;gon g&amp;#xE5;ng d&amp;#xE5; och d&amp;#xE5; bryr sig ingen om att det inte sker n&amp;#xE5;gon riktig utveckling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ett stort problem som aktivt f&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xE4;mrar webbtidningarna &amp;#xE4;r de betalningsmodeller f&amp;#xF6;r annonser som dominerar. De flesta annonser s&amp;#xE4;ljs per visning. Det g&amp;#xF6;r att tidningarna kl&amp;#xE4;mmer in s&amp;#xE5; m&amp;#xE5;nga annonser som m&amp;#xF6;jligt p&amp;#xE5; varje sida. Om de ist&amp;#xE4;llet skulle ha st&amp;#xF6;rre m&amp;#xF6;jlighet att ta betalt per klick, eller n&amp;#xE5;got annat effektm&amp;#xE5;l, skulle allt st&amp;#xF6;rre incitament uppst&amp;#xE5; f&amp;#xF6;r att visa r&amp;#xE4;tt annonser f&amp;#xF6;r r&amp;#xE4;tt personer vid r&amp;#xE4;tt tidpunkt, snarare &amp;#xE4;n att visa s&amp;#xE5; m&amp;#xE5;nga annonser som m&amp;#xF6;jligt, j&amp;#xE4;mt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Vart &amp;#xE4;r vi p&amp;#xE5; v&amp;#xE4;g?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vill man l&amp;#xE4;sa engelskspr&amp;#xE5;kiga artiklar finns det ganska gott om alternativ. Flipboard, Zite och Google Currents &amp;#xE4;r exempel p&amp;#xE5; tj&amp;#xE4;nster som ger riktigt bra digitala l&amp;#xE4;supplevelser. D&amp;#xE4;r samsas material fr&amp;#xE5;n m&amp;#xE5;nga olika k&amp;#xE4;llor, nyhetstidningar, bloggar sociala n&amp;#xE4;tverk &amp;#x2013; alla f&amp;#xE5;r vara med p&amp;#xE5; samma villkor. S&amp;#xE5;dana tj&amp;#xE4;nster kommer naturligtvis &amp;#xE4;ven att anpassas f&amp;#xF6;r den svenska marknaden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag &amp;#xE4;r &amp;#xF6;vertygad om att de svenska nyhetsmediernas st&amp;#xE5;lbad inte har b&amp;#xF6;rjat &amp;#xE4;n. &amp;#xC4;n s&amp;#xE5; l&amp;#xE4;nge l&amp;#xE4;ser de flesta sin papperstidning, men s&amp;#xE5; kommer det inte att se ut om n&amp;#xE5;gra &amp;#xE5;r. Gigantiska f&amp;#xF6;r&amp;#xE4;ndringar &amp;#xE4;r p&amp;#xE5; g&amp;#xE5;ng och de som nu &amp;#xE4;r herre p&amp;#xE5; t&amp;#xE4;ppan kommer att f&amp;#xE5; stora problem att beh&amp;#xE5;lla sin st&amp;#xE4;llning. Att klara &amp;#xF6;verg&amp;#xE5;ngen fr&amp;#xE5;n papperstidning till digital distribution &amp;#xE4;r ingen liten utmaning. N&amp;#xE4;r vi slutar l&amp;#xE4;sa nyheter p&amp;#xE5; papper kommer vi dessutom att st&amp;#xE4;lla radikalt annorlunda krav p&amp;#xE5; l&amp;#xE4;supplevelsen. Det ska bli sp&amp;#xE4;nnande att se vilka som klarar av att leva upp till de kraven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Har ni &amp;#xE5;sikter vill jag g&amp;#xE4;rna h&amp;#xF6;ra dem. F&amp;#xF6;rslagsvis p&amp;#xE5; Twitter (@eldh).&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Eldhs lag</title><id >aeldhslag2012-02-08t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/eldhs-lag"></link><updated >2012-02-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;D&amp;#xE5; en Usenetdiskussion blir l&amp;#xE4;ngre, g&amp;#xE5;r sannolikheten f&amp;#xF6;r att en j&amp;#xE4;mf&amp;#xF6;relse g&amp;#xF6;rs som involverar nazister eller Hitler mot ett&amp;quot; - Mike Godwin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Godwins lag &amp;#xE4;r ett v&amp;#xE4;lk&amp;#xE4;nt och st&amp;#xE4;ndigt aktuellt fenomen. Inte minst en dag som denna, d&amp;#xE5; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dn.se/kultur-noje/debatt-essa/hatet-som-gor-mig-politiskt-deprimerad&quot;&gt;Maria Sveland satte nytt svenskt Godwin-rekord i dagens DN&lt;/a&gt;, genom att f&amp;#xF6;rst referera till nazister och sedan referera till Anders Bering Breivik (den &amp;quot;nya Hitler&amp;quot; i Godwin-sammanhang) inte mindre &amp;#xE4;n sju g&amp;#xE5;nger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men det jag  har t&amp;#xE4;nkt p&amp;#xE5; &amp;#xE4;r inversen av Godwins lag, som &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dn.se/debatt/wallenbergs-anda-finns-inte-i-riksdagen&quot;&gt;Carl B Hamilton s&amp;#xE5; vackert exemplifierade ig&amp;#xE5;r&lt;/a&gt;, n&amp;#xE4;mligen de fall d&amp;#xE4;r debatten i st&amp;#xE4;llet f&amp;#xF6;r att handla om Hitler slutar i ett &amp;quot;Vad skulle Jesus g&amp;#xF6;ra?&amp;quot;. Logiken &amp;#xE4;r den samma: I brist p&amp;#xE5; argument tar man till en k&amp;#xE4;nd person med starkt symbolv&amp;#xE4;rde f&amp;#xF6;r att f&amp;#xE5; fram en po&amp;#xE4;ng. Ist&amp;#xE4;llet f&amp;#xF6;r Jesus kan man dra till med vilken helgonf&amp;#xF6;rklarad person som helst &amp;#x2013; Nelson Mandela, Moder Teresa, Martin Luther King, Olof Palme eller som Hamilton valde, Raul Wallenberg. Skillnaden &amp;#xE4;r endast att man ist&amp;#xE4;llet f&amp;#xF6;r att smutskasta en meningsmotst&amp;#xE5;ndare f&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xF6;ker grorifiera sig sj&amp;#xE4;lv.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Detta &amp;#xE4;r en styggelse, som m&amp;#xE5;ste bek&amp;#xE4;mpas med alla tillg&amp;#xE4;ngliga medel. Precis som anv&amp;#xE4;ndande av Hitler- och Breivik-referenser b&amp;#xF6;r diskvalificera g&amp;#xE4;rningsm&amp;#xE4;n fr&amp;#xE5;n vidare samtal, b&amp;#xF6;r &amp;#xE4;ven Jesus-referenserna rensas ut fr&amp;#xE5;n v&amp;#xE5;ra debattsidor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;D&amp;#xE5; en diskussion blir l&amp;#xE4;ngre, g&amp;#xE5;r sannolikheten f&amp;#xF6;r att en j&amp;#xE4;mf&amp;#xF6;relse g&amp;#xF6;rs som involverar Jesus eller andra helgonfigurer mot ett&amp;quot; - Andreas Eldh&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Din senste krnika kan suga en kasse kukar</title><id >adinsenstekronikakansugaenkassekukar2012-01-03t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/din-senste-krnika-kan-suga-en-kasse-kukar"></link><updated >2012-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I mitt twitterfl&amp;#xF6;de d&amp;#xF6;k f&amp;#xF6;ljande upp f&amp;#xF6;r n&amp;#xE5;gon dag sedan: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/#!/lisamagnusson/status/152370134835662848&quot;&gt;&amp;apos;facebooks nya &amp;quot;tidslinje&amp;quot; kan f &amp;#xF6; ocks&amp;#xE5; g&amp;#xE5; och suga en kasse kukar&amp;apos;&lt;/a&gt;. Att folk har starka &amp;#xE5;sikter om teknik &amp;#xE4;r sannerligen inget ovanligt. Det som d&amp;#xE4;remot &amp;#xE4;r ovanligt &amp;#xE4;r v&amp;#xE4;l formulerad och underbyggd kritik mot tekniken. I 99 fall av 100 stannar det vid just s&amp;#xE5;dana korta, ofta mycket grova, s&amp;#xE5;gningar. Vanligtvis inget man skulle f&amp;#xE4;sta n&amp;#xE5;gon s&amp;#xE4;rskild vikt vid. Men jag fastnade vid just den h&amp;#xE4;r tweeten, som skrevs av en person som jobbar med att formulera &amp;#xE5;sikter och som sannerligen inte skulle uttrycka sig s&amp;#xE5; om n&amp;#xE5;gon text som hon starkt ogillade. N&amp;#xE4;, inte ens de som uttryckligen kallar Lisa Magnusson f&amp;#xF6;r hora ber hon att suga en endaste liten kuk. Hade uttalandet g&amp;#xE4;llt en text, ett konstverk eller ett musikaliskt verk hade det betraktats som ett mycket grovt, sakl&amp;#xF6;st angrepp. Men nu handlade det om mjukvara och d&amp;#xE4;rf&amp;#xF6;r h&amp;#xF6;jer ingen ett &amp;#xF6;gonbryn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det h&amp;#xE4;r &amp;#xE4;r ett ganska vanligt problem, och jag skulle vilja h&amp;#xE4;vda att det &amp;#xE4;r en av grundorsakerna till att vi har ganska mycket d&amp;#xE5;liga system omkring oss. Folk bryr sig helt enkelt inte om att f&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xF6;ka f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5; systemen alls, utan agerar som hj&amp;#xE4;rnd&amp;#xF6;da flashbacktroll och kastar ur sig f&amp;#xF6;rsta b&amp;#xE4;sta invektiv. Om vi som faktiskt bygger och designar system stod upp f&amp;#xF6;r dem och kr&amp;#xE4;vde v&amp;#xE4;l underbyggda argument f&amp;#xF6;r varf&amp;#xF6;r v&amp;#xE5;ra system ska suga p&amp;#xE5;sar med manslemmar skulle vi dels bespara oss en massa skitsnack och dels skulle vi kunna f&amp;#xE5; ig&amp;#xE5;ng en konstruktiv diskussion om hur den teknik som vi anv&amp;#xE4;nder dagligen faktiskt fungerar. Men nu f&amp;#xF6;rs diskussionen p&amp;#xE5; samma niv&amp;#xE5; som mellan AFA och svenskarnas parti. Det &amp;#xE4;r inte en s&amp;#xE4;rskilt bra milj&amp;#xF6;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S&amp;#xE5; k&amp;#xE4;ra mediam&amp;#xE4;nniskor och &amp;#xF6;vriga twitterati, n&amp;#xE4;r ni kritiserar teknik, t&amp;#xE4;nk er att ni kritiserar n&amp;#xE5;gons senaste kr&amp;#xF6;nika. Det sitter m&amp;#xE4;nniskor p&amp;#xE5; andra sidan, inte helt olika er, och f&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xF6;ker g&amp;#xF6;ra s&amp;#xE5; bra tekniska l&amp;#xF6;sningar som vi bara kan, som vi hoppas att ni ska tycka om. Precis som ni vill vi h&amp;#xF6;ra konstruktiv, sansad kritik p&amp;#xE5; det vi g&amp;#xF6;r. T&amp;#xE4;nk igenom era argument och formulera er d&amp;#xE4;refter.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Ajour</title><id >aajour2011-10-24t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/ajour"></link><updated >2011-10-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Alla &amp;#xE4;r journalister&amp;quot;. Det &amp;#xE4;r meningen som har fastnat i folks medvetande efter att &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ajour.se&quot;&gt;Ajour&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#xF6;ppnade d&amp;#xF6;rrarna f&amp;#xF6;rra veckan. En ny sorts journalistik, d&amp;#xE4;r alla f&amp;#xE5;r vara med och skapa, verkar vara id&amp;#xE9;n. Bakom sajten st&amp;#xE5;r n&amp;#xE5;gra sociala medier-veteraner, bland andra Emanuel Karlsten och Damon Rasti.
Jag uppskattar tanken. D&amp;#xE4;r tar dock mitt uppskattande slut. Mer om det snart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sj&amp;#xE4;lv har jag kastat ut s&amp;#xE5;v&amp;#xE4;l tv:n som tidningarna och f&amp;#xE5;r nu st&amp;#xF6;rre delen av mitt nyhetsfl&amp;#xF6;de via twitter, facebook, v&amp;#xE4;l valda bloggar och en del fr&amp;#xE5;n gammelmedias mediasajter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.expressen.se/kultur/1.2595997/hall-i-ratten&quot;&gt;Jan Gradvall kallar&lt;/a&gt; Ajour-g&amp;#xE4;nget f&amp;#xF6;r gratis&amp;#xE5;kare och beklagar den riktiga journalismens n&amp;#xE4;ra f&amp;#xF6;rest&amp;#xE5;ende d&amp;#xF6;d. &amp;#xC4;ven &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.expressen.se/ledare/1.2596979/fredrik-krohnman-alla-ar-inte-journalister&quot;&gt;Fredrik Krohnman st&amp;#xE4;mmer in i s&amp;#xE5;gningsk&amp;#xF6;ren&lt;/a&gt; och hyllar den &amp;#xE4;kta journalistiken, som st&amp;#xE5;r upp f&amp;#xF6;r sanning, saklighet och objektivitet, detta allts&amp;#xE5; veckan efter Aftonbladet hittade p&amp;#xE5; ett regelverk som de sedan p&amp;#xE5;stod att H&amp;#xE5;kan Juholt hade brutit mot&amp;#x2026; Jag l&amp;#xE4;mnar &amp;#xF6;ppet f&amp;#xF6;r en stunds tystnad medan resterna av glashuset klirrar klart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De b&amp;#xE4;gge herrarna &amp;#xE4;r hur som helst inte ensamma. Ajour verkar inte f&amp;#xE5;tt n&amp;#xE5;got direkt lysande mottagande. Och kritiken h&amp;#xE5;ller ungef&amp;#xE4;r samma ton som herrarna Gradvall och Krohnman slagit an.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journalisternas roll &amp;#xE4;r m&amp;#xE5;ngfacetterad, men en stor del best&amp;#xE5;r i att vara p&amp;#xE5; r&amp;#xE4;tt st&amp;#xE4;lle, samt att ha kanaler och utrustning f&amp;#xF6;r att skicka rapporter fr&amp;#xE5;n detta st&amp;#xE4;lle. Nu har i princip alla med sig utrustning f&amp;#xF6;r att rapportera och till viss del finns &amp;#xE4;ven kanalerna - twitter, facebook etc. D&amp;#xE4;remot &amp;#xE4;r det v&amp;#xE4;ldigt sv&amp;#xE5;rt f&amp;#xF6;r vanligt folk att s&amp;#xE5;lla i den forsande floden av rapporter. Informationen finns, men man kan inte f&amp;#xE5; tag p&amp;#xE5; den. Den kommer f&amp;#xF6;r snabbt och den &amp;#xE4;r g&amp;#xF6;md i en massa irrelevant skr&amp;#xE4;p.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag vill h&amp;#xE4;vda att Ajours problem &amp;#xE4;r ett helt annat &amp;#xE4;n vad de flesta av deras kritiker vill g&amp;#xF6;ra g&amp;#xE4;llande. Ajour har kanske insett att det finns intressant inneh&amp;#xE5;ll i de sociala medierna, men de har inte hittat n&amp;#xE5;got s&amp;#xE4;tt att visa upp det inneh&amp;#xE5;llet. Ist&amp;#xE4;llet f&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xF6;ker de skapa nyheter av interna twitter- och kommentarsf&amp;#xE4;ltsdiskussioner. Det &amp;#xE4;r s&amp;#xE5; navelsk&amp;#xE5;dande att man baxnar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;V&amp;#xE5;r tids st&amp;#xF6;rsta fr&amp;#xE5;ga &amp;#xE4;r &amp;quot;vad h&amp;#xE4;nder?&amp;quot;, v&amp;#xE5;rt intresse ligger i nuet, men vi har inte verktygen f&amp;#xF6;r att f&amp;#xE5; svar p&amp;#xE5; fr&amp;#xE5;gan. Gammelmedia kommer bara att kunna svara p&amp;#xE5; fr&amp;#xE5;gan &amp;quot;vad h&amp;#xE4;nde?&amp;quot; och de sociala medierna kommer bara kunna svara om r&amp;#xE4;tt person fr&amp;#xE5;gar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D&amp;#xE5;den i Norge i somras var ett tillf&amp;#xE4;lle d&amp;#xE5; twitter visade sin styrka. Mitt fl&amp;#xF6;de fylldes med information som inte hittade ut i andra medier f&amp;#xF6;rr&amp;#xE4;n l&amp;#xE5;ng tid senare. Allt fr&amp;#xE5;n Moderaternas st&amp;#xE4;mma till Lady Gagas frisyrbyten kommenteras p&amp;#xE5; samma s&amp;#xE4;tt p&amp;#xE5; twitter och i bloggar. Snabbt dynamiskt, insiktsfullt, interaktivt och kvalitativt. Fr&amp;#xE5;gan &amp;#xE4;r bara hur man g&amp;#xF6;r denna upplevelse tillg&amp;#xE4;nglig f&amp;#xF6;r den breda massan, som inte har tid, ork eller lust att f&amp;#xF6;lja 200 personer p&amp;#xE5; twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ajour f&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xF6;ker inte svara p&amp;#xE5; den fr&amp;#xE5;gan. Ajour &amp;#xE4;r inte till f&amp;#xF6;r n&amp;#xE5;gon annan &amp;#xE4;n sociala medier-entusiaster. Tyv&amp;#xE4;rr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F&amp;#xF6;r vi beh&amp;#xF6;ver fler spelare i medielandskapet. Vi beh&amp;#xF6;ver mediekanaler som bryter ny mark, som t&amp;#xE4;nker nytt b&amp;#xE5;de journalistiskt och tekniskt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men ge mig en miljon och ett halv&amp;#xE5;r, och jag ska ge er framtidens tidning.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Slutet p Photoshop-eran</title><id >aslutetpaphotoshoperan2011-09-13t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/slutet-p-photoshop-eran"></link><updated >2011-09-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;L&amp;#xE4;ste &lt;a href=&quot;http://lukesbeard.com/posts/zerply-frontend/&quot;&gt;den h&amp;#xE4;r texten av Luke Beard&lt;/a&gt;, om hur han har jobbat n&amp;#xE4;r han designar &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zerply.com&quot;&gt;Zerply&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#x2014; en text som jag i h&amp;#xF6;gsta grad rekommenderar f&amp;#xF6;r alla med intresse f&amp;#xF6;r design eller webutveckling. Och det slog mig att en era i designhistorien &amp;#xE4;r &amp;#xF6;ver. Photoshop &amp;#xE4;r d&amp;#xF6;tt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F&amp;#xF6;r bara n&amp;#xE5;got &amp;#xE5;r sedan designades hemsidor helt och h&amp;#xE5;llet i Photoshop (eller kanske Illustrator) och sedan fick en kodapa i uppdrag att pixel f&amp;#xF6;r pixel &amp;#xF6;verf&amp;#xF6;ra .psd-filen till html och css, trots att produkten aldrig varit s&amp;#xE4;rskilt v&amp;#xE4;l anpassad f&amp;#xF6;r det (f&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xF6;k skapa en animerad .gif i PS p&amp;#xE5; ett smidigt s&amp;#xE4;tt om du kan). Skuggor, knappar, texter, bakgrunder; allt gjordes i Photoshop. Nu kan allt g&amp;#xF6;ras med CSS, och vill man g&amp;#xF6;ra designer som fungerar f&amp;#xF6;r flera plattformar, med olika pixeldensitet, blir pixelkavlande snabbt frustrerande.  En designer som vill g&amp;#xF6;ra ett bra jobb m&amp;#xE5;ste ha bra koll p&amp;#xE5; CSS och exempelvis jQuery. Framtiden finns i webbl&amp;#xE4;saren. Den grafiken som finns kvar blir ocks&amp;#xE5; i st&amp;#xF6;rre utstr&amp;#xE4;ckning vektorbaserad allt eftersom .svg-filer blir mer och mer vanliga, vilket g&amp;#xF6;r att &amp;#xE4;ven Illustrator vinner mark mot sin pixel&amp;#xE4;lskande bror.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foton har ocks&amp;#xE5; varit Photoshops dom&amp;#xE4;n i stor utstr&amp;#xE4;ckning. Det &amp;#xE4;r nog inte bara en hemmapappa som har tankat ned Photoshop fr&amp;#xE5;n piratbukten och sedan bara anv&amp;#xE4;nt det till att besk&amp;#xE4;ra bilder. Program som Picasa, iPhoto och &amp;#xE4;ven mer seri&amp;#xF6;sa fotohanteringsprogram som Aperture och Adobes eget Lightroom, samt f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5;s Instagram, Hipstamatic och resten av mobilboomen, har gjort att bara ett tappert f&amp;#xE5;tal sitter med semesterfotografierna i Photoshop fortfarande.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sj&amp;#xE4;lvklart kommer Photoshop inte upph&amp;#xF6;ra att existera. D&amp;#xE4;remot kommer det att &amp;#xE5;terg&amp;#xE5; till att anv&amp;#xE4;ndas till de saker som det &amp;#xE4;r riktigt bra p&amp;#xE5;: avancerad fotoredigering och avancerad pixelgrafik. D&amp;#xE4;r &amp;#xE4;r det b&amp;#xE4;st och l&amp;#xE4;r s&amp;#xE5; f&amp;#xF6;rbli ett tag till (&amp;#xE4;ven om program som &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pixelmator.com&quot;&gt;Pixelmator&lt;/a&gt; och webbaserade alternativ som &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aviary.com/&quot;&gt;aviary&lt;/a&gt; kommer att finna sin plats p&amp;#xE5; marknaden).&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Gldjeddarna</title><id >agladjedodarna2011-07-29t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/gldjeddarna"></link><updated >2011-07-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mattias Svensson tar i den ambiti&amp;#xF6;sa debattboken Gl&amp;#xE4;djed&amp;#xF6;darna sig an det s&amp;#xE5; kallade f&amp;#xF6;rmynderiet. Boken &amp;#xE4;r en kompromissl&amp;#xF6;s uppg&amp;#xF6;relse med regleringar, f&amp;#xF6;rbud, skatter och allt annat som syftar till att styra v&amp;#xE5;ra fria val i n&amp;#xE5;gon godtycklig riktning. Den tar sin b&amp;#xF6;rjan i hans fars kamp f&amp;#xF6;r att driva diskotek, med danstillst&amp;#xE5;nd och alkoholrestriktioner och ber&amp;#xE4;ttar vidare om moralister i alla dess former &amp;#x2013; deras m&amp;#xE5;l, medel och metoder. I det stora hela &amp;#xE4;r boken mycket balanserad, v&amp;#xE4;lskriven och genomt&amp;#xE4;nkt, och den smular f&amp;#xF6;rtj&amp;#xE4;nstfullt s&amp;#xF6;nder m&amp;#xE5;nga av f&amp;#xF6;rmyndarnas argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men n&amp;#xE4;r det blir komplicerat g&amp;#xF6;r Svensson det enkelt f&amp;#xF6;r sig. Och komplicerat blir det, framf&amp;#xF6;rallt n&amp;#xE4;r man diskuterar gr&amp;#xE4;nserna f&amp;#xF6;r det fria valet. P&amp;#xE5; den filosofiskt intressanta fr&amp;#xE5;gan om man ska vara till&amp;#xE5;ten att s&amp;#xE4;lja sig sj&amp;#xE4;lv som slav landar Svensson i ett kategoriskt &amp;quot;nej&amp;quot;. Det &amp;#xE4;r dock intressant att han inte tar med sig detta st&amp;#xE4;llningstagande till exempelvis debatten om drogf&amp;#xF6;rbud. F&amp;#xF6;r n&amp;#xE4;r man har fastnat i ett missbruk av tunga droger kan man inte anses ha mycket kvar av sin fria vilja - man &amp;#xE4;r fast i missbruket. Ist&amp;#xE4;llet dividerar han om statistik p&amp;#xE5; hur m&amp;#xE5;nga som lyckas ta sig ur missbruk, vilket inte &amp;#xE4;r &amp;#xF6;verdrivet m&amp;#xE5;nga. Hur man ska hantera de som har fastnat i sitt missbruk utan m&amp;#xF6;jlighet att ta sig ur f&amp;#xE5;r vi inte n&amp;#xE5;gra f&amp;#xF6;rslag p&amp;#xE5;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det finns all anledning att vara kritisk till drogpolitiken som den ser ut idag, inte minst det katastrofala kriget mot droger. D&amp;#xE4;remot kan man inte l&amp;#xE4;mna debatten efter att detta konstaterande. En drogpolitik &amp;#xE4;r och kommer vara n&amp;#xF6;dv&amp;#xE4;ndig. I detta sammanhang skulle det vara mycket intressant att diskutera exempelvis tv&amp;#xE5;ngsv&amp;#xE5;rd, subutexprogram, LVM-hem och andra drogpolitiska &amp;#xE5;tg&amp;#xE4;rder som faller utanf&amp;#xF6;r f&amp;#xF6;rbudsf&amp;#xE5;llan. Men det blir s&amp;#xE4;kert tid f&amp;#xF6;r den debatten n&amp;#xE5;gon annanstans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Den filosofiska fr&amp;#xE5;gan om huruvida man ska f&amp;#xE5; s&amp;#xE4;lja sitt fria val l&amp;#xE4;mnar mig dock inte. Det minimala antalet som skulle kunna t&amp;#xE4;nkas g&amp;#xF6;ra detta helt &amp;#xF6;ppet &amp;#xE4;r inte problemet. Problemet &amp;#xE4;r att folk via sina val kommer att f&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xE4;tta sig i situationer d&amp;#xE4;r deras fria vilja &amp;#xE4;r borta. S&amp;#xE5;ld, s&amp;#xF6;nderknarkad eller vad det vara m&amp;#xE5;nde. Kanske av f&amp;#xF6;rsumbarhet, kanske av okunnighet, kanske av sj&amp;#xE4;lvdestruktivitet. Vad blir d&amp;#xE5; svaret? F&amp;#xF6;rbud eller inte? Mot vad i s&amp;#xE5; fall? Vad det &amp;#xE4;n blir, &amp;#xE4;r det inte enkelt.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >&quot;Vanligt sunt frnuft&quot;</title><id >aquotvanligtsuntfornuftquot2011-05-15t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/vanligt-sunt-frnuft"></link><updated >2011-05-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jag ogillar m&amp;#xE5;nga saker, men finns det n&amp;#xE5;got som f&amp;#xE5;r mig att resa ragg lite extra s&amp;#xE5; &amp;#xE4;r det n&amp;#xE4;r n&amp;#xE5;gon yppar orden &amp;quot;vanligt sunt f&amp;#xF6;rnuft&amp;quot;. Inget annat uttryck &amp;#xE4;r samtidigt s&amp;#xE5; fantastiskt inneh&amp;#xE5;llsl&amp;#xF6;st, tvetydigt och missvisande.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sunt f&amp;#xF6;rnuft&amp;quot; anv&amp;#xE4;nds f&amp;#xF6;r att beskriva s&amp;#xE5;dant som man tycker &amp;#xE4;r s&amp;#xE5; sj&amp;#xE4;lvklart att det inte beh&amp;#xF6;ver motiveras, f&amp;#xF6;rklaras eller diskuteras. Samtidigt anv&amp;#xE4;nds det i stort sett uteslutande f&amp;#xF6;r att d&amp;#xF6;ma eller nedv&amp;#xE4;rdera n&amp;#xE5;gon som saknar detta vanliga sunda f&amp;#xF6;rnuft och f&amp;#xF6;ljaktligen har gjort n&amp;#xE5;got som vem som helst hade kunnat lista ut var &amp;quot;r&amp;#xE4;tt&amp;quot;. Om hen bara hade haft lite vanligt sunt f&amp;#xF6;rnuft allts&amp;#xE5;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alla normala, vettiga m&amp;#xE4;nniskor har sunt f&amp;#xF6;rnuft. Om man inte h&amp;#xE5;ller med n&amp;#xE4;r n&amp;#xE5;gon har lagt &amp;quot;sunt-f&amp;#xF6;rnuft&amp;quot;-kortet saknar man uppenbarligen en grundl&amp;#xE4;ggande m&amp;#xE4;nsklig funktion, man har i ett slag f&amp;#xF6;rvandlats fr&amp;#xE5;n en resonerande individ till ett &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dn.se/ledare/kolumner/vad-ar-en-europe&quot;&gt;hj&amp;#xE4;rnd&amp;#xF6;tt monster&lt;/a&gt;. Och allt skulle v&amp;#xE4;l kanske vara i sin ordning om det bara var odiskutabla sj&amp;#xE4;lvklarheter som motiverades med det sunda f&amp;#xF6;rnuftet. S&amp;#xE5;dant som bara de mest extrema flashback-foliehattarna kunde f&amp;#xE5; f&amp;#xF6;r sig att ifr&amp;#xE5;gas&amp;#xE4;tta. Well, vad tror ni det sunda f&amp;#xF6;rnuftet sade om till exempel r&amp;#xE4;ttigheter f&amp;#xF6;r svarta f&amp;#xF6;r 150 &amp;#xE5;r sedan? Hur l&amp;#xE4;nge sedan kunde man med sunt f&amp;#xF6;rnuft r&amp;#xE4;kna ut att homosexualitet &amp;#xE4;r en sjukdom? Att kvinnor inte skulle f&amp;#xE5; r&amp;#xF6;sta? Vad s&amp;#xE4;ger det sunda f&amp;#xF6;rnuftet hos m&amp;#xE4;nniskor i Pakistan, Iran, Kina, Italien, Grekland eller USA? Gissningsvis finns en inte obetydlig diskrepans mellan deras uppfattning av sunt och osunt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det sunda f&amp;#xF6;rnuftet &amp;#xE4;r en urs&amp;#xE4;kt f&amp;#xF6;r att inte t&amp;#xE4;nka. Det &amp;#xE4;r en h&amp;#xE4;nvisning till g&amp;#xE4;llande normer, moral eller &amp;quot;magk&amp;#xE4;nsla&amp;quot;. Det &amp;#xE4;r ett s&amp;#xE4;tt att s&amp;#xE4;ga att man &amp;#xE4;r fullkomligt s&amp;#xE4;ker p&amp;#xE5; sin sak men att man inte har en aning om varf&amp;#xF6;r man har r&amp;#xE4;tt. Det sunda f&amp;#xF6;rnuftet &amp;#xE4;r principl&amp;#xF6;st, fritt flytande och f&amp;#xF6;rdummande. T&amp;#xE4;nk efter innan du h&amp;#xE4;nvisar till det.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Att leva utan iPhone</title><id >aattlevautaniphone2011-04-18t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/att-leva-utan-iphone"></link><updated >2011-04-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Efter en lite oturlig episod f&amp;#xF6;r n&amp;#xE5;gra veckor sedan har jag levt mitt liv utan vad som i dagligt tal kallas &amp;quot;smartphone&amp;quot;. H&amp;#xE4;r f&amp;#xF6;ljer n&amp;#xE5;gra korta tankar om hur detta har p&amp;#xE5;verkat mig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag k&amp;#xF6;pte min iPhone 3GS ganska snart efter att den hade kommit ut, i september 2009. Jag hade just f&amp;#xE5;tt jobb och min gamla Nokia hade b&amp;#xF6;rjat kr&amp;#xE5;ngla. Man kan lugnt s&amp;#xE4;ga att detta f&amp;#xF6;r&amp;#xE4;ndrade mitt liv. Inte s&amp;#xE5; fasligt mycket kanske, men &amp;#xE4;nd&amp;#xE5; m&amp;#xE4;rkbart. Den var min kompanjon med vilken jag konsumerade tweets, bloggar, nyheter och musik, spelade spel, m&amp;#xE4;tte l&amp;#xF6;prundor, tog foton, m&amp;#xE4;tte l&amp;#xF6;prundor och checkade in s&amp;#xE5;v&amp;#xE4;l h&amp;#xE4;r som d&amp;#xE4;r - allt s&amp;#xE5;dant som man inte kan g&amp;#xF6;ra med en &amp;quot;vanlig&amp;quot; telefon. Jag var en riktig iPhone-junkie helt enkelt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19 m&amp;#xE5;nader efter ink&amp;#xF6;pet rycktes den bort fr&amp;#xE5;n mig och jag hade att falla tillbaka p&amp;#xE5; en &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gsmarena.com/sony_ericsson_k750-1090.php&quot;&gt;SonyEricsson K750i&lt;/a&gt;, en riktigt bra telefon n&amp;#xE4;r den introducerades sex &amp;#xE5;r tidigare. Men v&amp;#xE5;ren 2011 g&amp;#xE5;r det inte att komma undan att den k&amp;#xE4;nns n&amp;#xE5;got daterad. Utvecklingen har ju g&amp;#xE5;tt snabbare p&amp;#xE5; mobilmarknaden de senaste fem &amp;#xE5;ren &amp;#xE4;n &lt;a href=&quot;http://eldh.blogsome.com/2009/07/09/nokia-6220-classic-vs-nokia-6230/&quot;&gt;de fem f&amp;#xF6;reg&amp;#xE5;ende&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S&amp;#xE5; vad g&amp;#xF6;r man d&amp;#xE5; n&amp;#xE4;r man vant sig vid att kolla Mail, Twitter, Reeder och Facebook varje tunnelbaneresa, checka in p&amp;#xE5; varje aff&amp;#xE4;r och alltsom oftast g&amp;#xE5; runt med h&amp;#xF6;rlurar i &amp;#xF6;ronen? Det som r&amp;#xE4;ddade min psykiska h&amp;#xE4;lsa de f&amp;#xF6;rsta kritiska dagarna var nog att jag tack vare slumpens nycker precis hade k&amp;#xF6;pt sex mycket l&amp;#xE4;sv&amp;#xE4;rda b&amp;#xF6;cker som jag kunde borra ner n&amp;#xE4;san i p&amp;#xE5; kollektivtrafiken. Att &amp;#xE5;ka buss eller t-bana utan ha n&amp;#xE5;got att l&amp;#xE4;sa ser jag fortfarande som helt ot&amp;#xE4;nkbart. H&amp;#xF6;rlurspluggen fick flytta till den lilla iPod Shuffle jag fick n&amp;#xE4;r jag b&amp;#xF6;rjade mitt nuvarande jobb. Den stora f&amp;#xF6;r&amp;#xE4;ndringen var dock att jag b&amp;#xF6;rjade l&amp;#xE4;sa b&amp;#xF6;cker, samt att jag hade lite mer att ta igen p&amp;#xE5; twitter och i rss-l&amp;#xE4;saren n&amp;#xE4;r jag kom hem varje dag, s&amp;#xE5;dant man vanligtvis fixade p&amp;#xE5; v&amp;#xE4;gen om man hade sin iPhone med sig. Jag rensade ocks&amp;#xE5; ordentligt i rss-listan f&amp;#xF6;r att f&amp;#xE5; ned antalet artiklar per dag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dock m&amp;#xE4;rkte jag snabbt att mycket av de naturliga mikropauser som man har under en dag &amp;#x2014; n&amp;#xE4;r man v&amp;#xE4;ntar p&amp;#xE5; n&amp;#xE5;gon eller n&amp;#xE5;got, i hissen, p&amp;#xE5; bussh&amp;#xE5;llplatsen etc. &amp;#x2014; som jag tidigare &amp;#xE4;gnat &amp;#xE5;t telefonen nu gick &amp;#xE5;t till att v&amp;#xE4;nta, fundera och studera omgivningen. Onekligen blev jag lite mer medveten om min omgivning, p&amp;#xE5; gott och ont. Ibland &amp;#xE4;r det ju ganska sk&amp;#xF6;nt att sjunka in i sig sj&amp;#xE4;lv. Dock var min flickv&amp;#xE4;n glad att jag inte kunde checka in &amp;#xF6;verallt. Och jag uppt&amp;#xE4;ckte till min f&amp;#xF6;rv&amp;#xE5;ning att v&amp;#xE4;rlden inte gick under n&amp;#xE4;r jag inte hade kollat min twitter p&amp;#xE5; en dag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det &amp;#xE4;r lite konstigt, tragiskt skulle man kunna tycka, n&amp;#xE4;r en f&amp;#xF6;rlorad liten pryl leder till en sm&amp;#xE4;rre livskris. Nu kanske det inte var riktigt s&amp;#xE5; illa heller, men lite saker satte det hela &amp;#xE4;nd&amp;#xE5; i perspektiv. En junkie som tar en vit m&amp;#xE5;nad kommer onekligen att komma ut p&amp;#xE5; andra sidan med en del nya insikter i bagaget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nu &amp;#xE4;r jag i alla fall med smartphone igen, en ny Samsung Galaxy Ace. Jag hade v&amp;#xE4;ntat mig att det skulle vara en ganska stor l&amp;#xE4;ttnad att byta bort den gamla Ericsson-luren, men tv&amp;#xE4;rtom k&amp;#xE4;nde jag mig besviken f&amp;#xF6;rsta dygnet. Det beror nog till stor del p&amp;#xE5; att det tar ett tag att komma ig&amp;#xE5;ng med Android. Det &amp;#xE4;r mycket som ska fixas innan man f&amp;#xE5;r det som man vill ha det. Dessutom &amp;#xE4;r luren en budgetmodell som inte direkt &amp;#xE4;r blixtsnabb. Men det berodde ocks&amp;#xE5; p&amp;#xE5; att det inte var s&amp;#xE4;rskilt sp&amp;#xE4;nnande, allt det d&amp;#xE4;r som jag brukade h&amp;#xE5;lla p&amp;#xE5; med.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kanske kommer jag ha ett lite mer distansierat f&amp;#xF6;rh&amp;#xE5;llande till min telefon fram&amp;#xF6;ver. Kanske blir det som f&amp;#xF6;rut igen. N&amp;#xE5;got tror jag dock att jag har l&amp;#xE4;rt mig. Oavsett vilket kommer v&amp;#xE4;rlden att snurra vidare.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Allt r ett system</title><id >aalltarettsystem2011-03-31t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/allt-r-ett-system"></link><updated >2011-03-31T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jag har en god v&amp;#xE4;n som &amp;#xE4;r f&amp;#xF6;rest&amp;#xE5;ndare f&amp;#xF6;r en godisaff&amp;#xE4;r. En fantastisk liten butik med v&amp;#xE4;ggarna fyllda med olika sorters choklad och karameller. Jag var och h&amp;#xE4;lsade p&amp;#xE5; henne i helgen och en tr&amp;#xE5;kig sak h&amp;#xE4;nde. Hon gl&amp;#xF6;mde v&amp;#xE4;rmefl&amp;#xE4;kten p&amp;#xE5; n&amp;#xE4;r vi gick ifr&amp;#xE5;n butiken och godis f&amp;#xF6;r &amp;#xA3;400 f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xF6;rdes. Fruktansv&amp;#xE4;rt klantigt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eller?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;N&amp;#xE4;r vi gick fr&amp;#xE5;n butiken gick hade de andra tv&amp;#xE5; tjejerna som jobbade i butiken sl&amp;#xE4;ckt, l&amp;#xE5;st, r&amp;#xE4;knat ihop kassan och allt annat som ska g&amp;#xF6;ras n&amp;#xE4;r man st&amp;#xE4;nger butiken. Utom just att st&amp;#xE4;nga av fl&amp;#xE4;kten d&amp;#xE5;. Det fanns ingenting som p&amp;#xE5;minde min v&amp;#xE4;n om att hon m&amp;#xE5;ste komma ih&amp;#xE5;g att st&amp;#xE4;nga av fl&amp;#xE4;kten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hon blev ett offer f&amp;#xF6;r ett d&amp;#xE5;ligt system - ett sv&amp;#xE5;ranv&amp;#xE4;nt system, ett system som uppmuntrar till misstag. En rutin f&amp;#xF6;r hur saker ska g&amp;#xF6;ras, i vilken ordning och av vem, en checklista som man kan pricka av n&amp;#xE4;r man gjort det. Enkla saker kan g&amp;#xF6;ra stor nytta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag ser det mesta utifr&amp;#xE5;n ett systemperspektiv och ett anv&amp;#xE4;rbarhetsperspektiv. V&amp;#xE4;rlden &amp;#xE4;r ett system, vi &amp;#xE4;r dess anv&amp;#xE4;ndare. Jag brukar h&amp;#xE4;vda att trafiken har den mest avancerade och lyckade anv&amp;#xE4;ndbarheten som v&amp;#xE4;rlden har sk&amp;#xE5;dat. Det &amp;#xE4;r ett ofantligt stort och komplext system med m&amp;#xE5;nga anv&amp;#xE4;ndare som egentligen har otroligt lite information om vad de andra anv&amp;#xE4;ndarna i systemet g&amp;#xF6;r. N&amp;#xE5;gra enkla regler g&amp;#xF6;r dock att systemet fungerar. Vi har l&amp;#xE4;rt oss att k&amp;#xF6;ra p&amp;#xE5; r&amp;#xE4;tt sida, vi har l&amp;#xE4;rt oss h&amp;#xF6;gerregeln och vi har l&amp;#xE4;rt oss n&amp;#xE5;gra (men l&amp;#xE5;ngt ifr&amp;#xE5;n alla) symboler som styr systemet. Men givet de enkla reglerna som vem som helst kan l&amp;#xE4;ra sig &amp;#xE4;r trafiken v&amp;#xE4;ldigt l&amp;#xE4;ttanv&amp;#xE4;nd och det &amp;#xE4;r v&amp;#xE4;ldigt s&amp;#xE4;llan n&amp;#xE5;got g&amp;#xE5;r fel. En sak som trafiken &amp;#xE4;r bra p&amp;#xE5; &amp;#xE4;r att st&amp;#xE4;ndigt ge v&amp;#xE4;gledning. Det finns alltid en linje p&amp;#xE5; vardera sida om bilen som talar om vad man b&amp;#xF6;r g&amp;#xF6;ra. Kommer man till ett st&amp;#xE4;lle d&amp;#xE4;r man b&amp;#xF6;r stanna eller sakta ner finns det antagligen b&amp;#xE5;de en skylt och f&amp;#xE4;rg p&amp;#xE5; gatan som ber&amp;#xE4;ttar detta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F&amp;#xF6;r mig &amp;#xE4;r det h&amp;#xE4;r bara en tankelek, men s&amp;#xE4;tter man sig ner och klurar p&amp;#xE5; detta under en l&amp;#xE4;ngre tid kan man nog komma fram till n&amp;#xE5;got riktigt intressant.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Att hitta rtt folk</title><id >aatthittarattfolk2011-03-03t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/att-hitta-rtt-folk"></link><updated >2011-03-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;IT-konsultbolagen letar mycket folk. Jakten p&amp;#xE5; talanger bland konsultbolagen &amp;#xE4;r central under perioder d&amp;#xE5; efterfr&amp;#xE5;gan p&amp;#xE5; resurser &amp;#xE4;r stor, som nu, s&amp;#xE4;rskilt som det &amp;#xE4;r ganska ont om duktiga it-konsulter. Antalet som utexamineras &amp;#xE4;r ganska litet i f&amp;#xF6;rh&amp;#xE5;llande till efterfr&amp;#xE5;gan, och n&amp;#xE5;gon existerande &amp;#xF6;verkapacitet att ta av finns det inte heller. S&amp;#xE5;ledes beh&amp;#xF6;ver konsultbolagen hitta p&amp;#xE5; olika s&amp;#xE4;tt att aktivt locka till sig nytt folk. S&amp;#xE5;dana problem har inte f&amp;#xF6;retag som Propellerhead,  Apple och Spotify. De kan n&amp;#xF6;ja sig med att l&amp;#xE4;gga upp en liten bl&amp;#xE4;nkare p&amp;#xE5; sin hemsida och f&amp;#xE5;r &amp;#xE4;nd&amp;#xE5; fler s&amp;#xF6;kande &amp;#xE4;n de kan hantera. Ett vanligt tillv&amp;#xE4;gag&amp;#xE5;ngss&amp;#xE4;tt &amp;#xE4;r att erbjuda tipspengar. 10 000 om vi anst&amp;#xE4;ller n&amp;#xE5;gon du tipsat om. 15 000. 20 000! Man antar att personliga n&amp;#xE4;tverk &amp;#xE4;r ett fantastiskt s&amp;#xE4;tt att hitta r&amp;#xE4;tt folk p&amp;#xE5;, och det st&amp;#xE4;mmer s&amp;#xE4;kert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Konsultbolag som implmenterar internsystem f&amp;#xF6;r F&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xE4;kringskassan kommer aldrig att bli s&amp;#xE5; attraktiva arbetsgivare som exempelvis Twitter och Google, som g&amp;#xF6;r coola tj&amp;#xE4;nster och produkter som folk gillar att anv&amp;#xE4;nda. D&amp;#xE5; g&amp;#xE4;ller det att vara proaktiv och spela p&amp;#xE5; de styrkor man faktiskt har. F&amp;#xF6;r varken otroligt duktiga medarbetare eller roliga arbetsuppgifter saknas. Det som saknas &amp;#xE4;r ett s&amp;#xE4;tt att kommunicera ut och skapa intresse f&amp;#xF6;r detta hos potentiella framtida rekryter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connecta &amp;#xE4;r en av landets st&amp;#xF6;rre konsultfirmor. De har reklam i alla sk&amp;#xE5;p i omkl&amp;#xE4;dningsrummen p&amp;#xE5; SATS tr&amp;#xE4;ningscenter. D&amp;#xE4;r tror man sig ha hittat r&amp;#xE4;tt m&amp;#xE5;lgrupp. S&amp;#xE5; h&amp;#xE4;r kanske tankeg&amp;#xE5;ngarna gick: Ambiti&amp;#xF6;sa, duktiga m&amp;#xE4;nniskor h&amp;#xE5;ller sig i form. Gillar yoga, spinning och dr&amp;#xF6;mmer om att bli IT-konsulter. Accenture &amp;#xE4;r v&amp;#xE4;rldens st&amp;#xF6;rsta konsultbolag och de satsade fram till December 2009 stenh&amp;#xE5;rt p&amp;#xE5; att anv&amp;#xE4;nda en viss golfspelare i sin reklam (&amp;apos;Go on. Be a Tiger.&amp;apos;). Sedan de kommit fram att hans fru hade anledning att bli lite putt (pun intended) ersattes han i all hast av ansiktsl&amp;#xF6;sa koreanska skridsko&amp;#xE5;kare. Alla f&amp;#xF6;retag h&amp;#xE5;ller sig framme p&amp;#xE5; arbetsmarknadsdagar och m&amp;#xE4;ssor, anordnar aktiviteter och &amp;quot;tr&amp;#xE4;ffar folk&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alla har sina strategier. Men p&amp;#xE5; n&amp;#xE4;tet &amp;#xE4;r tystnaden &amp;#xF6;ronbed&amp;#xF6;vande. Visst, det finns kanske facebooksidor, kanske en &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.se.capgemini.com/karriarbloggen/&quot;&gt;blogg&lt;/a&gt; som med lite tur uppdateras en g&amp;#xE5;ng i m&amp;#xE5;naden, men antagligen mer s&amp;#xE4;llan &amp;#xE4;n s&amp;#xE5;. S&amp;#xE5;dant skr&amp;#xE4;mmer nog bort fler talanger &amp;#xE4;n det lockar. Vem vill jobba p&amp;#xE5; ett f&amp;#xF6;retag som inte bryr sig?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M&amp;#xE5;nga konsulter &amp;#xE4;r duktiga och driftiga &amp;#x2013; de bloggar, twittrar och genererar intresse inom omr&amp;#xE5;den d&amp;#xE4;r de kan mycket. Men f&amp;#xF6;retagen v&amp;#xE5;gar inte utnyttja dessa kanaler. Antagligen &amp;#xE4;r det en &amp;#xE4;ngslighet &amp;#xF6;ver varum&amp;#xE4;rket som g&amp;#xF6;r att allt som st&amp;#xE5;r p&amp;#xE5; samma sk&amp;#xE4;rm som en logotyp m&amp;#xE5;ste granskas i flera led. Visst skapar man kontroll, men man f&amp;#xF6;rlorar i kommunikation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mitt f&amp;#xF6;rslag &amp;#xE4;r enkelt: Uppmuntra, underl&amp;#xE4;tta och bel&amp;#xF6;na digitalt n&amp;#xE4;tverkande. L&amp;#xE5;t alla anst&amp;#xE4;llda som vill blogga, twittra och n&amp;#xE4;tverka i f&amp;#xF6;retagets namn (med en liten badge p&amp;#xE5; twitter-avataren t ex). Ha en tydlig men till&amp;#xE5;tande policy och uppmuntra ett personligt tilltal. G&amp;#xF6;r som &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/wired&quot;&gt;Wired&lt;/a&gt; och l&amp;#xE5;t de anst&amp;#xE4;llda turas om att ta hand om ett officiellt f&amp;#xF6;retagskonto en vecka i taget. Ha ett g&amp;#xE4;ng bloggar d&amp;#xE4;r flera anst&amp;#xE4;llda hj&amp;#xE4;lper till att skriva inom olika &amp;#xE4;mnen. Och ge tillb&amp;#xF6;rlig ers&amp;#xE4;ttning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det handlar om att s&amp;#xE5; mycket som m&amp;#xF6;jligt exponera de talanger man har p&amp;#xE5; f&amp;#xF6;retaget, att lita p&amp;#xE5; att det man g&amp;#xF6;r &amp;#xE4;r intressant och p&amp;#xE5; att man besitter stora m&amp;#xE4;ngder kompetens som v&amp;#xE4;xer om den f&amp;#xE5;r komma ut i luften.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Recension: Samsung Galaxy Ace</title><id >arecensionsamsunggalaxyace2011-02-21t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/recension-samsung-galaxy-ace"></link><updated >2011-02-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jag &amp;#xE4;r en Apple-kille. Inget att sticka under stol med. Jag har tv&amp;#xE5; macar och en iPhone. N&amp;#xE4;r jag skulle ha en ny jobbtelefon tyckte jag dock att det var dags att bes&amp;#xF6;ka Android-v&amp;#xE4;rlden, f&amp;#xF6;r att f&amp;#xE5; lite perspektiv p&amp;#xE5; tillvaron. Valet f&amp;#xF6;ll p&amp;#xE5; Samsung Galaxy Ace, en mellanklassmodell som precis b&amp;#xF6;rjat landa i svenska butiker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifikationerna &amp;#xE4;r inte &amp;#xF6;verdrivet imponerande men med tanke p&amp;#xE5; priset (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phonehouse.se/Mobiltelefoner/Samsung/Samsung-S5830-Galaxy-Ace&quot;&gt;3299:- hos Phone House&lt;/a&gt;) f&amp;#xE5;r den &amp;#xE4;nd&amp;#xE5; anses prisv&amp;#xE4;rd. 3,5&amp;quot;-sk&amp;#xE4;rm p&amp;#xE5; 320x480 pixlar, 800MHz-processor, 5Mpx-kamera med blixt och Android 2.2 Froyo med Samsungs TouchWiz-UI &amp;#xE4;r v&amp;#xE4;l det viktigaste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;L&amp;#xE5;dan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Med telefonen f&amp;#xF6;ljer ett micro-SD-kort p&amp;#xE5; 2 GB med tillh&amp;#xF6;rande adapter, en v&amp;#xE4;ggladdare, en USB-kabel och en instruktionsbok. N&amp;#xE5;got headset har Samsung inte kostat p&amp;#xE5; sig. Sn&amp;#xE5;lt kan tyckas, men inget jag st&amp;#xF6;r mig p&amp;#xE5; eftersom jag har ett bra Klipsch-headset redan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Utsidan&lt;/h2&gt;   

&lt;p&gt;En av sakerna som lockade hos Galaxy Ace var utseendet. Det &amp;#xE4;r n&amp;#xE5;got inspirerat av iPhone 4, med den blanksvarta framsidan och metallbandet som g&amp;#xE5;r runt telefonen. Baksidan &amp;#xE4;r gjord av greppv&amp;#xE4;nlig gummiaktig plast med tydlig struktur. Den &amp;#xE4;r lite plastig men k&amp;#xE4;nns &amp;#xE4;nd&amp;#xE5; solid och v&amp;#xE4;lbyggd, dock kommer den inte i n&amp;#xE4;rheten av iPhone i den delt&amp;#xE4;vlingen. Till och med min gamla 3GS &amp;#xE4;r betydligt mer stabil en Acen. P&amp;#xE5;/av-knappen sitter p&amp;#xE5; h&amp;#xF6;gra sidan och volymknapparna p&amp;#xE5; den v&amp;#xE4;nstra. SD-kortet och micro-USB-uttaget sitter bakom varsina sm&amp;#xE5; luckor. Jag uppskattar att laddaren g&amp;#xE5;r in p&amp;#xE5; ovansidan av telefonen. Det g&amp;#xF6;r det enkelt att anv&amp;#xE4;nda den &amp;#xE4;ven n&amp;#xE4;r den &amp;#xE4;r inkopplad. Framsidan har en synlig knapp, som fungerar som hem-knapp, very iPhone-like. Det finns &amp;#xE4;ven tv&amp;#xE5; touch-knappar &amp;#x2013; &amp;apos;bak&amp;#xE5;t&amp;apos; och &amp;apos;alternativ&amp;apos; &amp;#x2013; som lyser upp n&amp;#xE4;r man h&amp;#xE5;ller p&amp;#xE5; att klicka runt. D&amp;#xE4;remot &amp;#xE4;r de inte alltid upplysta n&amp;#xE4;r man kan anv&amp;#xE4;nda sig av dem, vilket &amp;#xE4;r lite f&amp;#xF6;rvirrande. Baksidan har f&amp;#xF6;rutom kameran &amp;#xE4;ven ett par h&amp;#xE5;l f&amp;#xF6;r h&amp;#xF6;gtalaren. Sk&amp;#xE4;rmen &amp;#xE4;r inte s&amp;#xE4;rskilt h&amp;#xF6;guppl&amp;#xF6;st, men sk&amp;#xE4;ms inte f&amp;#xF6;r sig bredvid min iPhone 3GS. F&amp;#xE4;rgerna k&amp;#xE4;nns till och med lite klarare p&amp;#xE5; Galaxy Acen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Insidan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, jag har bara iPhone att j&amp;#xE4;mf&amp;#xF6;ra med. Har testat lite olika Android-lurar ocks&amp;#xE5;, men inte tillr&amp;#xE4;ckligt l&amp;#xE4;nge f&amp;#xF6;r att bilda mig en riktig uppfattning om operativsystemet. TouchWiz-gr&amp;#xE4;nssnittet k&amp;#xE4;nns dock ganska intuitivt och man kommer snabbt ig&amp;#xE5;ng. Grafiken flyter inte p&amp;#xE5; lika fint som p&amp;#xE5; iPhone &amp;#x2013; det hackar lite grann n&amp;#xE4;r man scrollar runt. Det k&amp;#xE4;nns som att h&amp;#xE5;rdvaran &amp;#xE4;r i klenaste laget. Det &amp;#xE4;r dock inte v&amp;#xE4;rre &amp;#xE4;n att det ska ses som en kosmetisk miss snarare &amp;#xE4;n en funktionell. Klart b&amp;#xE4;ttre &amp;#xE4;n andra Android-lurar jag har testat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag &amp;#xE4;r inte helt s&amp;#xE5;ld p&amp;#xE5; uppl&amp;#xE4;gget med hemsk&amp;#xE4;rmar och &amp;quot;k&amp;#xE4;llaren&amp;quot; d&amp;#xE4;r alla appar finns, men jag tror nog jag kommer kunna v&amp;#xE4;nja mig vid det ocks&amp;#xE5;. Det &amp;#xE4;r trevligt att man kan ha widgets p&amp;#xE5; hemsk&amp;#xE4;rmen, men det &amp;#xE4;r inte alltid syftet med dem k&amp;#xE4;nns alldeles solklart (hur meningsfullt &amp;#xE4;r det t ex att se den senaste tweeten i sin feed?). Hur man ska strukturera hemsk&amp;#xE4;rmen &amp;#xE4;r nog n&amp;#xE5;got man f&amp;#xE5;r pr&amp;#xF6;va sig fram till. Jag passade snabbt p&amp;#xE5; att byta launcher till &lt;a href=&quot;http://jbthemes.com/anderweb/&quot;&gt;ADW.launcher&lt;/a&gt;, som &amp;#xE4;r betydligt mycket snabbare och trevligare &amp;#xE4;n Samsungs orginal. Rekommenderar alla att g&amp;#xF6;ra detsamma!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det inbyggda tangentbordet &amp;#xE4;r riktigt bra. Det enda jag st&amp;#xF6;r mig p&amp;#xE5; &amp;#xE4;r att det byter upps&amp;#xE4;ttning n&amp;#xE4;r man skiftar mellan gemener och versaler. Jag tappar bort mig bland versalerna. IPhone-l&amp;#xF6;sningen med en &amp;quot;lysande&amp;quot; shift-knapp och st&amp;#xE4;ndiga versaler p&amp;#xE5; tangenterna k&amp;#xE4;nns mycket smidigare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Android vs. Apple&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Med &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doubletwist.com/&quot;&gt;DoubleTwist&lt;/a&gt; g&amp;#xE5;r det smidigt att synka media med sin mac, &amp;#xE4;ven &amp;#xF6;ver WiFi om man skaffar &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doubletwist.com/airsync/&quot;&gt;AirSync-appen&lt;/a&gt; f&amp;#xF6;r 32 kronor. 1-0 till Android d&amp;#xE4;r. Applikationsutbudet d&amp;#xE4;remot k&amp;#xE4;nns lite skralt p&amp;#xE5; Android. Dels saknas en del lite mer obskyra appar (Funbeat, Viber etc) och dels &amp;#xE4;r de appar som finns ofta lite s&amp;#xE4;mre. Reeder och Twitter for iPhone, som &amp;#xE4;r mina tv&amp;#xE5; mest anv&amp;#xE4;nda appar, har exempelvis inga likv&amp;#xE4;rdiga ers&amp;#xE4;ttare p&amp;#xE5; Android (som jag har hittat, men jag har i &amp;#xE4;rlighetens namn bara letat v&amp;#xE4;ldigt kort). I &amp;#xF6;vrigt &amp;#xE4;r inst&amp;#xE4;llningsm&amp;#xF6;jligheterna tilltalande m&amp;#xE5;nga. Det &amp;#xE4;r bra om man vet hur man vill ha det, men &amp;#xE4;r man ingen power user tror jag nog iOS bjuder p&amp;#xE5; en l&amp;#xE5;ngt b&amp;#xE4;ttre anv&amp;#xE4;ndarupplevelse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fr&amp;#xE5;gan &amp;#xE4;r d&amp;#xE5;, &amp;#xE4;r den b&amp;#xE4;ttre eller s&amp;#xE4;mre &amp;#xE4;n min iPhone 3GS? Njae, jag v&amp;#xE4;ntar med den domen ett tag till. Gissningsvis kommer det fler delar i den h&amp;#xE4;r recensionen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS. Klicka p&amp;#xE5; bilden ovan f&amp;#xF6;r fler bilder DS.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >En principsak</title><id >aenprincipsak2011-02-14t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/en-principsak"></link><updated >2011-02-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Roland Poirier Martinsson skriver i senaste Neo om Wikileaks. Han gillar verkligen inte Wikileaks, vilket f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5;s inte &amp;#xE4;r n&amp;#xE5;gon nyhet f&amp;#xF6;r oss som sett hans &lt;a href=&quot;http://svtplay.se/v/2262698/gomorron_sverige/debatt_om_wikileaks_publiceringar&quot;&gt;tidigare&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tv4play.se/nyheter_och_debatt/nyhetsmorgon?title=debatt_behandlar_svensk_media_wikileaks_for_okritiskt&amp;amp;videoid=1160831&quot;&gt;debatter&lt;/a&gt; och &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.svd.se/opinion/ledarsidan/moraliskt-moras-under-wikileaks_5804255.svd&quot;&gt;artiklar&lt;/a&gt; i &amp;#xE4;mnet. Artikeln i Neo har ett antal po&amp;#xE4;nger, av vilka en del kan bortses fr&amp;#xE5;n utan vidare, som att han anser sig ha r&amp;#xE4;tt f&amp;#xF6;r att alla andra debatt&amp;#xF6;rer tycker annorlunda, samt att v&amp;#xE4;nstern borde tycka som honom eftersom de &amp;#xE4;r emot yttrandefrihet. V&amp;#xE4;nsters motst&amp;#xE5;nd mot yttrandefrihet har aldrig varit s&amp;#xE5; starkt som deras aversion mot v&amp;#xE4;stv&amp;#xE4;rlden i allm&amp;#xE4;nhet och USA i synnerhet, den r&amp;#xF6;da tr&amp;#xE5;d som kan leda den s&amp;#xE4;mste navigat&amp;#xF6;r r&amp;#xE4;tt i den socialistiska &amp;#xE5;siktsdjungeln.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vidare anser RPM att liberaler som f&amp;#xF6;rsvarar Wikileaks &amp;#xE4;r obegripliga eftersom yttrandefriheten m&amp;#xE5;ste ha begr&amp;#xE4;nsningar och att det s&amp;#xE5;ledes h&amp;#xF6;r till god liberal tradition att till exempel klassa s&amp;#xE5;dant som kan vara skadligt f&amp;#xF6;r rikets s&amp;#xE4;kerhet, individers integritet och s&amp;#xE4;kerhet eller upphovsr&amp;#xE4;ttsinnehavares r&amp;#xE4;ttigheter, som illegalt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPM diskuterar &amp;#xE4;ven det amerikanska lagrummet och kommer fram till att wikileaks verksamhet med st&amp;#xF6;rsta s&amp;#xE4;kerhet &amp;#xE4;r fullkomligt laglig. Han h&amp;#xE4;vdar dock att verksamheten skulle vara &amp;#xE5;talbar i Sverige men utan att precisera exakt hur den skulle bryta mot ett av v&amp;#xE4;rldens starkaste presskydd. Jag l&amp;#xE4;mnar detta &amp;#xE5;t n&amp;#xE5;gon med mer juridiskt kunnande att bed&amp;#xF6;ma. Hur som helst landar han i slutsatsen att Julian Assange b&amp;#xF6;r &amp;#xE5;talas, till skillnad mot de som l&amp;#xE4;ckte The Pentagon Papers, och till skillnad mot de tidningar som publicerat exakt samma uppgifter som Wikileaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Att RPM vill se Julian Assange skaka galler &amp;#xE4;r ingen nyhet. F&amp;#xF6;r att vinna gillande f&amp;#xF6;r denna st&amp;#xE5;ndpunkt v&amp;#xE4;ljer han (implicit) att anklaga Wikileaks f&amp;#xF6;r att sj&amp;#xE4;lva ha stulit dokumenten de publicerar, vilket inget mig veteligen tyder p&amp;#xE5; att de gjort. Det &amp;#xE4;r av den anledningen Bradley Manning och ingen annan spenderar tjugotre timmar per dygn i isoleringscell utan n&amp;#xE5;gon r&amp;#xE4;tteg&amp;#xE5;ng i sikte.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Och d&amp;#xE4;r glider vi in p&amp;#xE5; en annan del av RPM:s argumentation mot Wikileaks, n&amp;#xE4;mligen att det &amp;#xE4;r f&amp;#xF6;rkastligt att publicerar s&amp;#xE5;dant som skadar &amp;quot;den demokratiska v&amp;#xE4;rlden&amp;quot; och &amp;quot;det &amp;#xF6;ppna samh&amp;#xE4;llet&amp;quot; ist&amp;#xE4;llet f&amp;#xF6;r diktaturerna som den demokratiska v&amp;#xE4;rlden f&amp;#xF6;r krig mot. Naturligtvis &amp;#xE4;r USA ett mer demokratiskt land &amp;#xE4;n de flesta andra i v&amp;#xE4;rlden, men det betyder inte att det inte finns oegentligheter som m&amp;#xE5;r bra av att avsl&amp;#xF6;jas. Hade han argumenterat p&amp;#xE5; samma s&amp;#xE4;tt om dokument som visade att USA lj&amp;#xF6;g inf&amp;#xF6;r Irakinvasionen? Och vad skiljer den argumentationen fr&amp;#xE5;n den som diktaturerna sj&amp;#xE4;lva anv&amp;#xE4;nder f&amp;#xF6;r att stoppa intern kritik?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Min po&amp;#xE4;ng &amp;#xE4;r att den &amp;#xF6;ppna v&amp;#xE4;rlden m&amp;#xE5;ste kunna t&amp;#xE5;la en mycket h&amp;#xE5;rd journalistisk granskning, om den inte g&amp;#xF6;r det &amp;#xE4;r det ett tydligt tecken p&amp;#xE5; att den &amp;#xE4;r p&amp;#xE5; v&amp;#xE4;g bort fr&amp;#xE5;n &amp;#xF6;ppenheten. D&amp;#xE5; kan dess f&amp;#xF6;retr&amp;#xE4;dare antingen v&amp;#xE4;lja att &amp;#xE5;ter g&amp;#xE5; mot &amp;#xF6;ppenhet eller att ytterligare sluta sig. Till slut handlar det om gr&amp;#xE4;nsdragningar, precis som RPM ocks&amp;#xE5; konstaterar, och om man inte ser en plats f&amp;#xF6;r Wikileaks och liknande organisationer (som utan tvekan kommer att ploppa upp s&amp;#xE5;v&amp;#xE4;l till h&amp;#xF6;ger som v&amp;#xE4;nster)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man kan vara kritisk mot Wikileaks av m&amp;#xE5;nga anledningar &amp;#x2013; deras politiska agenda, deras dysfunktionella organisation och inte minst praktarslet Julian Assange. Men att anv&amp;#xE4;nda dem som slagtr&amp;#xE4; f&amp;#xF6;r att minska press- och yttrandefriheten eller m&amp;#xF6;jligheten f&amp;#xF6;r whistleblowers att avsl&amp;#xF6;ja missf&amp;#xF6;rh&amp;#xE5;llanden &amp;#xE4;r inte &amp;#xF6;nskv&amp;#xE4;rt. Vilka &amp;#xE5;sikter en nyhetsf&amp;#xF6;rmedlare har och hur dessa i s&amp;#xE5; fall g&amp;#xF6;r sin nyhetsv&amp;#xE4;rdering kan man absolut ha &amp;#xE5;sikter om, och i det avseendet &amp;#xE4;r onekligen Wikileaks klanderv&amp;#xE4;rt. D&amp;#xE4;remot omfattar tryckfriheten &amp;#xE4;ven den som har avvikande mening. F&amp;#xF6;r det som skiljer Julian Assange och &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentagon_Papers&quot;&gt;Daniel Ellsberg&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#xE5;t &amp;#xE4;r inte fr&amp;#xE4;mst deras metoder, utan deras politiska &amp;#xE5;sikter. Och yttrandefrihetens gr&amp;#xE4;nser b&amp;#xF6;r inte g&amp;#xE5; l&amp;#xE4;ngs politiska skiljelinjer, som Roland Poirier Martinsson skulle vilja.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Som avslutning vill jag uttrycka en stilla f&amp;#xF6;rhoppning att r&amp;#xF6;relser liknande Wikileaks kan v&amp;#xE4;xa upp och sprida ljus &amp;#xF6;ver saker som p&amp;#xE5;g&amp;#xE5;r i skuggorna i exempelvis Iran, Kina, Israel, Ryssland etc.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Till den stelbenta byrkratins frsvar</title><id >atilldenstelbentabyrakratinsforsvar2011-01-28t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/till-den-stelbenta-byrkratins-frsvar"></link><updated >2011-01-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Det klagas ofta p&amp;#xE5; byr&amp;#xE5;krati. Det &amp;#xE4;r ju s&amp;#xE5; enkelt att tycka att folk bara skulle anv&amp;#xE4;nda sitt vanliga sunda f&amp;#xF6;rnuft. Jag har t&amp;#xE4;nkt liknande tankar sj&amp;#xE4;lv, precis som de flesta antar jag, och s&amp;#xE5;dana &amp;#xE5;sikter &amp;#xE4;r oftast sv&amp;#xE5;ra att argumentera mot. Vad d&amp;#xE5; &amp;quot;Nej, jag tycker inte att folk borde anv&amp;#xE4;nda sina vanliga sunda f&amp;#xF6;rnuft&amp;quot;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men ju mer jag t&amp;#xE4;nker p&amp;#xE5; det desto mer tycker jag att det byr&amp;#xE5;kratin beh&amp;#xF6;ver &amp;#xE4;r fanatiska tillskyndare. Om folk skulle anv&amp;#xE4;nda sina &amp;quot;sunda f&amp;#xF6;rnuft&amp;quot; skulle det ta hus i helvete kan jag s&amp;#xE4;ga. (Se d&amp;#xE4;r, &amp;#xE4;nnu ett exempel p&amp;#xE5; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=136332289764451&amp;amp;set=a.136332286431118.26053.136094543121559&quot;&gt;korrekt anv&amp;#xE4;ndande av citationstecken&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stelbent byr&amp;#xE5;krati inneb&amp;#xE4;r att de som handl&amp;#xE4;gger &amp;#xE4;renden, exempelvis p&amp;#xE5; F&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xE4;kringskassan, till punkt och pricka f&amp;#xF6;ljer de regelverk som finns. De senaste &amp;#xE5;ren &amp;#x2013; ja, s&amp;#xE5; l&amp;#xE4;nge mitt unga huvud kan minnas egentligen &amp;#x2013; har en rad fall uppm&amp;#xE4;rksammats d&amp;#xE4;r detta har orsakat individer mer eller mindre omfattande skada. Vem minns till exempel inte Fallet Annica som livade upp veckorna innan valet i h&amp;#xF6;stas? Allt sunt f&amp;#xF6;rnuft talar f&amp;#xF6;r att man i vissa fall ska kunna kringg&amp;#xE5; reglerna. Medierna &amp;#xE4;lskar f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5;s ocks&amp;#xE5; h&amp;#xE4;xjakter d&amp;#xE4;r man kan &amp;#xE5;beropa sunt f&amp;#xF6;rnuft och svartm&amp;#xE5;la s&amp;#xE5;v&amp;#xE4;l byr&amp;#xE5;kratin som det regelverk som den st&amp;#xF6;djer sig p&amp;#xE5;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regelverk som &amp;#xE4;r d&amp;#xE5;liga ska kritiseras&lt;/strong&gt;. Men byr&amp;#xE5;kratin ska kritiseras endast om den inte g&amp;#xF6;r sitt jobb &amp;#x2013; allts&amp;#xE5; om den inte f&amp;#xF6;ljer reglerna. Hade en proteststorm flugit upp om Annica Holmquist hade f&amp;#xE5;tt sjukf&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xE4;kring p&amp;#xE5; grund av att n&amp;#xE5;gon handl&amp;#xE4;ggare kringg&amp;#xE5;tt reglerna? I think not. Hade d&amp;#xE5; de felaktiga reglerna &amp;#xE4;ndrats? I think not. G&amp;#xE5;r handl&amp;#xE4;ggare runt reglerna kommer v&amp;#xE5;ra lagstiftare undan med v&amp;#xE4;rdel&amp;#xF6;sa regelverk, och vi f&amp;#xE5;r ist&amp;#xE4;llet ett samh&amp;#xE4;lle d&amp;#xE4;r varje enskilt fall avg&amp;#xF6;rs av handl&amp;#xE4;ggarens godtycke och det enda man har att luta sig mot &amp;#xE4;r regelverk som kan vara hur otydliga eller or&amp;#xE4;ttvisa som helst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men det finns mer. Likhet inf&amp;#xF6;r lagen, f&amp;#xF6;ruts&amp;#xE4;gbarhet &amp;#xE4;r till exempel saker som brukar tas upp men som jag inte tycker det &amp;#xE4;r v&amp;#xE4;rt att orera om just h&amp;#xE4;r.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vanligt sunt f&amp;#xF6;rnuft &amp;#xE4;r inte vanligt.&lt;/strong&gt; Folk har nog v&amp;#xE4;ldigt olika uppfattning om vad sunt f&amp;#xF6;rnuft inneb&amp;#xE4;r. Det &amp;#xE4;r ett s&amp;#xE4;rdeles fluffigt begrepp. I hur m&amp;#xE5;nga fr&amp;#xE5;gor man f&amp;#xE5; samma svar om vad som var sunt om man fr&amp;#xE5;gade en v&amp;#xE4;nsterpartist respektive en Sverigedemokrat? Tror ni de skulle g&amp;#xF6;ra samma bed&amp;#xF6;mningar om de arbetade som handl&amp;#xE4;ggare och kunde till&amp;#xE4;mpa sitt eget sunda f&amp;#xF6;rnuft? Om man skulle uppmuntra en st&amp;#xF6;rre andel sunt f&amp;#xF6;rnuft skulle man &amp;#xF6;verl&amp;#xE4;mna makt &amp;#xE5;t en hel massa anonyma tj&amp;#xE4;nstem&amp;#xE4;n som skulle kunna agera helt utefter eget tycke. Det skulle i sin tur kr&amp;#xE4;va att deras tycke sammanf&amp;#xF6;ll med den linje som regeringen har beslutat om. Allts&amp;#xE5; skulle det riskera att leda till politisk likriktning och sj&amp;#xE4;lvcensur. Jag har inget till &amp;#xF6;vers f&amp;#xF6;r varken (V) eller (SD) men deras sympatis&amp;#xF6;rer m&amp;#xE5;ste likv&amp;#xE4;l kunna ta tj&amp;#xE4;nstemannajobb utan att f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xF6;ra systemet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stelbent byr&amp;#xE5;krati en en f&amp;#xF6;ruts&amp;#xE4;ttning f&amp;#xF6;r snabb &amp;#xE4;rendehantering.&lt;/strong&gt; En kritik som riktas mot byr&amp;#xE5;krati &amp;#xE4;r att den &amp;#xE4;r l&amp;#xE5;ngsam. Handl&amp;#xE4;ggningstider p&amp;#xE5; X antal m&amp;#xE5;nader etc. Enda s&amp;#xE4;ttet att f&amp;#xE5; bort den l&amp;#xE5;ngsamma byr&amp;#xE5;kratin &amp;#xE4;r att g&amp;#xF6;ra den s&amp;#xE5; stelbent att den kan automatiseras. Ju fler processer som kan sk&amp;#xF6;tas utan inblandning av handl&amp;#xE4;ggare, desto mer tid f&amp;#xE5;r de till att hantera de &amp;#xE4;renden som verkligen beh&amp;#xF6;ver en m&amp;#xE4;nniskas uppm&amp;#xE4;rksamhet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K&amp;#xE4;nner inte att jag utt&amp;#xF6;mt &amp;#xE4;mnet, s&amp;#xE5; jag kanske &amp;#xE5;terkommer. Bite sized snacks &amp;#xE4;r min devis.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Relationer 101</title><id >arelationer1012011-01-14t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/relationer-101"></link><updated >2011-01-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jag och Internet kom till Sverige ungef&amp;#xE4;r samtidigt, f&amp;#xF6;r knappa 27 &amp;#xE5;r sedan. Vi har v&amp;#xE4;xt upp tillsammans och &amp;#xE4;r en naturlig del av varandras liv. Vi &amp;#xE4;r generationsbr&amp;#xF6;der. Vi f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5;r varandra. D&amp;#xE4;rtill har jag alltid varit intresserad av datorer, teknik och kommunikation, b&amp;#xE5;de privat och yrkesm&amp;#xE4;ssigt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En del saker som ter sig sj&amp;#xE4;lvklara f&amp;#xF6;r mig verkar helt ha g&amp;#xE5;tt andra f&amp;#xF6;rbi. Det beror kanske p&amp;#xE5; generationsskillnader, teknikanalfabetism eller bara brist p&amp;#xE5; intresse, men m&amp;#xE5;nga verkar inte ha reflekterat s&amp;#xE4;rskilt mycket&amp;#xF6;ver de m&amp;#xE5;nga s&amp;#xE4;tt som Internet har f&amp;#xF6;r&amp;#xE4;ndrat samh&amp;#xE4;llet och oss som &amp;#xE4;r en del av det.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bengt Ohlsson har en &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pastan.nu/bloggen/inlagg/3345&quot;&gt;kr&amp;#xF6;nika i g&amp;#xE5;rdagens DN&lt;/a&gt; om hur Facebook skapar en illusion av att man &amp;#xE4;r social och att man har l&amp;#xE5;tsasv&amp;#xE4;nner ist&amp;#xE4;llet f&amp;#xF6;r riktiga v&amp;#xE4;nner. Det &amp;#xE4;r s&amp;#xE5;dant som jag vanligtvis skulle l&amp;#xE5;ta passera, f&amp;#xF6;r det &amp;#xE4;r absolut ingen ny &amp;quot;kritik&amp;quot;. Tv&amp;#xE4;rtom &amp;#xE4;r det i princip den enda sortens kritik som har riktats mot Facebook, bortr&amp;#xE4;knat diverse integritetskontroverser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag tror att den h&amp;#xE4;r sortens kritik frodas p&amp;#xE5; grund av en ganska basal begreppsf&amp;#xF6;rvirring. Kritikerna utg&amp;#xE5;r fr&amp;#xE5;n att en v&amp;#xE4;nskap p&amp;#xE5; Internet &amp;#xE4;r samma sak som en v&amp;#xE4;nskap var n&amp;#xE4;r de v&amp;#xE4;xte upp, i den &amp;quot;riktiga&amp;quot; v&amp;#xE4;rlden. Men att bli v&amp;#xE4;n n&amp;#xE5;gon p&amp;#xE5; Facebook &amp;#xE4;r inte samma sak som att vara v&amp;#xE4;nner i verkliga livet. Det liknar faktiskt ingen sorts relation som funnits tidigare i historien, f&amp;#xF6;r att det s&amp;#xE4;ttet att kommunicera som har v&amp;#xE4;xt fram p&amp;#xE5; de sociala medierna liknar inget som tidigare varit m&amp;#xF6;jligt. Allt det h&amp;#xE4;r g&amp;#xE4;ller f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5;s alla sorters sociala medier, men Facebook f&amp;#xE5;r utst&amp;#xE5; mest kritik f&amp;#xF6;r att d&amp;#xE4;r &amp;#xE4;r begreppsf&amp;#xF6;rvirringen som st&amp;#xF6;rst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag &amp;#xE4;r v&amp;#xE4;n p&amp;#xE5; Facebook med personer som jag aldrig tr&amp;#xE4;ffat, som jag tr&amp;#xE4;ffat bara ett par g&amp;#xE5;nger och de som jag tr&amp;#xE4;ffar varje dag. Det &amp;#xE4;r folk som jag har mycket gemensamt med, lite gemensamt med och inget gemensamt med. L&amp;#xE5;t mig ta ett exempel p&amp;#xE5; hur de h&amp;#xE4;r relationerna och kommunikationen kan fungera:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I somras skulle jag och en v&amp;#xE4;n (i ordets &amp;#xE4;ldre bem&amp;#xE4;rkelse) &amp;#xE5;ka ut p&amp;#xE5; semester i Europa. Jag skrev ett Facebookinl&amp;#xE4;gg och fr&amp;#xE5;gade om n&amp;#xE5;gon ville med. En bekant som jag jobbat med &amp;#xE5;ret innan svarade att han ocks&amp;#xE5; t&amp;#xE4;nkt resa i Europa under samma period. Vi slog v&amp;#xE5;ra p&amp;#xE5;sar ihop och med varsitt InterRailkort drog vi oss s&amp;#xF6;derut. Under resan uppdaterade jag f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5;s min omv&amp;#xE4;rld om var vi var och vad vi gjorde, och n&amp;#xE4;r jag noterade att det regnade i Prag fick jag ett meddelande fr&amp;#xE5;n en amerikan som jag tr&amp;#xE4;ffat ett par g&amp;#xE5;nger i n&amp;#xE4;r jag bodde i Australien tv&amp;#xE5; &amp;#xE5;r tidigare. Han var i Prag och h&amp;#xE4;lsade p&amp;#xE5; sin faster och vi best&amp;#xE4;mde oss f&amp;#xF6;r att tr&amp;#xE4;ffas. Efter ett par trevliga dagar tillsammans i Prag for vi vidare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I Facebook-v&amp;#xE4;rlden skapar man band till folk man annars sedan l&amp;#xE4;nge skulle ha gl&amp;#xF6;mt bort. Man masskommunicerar. Man har l&amp;#xF6;sa relationer, relationer som skulle ha varit om&amp;#xF6;jliga utan den sortens kommunikation. Jag hade inte haft en aning om att min v&amp;#xE4;n hade varit intresserad av att f&amp;#xF6;lja med ut i Europa, och jag hade inte haft en aning om att amerikanen var i Prag samtidigt som jag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men de l&amp;#xF6;sa relationerna beh&amp;#xF6;ver inte leda till fysiska m&amp;#xF6;ten.  &amp;#xC4;ven en kommentar h&amp;#xE4;r och d&amp;#xE4;r, en tumme upp n&amp;#xE4;r man gillar n&amp;#xE5;got, &amp;#xE4;r en del av de l&amp;#xF6;sa v&amp;#xE4;nskapsband som man nu kan skapa. Dessa relationer annorlunda &amp;#xE4;n vad m&amp;#xE5;nga &amp;#xE4;r vana vid, och anses d&amp;#xE4;rf&amp;#xF6;r vara mindre v&amp;#xE4;rda. Vissa personer som vi har relationer med p&amp;#xE5; sociala n&amp;#xE4;tverk &amp;#xE4;r s&amp;#xE5;dana som vi inte vill umg&amp;#xE5;s med bortanf&amp;#xF6;r datorsk&amp;#xE4;rmen, enligt Bengt Ohlsson ett fantastiskt exempel p&amp;#xE5; att allt bara &amp;#xE4;r p&amp;#xE5; l&amp;#xE5;tsas. Men man kan ha ett relevant utbyte, &amp;#xE4;ven om det inte tar fysisk form. Och naturligtvis har man inte ens lust att umg&amp;#xE5;s digitalt med alla gamla gymnasiekompisar. Det beh&amp;#xF6;ver man f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5;s inte heller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Den andra delen av kritiken &amp;#xE4;r att facebook tr&amp;#xE4;nger ut det &amp;quot;riktiga&amp;quot; umg&amp;#xE4;nget och ers&amp;#xE4;tter det med en illusion. F&amp;#xF6;r det f&amp;#xF6;rsta &amp;#xE4;r det att f&amp;#xF6;rringa v&amp;#xE4;rdet av n&amp;#xE4;trelationer. Det &amp;#xE4;r f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5;s upp till var och en att bed&amp;#xF6;ma olika relationer med olika personer, men att s&amp;#xE4;ga att alla relationer p&amp;#xE5; n&amp;#xE4;tet &amp;#xE4;r p&amp;#xE5; l&amp;#xE5;tsas &amp;#xE4;r inte seri&amp;#xF6;st. F&amp;#xF6;r det andra h&amp;#xE5;ller jag inte med om att fysiska relationer tr&amp;#xE4;ngs ut. Sj&amp;#xE4;lvklart kan det bli f&amp;#xF6;r mycket facebook, men jag tycker generellt att n&amp;#xE4;tv&amp;#xE4;nskaper lever ett symbiotiskt liv med gammaldags relationer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man m&amp;#xE5;ste hitta sin egen balans mellan n&amp;#xE4;trelationer och fysiska relationer, men utan att f&amp;#xF6;rringa n&amp;#xE5;gon av dem. Om man inte f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5;r att nya kommunikationss&amp;#xE4;tt skapar nya sorters relationer kommer man, precis som Bengt Ohlsson, att undra hur man kan vara ensam om man har 1000 facebookv&amp;#xE4;nner.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >&quot;Konsultmssighet&quot;</title><id >aquotkonsultmassighetquot2011-01-03t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/konsultmssighet"></link><updated >2011-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ska du vara it-konsult kr&amp;#xE4;vs det att du har en hel kunskaper och f&amp;#xE4;rdigheter. Du ska kunna l&amp;#xE4;ra dig snabbt, s&amp;#xE4;tta dig in i nya saker och vara kompetent inom ditt omr&amp;#xE5;de. Men det finns en egenskap som trumfar alla andra: &lt;strong&gt;Konsultm&amp;#xE4;ssighet&lt;/strong&gt;. Vad &amp;#xE4;r d&amp;#xE5; detta?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bryt s&amp;#xF6;nder ordet: Konsultm&amp;#xE4;ssig. Liknande en konsult. F&amp;#xF6;r att bli konsult ska du allts&amp;#xE5; vara som en konsult &amp;#xE4;r.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hur &amp;#xE4;r d&amp;#xE5; en konsult? En konsult &amp;#xE4;r trevlig, tillm&amp;#xF6;tesg&amp;#xE5;ende och flexibel. En konsult &amp;#xE4;r representabel. En god ambassad&amp;#xF6;r f&amp;#xF6;r sitt f&amp;#xF6;retag. Egentligen handlar det om samma princip som n&amp;#xE4;r det g&amp;#xE4;ller &lt;a href=&quot;http://eldh.co/tankar/dresscode&quot;&gt;dresscode&lt;/a&gt;. Stick. Inte. Ut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M&amp;#xE5;nga skulle s&amp;#xE4;kert l&amp;#xE4;sa in fler saker i begreppet konsultm&amp;#xE4;ssighet - intresse f&amp;#xF6;r aff&amp;#xE4;rsnytta, social kompetens etc. etc. Sannolikt skiljer begreppets inneb&amp;#xF6;rd ocks&amp;#xE5; kraftigt p&amp;#xE5; olika f&amp;#xF6;retag och till och med mellan olika personer som jobbar med varandra. D&amp;#xE4;ri ligger problemet. Konsultbranchen &amp;#xE4;r full av flummiga begrepp. Alla brancher har v&amp;#xE4;l sin egen vokabul&amp;#xE4;r. Det handlar dels om effektivitet, men &amp;#xE4;ven om att skapa en tillh&amp;#xF6;righet. Inget fel med det. N&amp;#xE4;r man &amp;#xE4;r d&amp;#xE4;r inne &amp;#xE4;r b&amp;#xE4;gge sakerna viktiga.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men &amp;quot;konsultm&amp;#xE4;ssighet&amp;quot; anv&amp;#xE4;nds framf&amp;#xF6;rallt i rekryteringsprocessen. F&amp;#xF6;r att s&amp;#xE5;lla. Att anv&amp;#xE4;nda ett s&amp;#xE5;dant begrepp n&amp;#xE4;r man rekryterar &amp;#xE4;r jag v&amp;#xE4;ldigt skeptisk till. Det &amp;#xF6;ppnar f&amp;#xF6;r godtycke, missf&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5;nd och i f&amp;#xF6;rl&amp;#xE4;ngningen d&amp;#xE5;liga rekryteringar. Jag tror att det &amp;#xE4;r viktigt att ha tydliga kriterier uppsatta n&amp;#xE4;r man letar nya medarbetare. Speciellt n&amp;#xE4;r man ofta &amp;#xE4;r ett helt g&amp;#xE4;ng som tillsammans bed&amp;#xF6;mer olika aspekter av olika kandidater &amp;#xE4;r det viktigt att ha ett tydligt gemensamt spr&amp;#xE5;k. Konsultm&amp;#xE4;ssighet &amp;#xE4;r s&amp;#xE5; l&amp;#xE5;ngt ifr&amp;#xE5;n tydligt som man kan komma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vad ska man d&amp;#xE5; anv&amp;#xE4;nda ist&amp;#xE4;llet? Well, det &amp;#xE4;r en icke alldeles trivial fr&amp;#xE5;ga. Att ers&amp;#xE4;tta ett flummigt och vagt begrepp med konkreta och specifika ers&amp;#xE4;ttare &amp;#xE4;r av naturen sv&amp;#xE5;rt, och det kommer alltid att kl&amp;#xE4;mmas en del t&amp;#xE5;r i processen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag har dock ett par f&amp;#xF6;rslag p&amp;#xE5; saker som man kan utv&amp;#xE4;rdera ist&amp;#xE4;llet. Det &amp;#xE4;r ingen komplett lista, men jag skulle hellre anv&amp;#xE4;nda den h&amp;#xE4;r listan &amp;#xE4;n att ge mig p&amp;#xE5; att f&amp;#xF6;rs&amp;#xF6;ka bed&amp;#xF6;ma &amp;quot;konsultm&amp;#xE4;ssighet&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Utseende.&lt;/strong&gt; Tror ni att jag sk&amp;#xE4;mtar? G&amp;#xF6;r inte det. Utseendet &amp;#xE4;r viktigt, som jag var inne p&amp;#xE5; i f&amp;#xF6;rra bloggposten. Det handlar om att inte sticka ut f&amp;#xF6;r mycket p&amp;#xE5; fel s&amp;#xE4;tt, och det handlar om att veta vad man kan utl&amp;#xE4;sa fr&amp;#xE5;n n&amp;#xE5;gons utseende. Det &amp;#xE4;r f&amp;#xF6;rst&amp;#xE5;s inte bara om kl&amp;#xE4;der som spelar roll utan &amp;#xE4;ven frisyr, h&amp;#xE5;llning, form, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trevlighet.&lt;/strong&gt; V&amp;#xE4;ldigt enkelt. Gillar man personen eller inte? Troligtvis kommer andra att g&amp;#xF6;ra en liknande bed&amp;#xF6;mning, och det &amp;#xE4;r viktigt att inte anst&amp;#xE4;lla personer som ingen gillar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aff&amp;#xE4;rssinne.&lt;/strong&gt; Oj oj. H&amp;#xE4;r har vi ett potentiellt flumbegrepp igen. Men jag h&amp;#xE4;vdar att det &amp;#xE4;r tillr&amp;#xE4;ckligt anv&amp;#xE4;ndbart f&amp;#xF6;r att kunna vara med h&amp;#xE4;r, samt att det f&amp;#xE5;ngar en viktig del av det man brukar mena med konsultm&amp;#xE4;ssighet. Det handlar helt enkelt om man har en k&amp;#xE4;nsla f&amp;#xF6;r att det man levererar ska vara av v&amp;#xE4;rde f&amp;#xF6;r kunden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sammantaget tror jag att det &amp;#xE4;r viktigt att man inte hymlar med vad man faktiskt bed&amp;#xF6;mer. Det g&amp;#xE4;ller ocks&amp;#xE5; att veta varf&amp;#xF6;r man vill ha anst&amp;#xE4;llda med vissa egenskaper. Vad &amp;#xE4;r det som egentligen spelar roll?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fotnot: Jag har inte jobbat j&amp;#xE4;ttemycket med rekrytering och jag kommer s&amp;#xE4;kert f&amp;#xE5; anledning att revidera och utveckla ovanst&amp;#xE5;ende resonemang fram&amp;#xF6;ver. Jag kommer ocks&amp;#xE5; att &amp;#xE5;terkomma till andra aspekter p&amp;#xE5; rekrytering och konsultrollen, s&amp;#xE5;v&amp;#xE4;l som andra delar av konsultspr&amp;#xE5;ket.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Dresscode</title><id >adresscode2010-12-20t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/dresscode"></link><updated >2010-12-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;N&amp;#xE4;r jag skulle &amp;#xE5;ka t&amp;#xE5;g fr&amp;#xE5;n S&amp;#xF6;derhamn till Uppsala en sommar f&amp;#xF6;r n&amp;#xE5;gra &amp;#xE5;r sedan hade jag p&amp;#xE5; mig ett par trasiga jeans. V&amp;#xE4;ldigt trasiga jeans. Men det var sommarlov och jag var obrydd, precis som vanligt. Jag kommer ih&amp;#xE5;g det f&amp;#xF6;r att den &amp;#xE4;ldre sl&amp;#xE4;kting som skjutsade mig till stationen var synnerligen uppr&amp;#xF6;rd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag har aldrig varit v&amp;#xE4;lkl&amp;#xE4;dd. T-shirt och jeans har varit min uniform till vardags s&amp;#xE5;v&amp;#xE4;l som fest fr&amp;#xE5;n barnsben. N&amp;#xE4;r jag blev klar med studierna b&amp;#xE4;vade jag f&amp;#xF6;r att beh&amp;#xF6;va byta ut garderoben. Mitt f&amp;#xF6;rsta jobb innebar dock ingen direkt f&amp;#xF6;r&amp;#xE4;ndring fr&amp;#xE5;n studietiden, mer &amp;#xE4;n att de mest slitna paltorna fick ligga kvar i garderoben. Jag tr&amp;#xE4;ffade &amp;#xE4;nd&amp;#xE5; kunder v&amp;#xE4;ldigt s&amp;#xE4;llan &amp;#x2013; vi hade inte s&amp;#xE5; m&amp;#xE5;nga &amp;#x2013; och de flesta andra av kollegorna var mer eller mindre n&amp;#xF6;rdiga programmerare och s&amp;#xE5;g ut som programmerare g&amp;#xF6;r.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;N&amp;#xE4;r jag tog klivet till det Stora Konsultf&amp;#xF6;retaget d&amp;#xE4;remot var jag s&amp;#xE5; illa tvungen att bli vuxen &amp;#xE4;ven i kl&amp;#xE4;dv&amp;#xE4;g. Ut med hoodies och band-tshirts och in med skjorta och kavaj. Snabbt ins&amp;#xE5;g jag att det inte r&amp;#xE4;ckte med att k&amp;#xF6;pa det som fanns av m&amp;#xE4;rket &amp;quot;Kostym&amp;quot; p&amp;#xE5; Weekday heller. Skjortorna blir skrynkliga s&amp;#xE5; fort man tittar p&amp;#xE5; dem och man ser ut som en bortkommen praktikant. Det &amp;#xE4;r inte det intrycket man vill g&amp;#xF6;ra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det b&amp;#xE4;r mig emot att f&amp;#xF6;lja str&amp;#xF6;mmen, hoppa in i l&amp;#xE4;mmelt&amp;#xE5;get och bli precis som alla andra. Jag har aldrig jobbat f&amp;#xF6;r att passa in, s&amp;#xE5; varf&amp;#xF6;r m&amp;#xE5;ste jag g&amp;#xF6;ra det nu? Det &amp;#xE4;r v&amp;#xE4;l &amp;#xE4;nd&amp;#xE5; det jag presterar som &amp;#xE4;r av vikt? Well, som konsult har du inte mycket tid p&amp;#xE5; dig. Du m&amp;#xE5;ste kunna g&amp;#xF6;ra ett bra intryck p&amp;#xE5; vem som helst n&amp;#xE4;r som helst. Vissa dagar sitter du i ett h&amp;#xF6;rn och tr&amp;#xE4;ffar knappt en k&amp;#xE4;ft p&amp;#xE5; hela dagen. N&amp;#xE4;sta dagen kastas du in i ett kundm&amp;#xF6;te p&amp;#xE5; f&amp;#xF6;rmiddagen, lunchar med chefen och h&amp;#xE5;ller i en intervju p&amp;#xE5; eftermiddagen. Om du d&amp;#xE5; sticker ut f&amp;#xF6;r mycket fr&amp;#xE5;n det vedertagna hamnar fokus p&amp;#xE5; det ist&amp;#xE4;llet f&amp;#xF6;r p&amp;#xE5; det v&amp;#xE4;sentliga. Dessutom f&amp;#xF6;rmedlar dina kl&amp;#xE4;der en ganska tydlig indikation av vem du &amp;#xE4;r.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;s-h-r-k-nner-du-igen-olika-typer-av-konsulter&quot;&gt;S&amp;#xE5; h&amp;#xE4;r k&amp;#xE4;nner du igen olika typer av konsulter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#xBB; &lt;strong&gt;Kostym med slips&lt;/strong&gt; och han &amp;#xE4;r managementkonsult. Inte bara det. Han har inte varit teknikkonsult, hans fr&amp;#xE4;msta verktyg &amp;#xE4;r PowerPoint och han tycker att Excel &amp;#xE4;r ett avancerat programmeringsspr&amp;#xE5;k, utan att ana hur n&amp;#xE4;ra sanningen han &amp;#xE4;r. Alternativt jobbar han i finansbranchen. D&amp;#xE4;r har alla slips. I s&amp;#xE5; fall m&amp;#xE5;ste man kolla p&amp;#xE5; sko-, och kostymkvalitet f&amp;#xF6;r att artbest&amp;#xE4;mma honom. Billigt = kodapa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#xBB; &lt;strong&gt;Skjorta + kavaj eller kostymbyxor med skjorta och stickad tr&amp;#xF6;ja&lt;/strong&gt;. Managementkonsult som kan skriva &amp;quot;Hello World!&amp;quot; i minst tv&amp;#xE5; spr&amp;#xE5;k, alternativt kodapa med ambitioner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#xBB; &lt;strong&gt;Skjorta + jeans eller jeans + stickad tr&amp;#xF6;ja&lt;/strong&gt;. Kodapa, m&amp;#xF6;jligtvis med illusioner om att komma h&amp;#xF6;gre upp i v&amp;#xE4;rdekedjan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#xBB; &lt;strong&gt;Hipsteruniform&lt;/strong&gt;. Designer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#xBB; &lt;strong&gt;Jeans + t-shirt + kulmage&lt;/strong&gt;. Troligtvis inte konsult. Kan kanske vara k&amp;#xE4;llarkodapa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Detta &amp;#xE4;r vad folk kommer att se. F&amp;#xF6;r att ge det intrycket du &amp;#xE4;r ute efter g&amp;#xF6;r du b&amp;#xE4;st i att n&amp;#xE5;got s&amp;#xE5;n&amp;#xE4;r f&amp;#xF6;lja dessa normer. Det beh&amp;#xF6;ver definitivt inte betyda att man f&amp;#xF6;rsakar all individualism. Det finns m&amp;#xE5;nga detaljer att arbeta med. Mode handlar om detaljer. Men att vara konsult handlar om att vara str&amp;#xF6;mlinjeformad. N&amp;#xE5;got jag kommer &amp;#xE5;terkomma till.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fotnot: N&amp;#xE5;gon kanske t&amp;#xE4;nker att jag osynligg&amp;#xF6;r kvinnor genom att endast prata om manliga kl&amp;#xE4;der. Men det borde vara ganska uppenbart att jag inte kan s&amp;#xE4;rskilt mycket om kvinnor eller deras kl&amp;#xE4;der. Jag publicerar dock g&amp;#xE4;rna en text fr&amp;#xE5;n n&amp;#xE5;gon som k&amp;#xE4;nner sig mer kompetent p&amp;#xE5; det omr&amp;#xE5;det. Det skulle vara intressant.
Fotnot 2: Ordet kodapa kan l&amp;#xE5;ta nedv&amp;#xE4;rderande. Ta det inte s&amp;#xE5;. utan dem skulle inget i v&amp;#xE4;rlden funka. Geeks rule the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Individualism r inte s poppis</title><id >aindividualismarintesapoppis2010-12-15t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="undefinedblog/individualism-r-inte-s-poppis"></link><updated >2010-12-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jantelagen lever onekligen, men har till viss del bytt skepnad. Det &amp;#xE4;r helt ok att tro att man &amp;#xE4;r n&amp;#xE5;got och att man kan n&amp;#xE5;got. D&amp;#xE4;remot &amp;#xE4;r det inte ok att tycka, g&amp;#xF6;ra eller vara intresserad av fel saker. Man ska vara politiskt medveten, &amp;#xE4;ta r&amp;#xE4;tt, t&amp;#xE4;nka p&amp;#xE5; klimatet och vara lagom &amp;#xF6;dmjuk. D&amp;#xE4;rf&amp;#xF6;r r&amp;#xF6;rde G&amp;#xF6;ran H&amp;#xE4;gglunds kampanj i somras upp s&amp;#xE5; m&amp;#xE5;nga k&amp;#xE4;nslor  - f&amp;#xF6;r Verklighetens folk &amp;#xE4;r just svennarna som inte bryr sig. De ska ju motarbetas och h&amp;#xE5;nas, inte omfamnas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fredrik Lindstr&amp;#xF6;m &amp;amp; Henrik Schyffert har en ny &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.svd.se/kulturnoje/nyheter/fredrik-lindstrom-och-henrik-schyffert-tar-sig-an-inredningshysterin_5178877.svd&quot;&gt;krogshow&lt;/a&gt; med ett enkelt tema: det &amp;#xE4;r inte ok att vara intresserad av inredning. Det &amp;#xE4;r inte ok att bry sig mer om sitt hem &amp;#xE4;n om &amp;quot;v&amp;#xE4;rldsproblemen&amp;quot;. Det g&amp;#xE5;r i samma sp&amp;#xE5;r som reaktionerna p&amp;#xE5; DN:s artikel &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dn.se/bostad/vindsvaningar-har-blivit-ett-satt-att-leva-1.1185309&quot;&gt;Vindsv&amp;#xE5;ningar har blivit ett s&amp;#xE4;tt att leva&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, d&amp;#xE4;r b&amp;#xE5;de skribenten Sara Trus och paret som det handlar om fick utst&amp;#xE5; veckor av h&amp;#xE5;n och okv&amp;#xE4;dningsord fr&amp;#xE5;n en enad twittermobb, med just Schyffert i frontlinjen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Att just inredningsintresset &amp;#xE4;r mest utsatt f&amp;#xF6;r detta hat beror nog p&amp;#xE5; att det representerar inte bara en politisk obryddhet, utan &amp;#xE4;ven en annan hatad egenskap - rikedom. Inte f&amp;#xF6;r att man n&amp;#xF6;dv&amp;#xE4;ndigtvis m&amp;#xE5;ste vara politiskt ointresserad f&amp;#xF6;r att man vill bo vackert, men det &amp;#xE4;r en ytterst opolitisk aktivitet. Just d&amp;#xE4;rf&amp;#xF6;r ses det som ett s&amp;#xE5; kraftigt politiskt statement: &amp;quot;Jag &amp;#xE4;r rik och inte intresserad&amp;quot;. Men samma k&amp;#xE4;nslor riktas mot dem som noga &amp;#xF6;verv&amp;#xE4;ger vilken 52&amp;quot; platt-tv man ska k&amp;#xF6;pa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modebloggare, datorspelare, k&amp;#xF6;tt&amp;#xE4;tare, Thailandsresen&amp;#xE4;re och r&amp;#xF6;kare &amp;#xE4;r bara n&amp;#xE5;gra av de som ocks&amp;#xE5; f&amp;#xE5;r en sl&amp;#xE4;ng av sleven d&amp;#xE5; och d&amp;#xE5;. Jantelagen blandas med moralism och blir till en ovanligt osmaklig soppa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det fina i kr&amp;#xE5;ks&amp;#xE5;ngen &amp;#xE4;r att de bespottade inte bryr sig. Det &amp;#xE4;r ett krig som bara utk&amp;#xE4;mpas av en sida, medan de attackerade bara v&amp;#xE4;nder ryggen till. D&amp;#xE4;rf&amp;#xF6;r kommer de ocks&amp;#xE5; att vinna. Skulle de d&amp;#xE4;remot b&amp;#xF6;rja f&amp;#xF6;rsvara sig skulle de f&amp;#xE5; det sv&amp;#xE5;rare. Det kanske &amp;#xE4;r d&amp;#xE4;rf&amp;#xF6;r Kristdemokraterna bara har 3,2% i senaste opinionsm&amp;#xE4;tningen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag passar p&amp;#xE5; att puffa f&amp;#xF6;r fantastiska &lt;a href=&quot;http://store.yankodesign.com/&quot;&gt;Yanko Design&lt;/a&gt;. D&amp;#xE4;r finns det grejer.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>