<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title >eldh.co</title><link href="http://eldh.co/atom.xml" rel="self"> </link><link href="http://eldh.co/"> </link><updated >2015-04-11T16:02:28+02:00</updated><id >http://eldh.co/</id><author ><name >Andreas Eldh</name><email >andreas.eldh@gmail.com</email></author><entry ><title >Individualism är inte så poppis</title><id >aindividualismarintesapoppis2010-12-15t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/individualism-r-inte-s-poppis"></link><updated >2010-12-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jantelagen lever onekligen, men har till viss del bytt skepnad. Det är helt ok att tro att man är något och att man kan något. Däremot är det inte ok att tycka, göra eller vara intresserad av fel saker. Man ska vara politiskt medveten, äta rätt, tänka på klimatet och vara lagom ödmjuk. Därför rörde Göran Hägglunds kampanj i somras upp så många känslor  - för Verklighetens folk är just svennarna som inte bryr sig. De ska ju motarbetas och hånas, inte omfamnas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fredrik Lindström &amp;amp; Henrik Schyffert har en ny &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.svd.se/kulturnoje/nyheter/fredrik-lindstrom-och-henrik-schyffert-tar-sig-an-inredningshysterin_5178877.svd&quot;&gt;krogshow&lt;/a&gt; med ett enkelt tema: det är inte ok att vara intresserad av inredning. Det är inte ok att bry sig mer om sitt hem än om &amp;quot;världsproblemen&amp;quot;. Det går i samma spår som reaktionerna på DN:s artikel &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dn.se/bostad/vindsvaningar-har-blivit-ett-satt-att-leva-1.1185309&quot;&gt;Vindsvåningar har blivit ett sätt att leva&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, där både skribenten Sara Trus och paret som det handlar om fick utstå veckor av hån och okvädningsord från en enad twittermobb, med just Schyffert i frontlinjen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Att just inredningsintresset är mest utsatt för detta hat beror nog på att det representerar inte bara en politisk obryddhet, utan även en annan hatad egenskap - rikedom. Inte för att man nödvändigtvis måste vara politiskt ointresserad för att man vill bo vackert, men det är en ytterst opolitisk aktivitet. Just därför ses det som ett så kraftigt politiskt statement: &amp;quot;Jag är rik och inte intresserad&amp;quot;. Men samma känslor riktas mot dem som noga överväger vilken 52&amp;quot; platt-tv man ska köpa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modebloggare, datorspelare, köttätare, Thailandsresenäre och rökare är bara några av de som också får en släng av sleven då och då. Jantelagen blandas med moralism och blir till en ovanligt osmaklig soppa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det fina i kråksången är att de bespottade inte bryr sig. Det är ett krig som bara utkämpas av en sida, medan de attackerade bara vänder ryggen till. Därför kommer de också att vinna. Skulle de däremot börja försvara sig skulle de få det svårare. Det kanske är därför Kristdemokraterna bara har 3,2% i senaste opinionsmätningen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag passar på att puffa för fantastiska &lt;a href=&quot;http://store.yankodesign.com/&quot;&gt;Yanko Design&lt;/a&gt;. Där finns det grejer.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Dresscode</title><id >adresscode2010-12-20t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/dresscode"></link><updated >2010-12-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;När jag skulle åka tåg från Söderhamn till Uppsala en sommar för några år sedan hade jag på mig ett par trasiga jeans. Väldigt trasiga jeans. Men det var sommarlov och jag var obrydd, precis som vanligt. Jag kommer ihåg det för att den äldre släkting som skjutsade mig till stationen var synnerligen upprörd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag har aldrig varit välklädd. T-shirt och jeans har varit min uniform till vardags såväl som fest från barnsben. När jag blev klar med studierna bävade jag för att behöva byta ut garderoben. Mitt första jobb innebar dock ingen direkt förändring från studietiden, mer än att de mest slitna paltorna fick ligga kvar i garderoben. Jag träffade ändå kunder väldigt sällan – vi hade inte så många – och de flesta andra av kollegorna var mer eller mindre nördiga programmerare och såg ut som programmerare gör.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;När jag tog klivet till det Stora Konsultföretaget däremot var jag så illa tvungen att bli vuxen även i klädväg. Ut med hoodies och band-tshirts och in med skjorta och kavaj. Snabbt insåg jag att det inte räckte med att köpa det som fanns av märket &amp;quot;Kostym&amp;quot; på Weekday heller. Skjortorna blir skrynkliga så fort man tittar på dem och man ser ut som en bortkommen praktikant. Det är inte det intrycket man vill göra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det bär mig emot att följa strömmen, hoppa in i lämmeltåget och bli precis som alla andra. Jag har aldrig jobbat för att passa in, så varför måste jag göra det nu? Det är väl ändå det jag presterar som är av vikt? Well, som konsult har du inte mycket tid på dig. Du måste kunna göra ett bra intryck på vem som helst när som helst. Vissa dagar sitter du i ett hörn och träffar knappt en käft på hela dagen. Nästa dagen kastas du in i ett kundmöte på förmiddagen, lunchar med chefen och håller i en intervju på eftermiddagen. Om du då sticker ut för mycket från det vedertagna hamnar fokus på det istället för på det väsentliga. Dessutom förmedlar dina kläder en ganska tydlig indikation av vem du är.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Så här känner du igen olika typer av konsulter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;» &lt;strong&gt;Kostym med slips&lt;/strong&gt; och han är managementkonsult. Inte bara det. Han har inte varit teknikkonsult, hans främsta verktyg är PowerPoint och han tycker att Excel är ett avancerat programmeringsspråk, utan att ana hur nära sanningen han är. Alternativt jobbar han i finansbranchen. Där har alla slips. I så fall måste man kolla på sko-, och kostymkvalitet för att artbestämma honom. Billigt = kodapa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;» &lt;strong&gt;Skjorta + kavaj eller kostymbyxor med skjorta och stickad tröja&lt;/strong&gt;. Managementkonsult som kan skriva &amp;quot;Hello World!&amp;quot; i minst två språk, alternativt kodapa med ambitioner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;» &lt;strong&gt;Skjorta + jeans eller jeans + stickad tröja&lt;/strong&gt;. Kodapa, möjligtvis med illusioner om att komma högre upp i värdekedjan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;» &lt;strong&gt;Hipsteruniform&lt;/strong&gt;. Designer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;» &lt;strong&gt;Jeans + t-shirt + kulmage&lt;/strong&gt;. Troligtvis inte konsult. Kan kanske vara källarkodapa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Detta är vad folk kommer att se. För att ge det intrycket du är ute efter gör du bäst i att något sånär följa dessa normer. Det behöver definitivt inte betyda att man försakar all individualism. Det finns många detaljer att arbeta med. Mode handlar om detaljer. Men att vara konsult handlar om att vara strömlinjeformad. Något jag kommer återkomma till.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fotnot: Någon kanske tänker att jag osynliggör kvinnor genom att endast prata om manliga kläder. Men det borde vara ganska uppenbart att jag inte kan särskilt mycket om kvinnor eller deras kläder. Jag publicerar dock gärna en text från någon som känner sig mer kompetent på det området. Det skulle vara intressant.
Fotnot 2: Ordet kodapa kan låta nedvärderande. Ta det inte så. utan dem skulle inget i världen funka. Geeks rule the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >&quot;Konsultmässighet&quot;</title><id >aquotkonsultmassighetquot2011-01-03t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/konsultmssighet"></link><updated >2011-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ska du vara it-konsult krävs det att du har en hel kunskaper och färdigheter. Du ska kunna lära dig snabbt, sätta dig in i nya saker och vara kompetent inom ditt område. Men det finns en egenskap som trumfar alla andra: &lt;strong&gt;Konsultmässighet&lt;/strong&gt;. Vad är då detta?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bryt sönder ordet: Konsultmässig. Liknande en konsult. För att bli konsult ska du alltså vara som en konsult är.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hur är då en konsult? En konsult är trevlig, tillmötesgående och flexibel. En konsult är representabel. En god ambassadör för sitt företag. Egentligen handlar det om samma princip som när det gäller &lt;a href=&quot;http://eldh.co/tankar/dresscode&quot;&gt;dresscode&lt;/a&gt;. Stick. Inte. Ut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Många skulle säkert läsa in fler saker i begreppet konsultmässighet - intresse för affärsnytta, social kompetens etc. etc. Sannolikt skiljer begreppets innebörd också kraftigt på olika företag och till och med mellan olika personer som jobbar med varandra. Däri ligger problemet. Konsultbranchen är full av flummiga begrepp. Alla brancher har väl sin egen vokabulär. Det handlar dels om effektivitet, men även om att skapa en tillhörighet. Inget fel med det. När man är där inne är bägge sakerna viktiga.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men &amp;quot;konsultmässighet&amp;quot; används framförallt i rekryteringsprocessen. För att sålla. Att använda ett sådant begrepp när man rekryterar är jag väldigt skeptisk till. Det öppnar för godtycke, missförstånd och i förlängningen dåliga rekryteringar. Jag tror att det är viktigt att ha tydliga kriterier uppsatta när man letar nya medarbetare. Speciellt när man ofta är ett helt gäng som tillsammans bedömer olika aspekter av olika kandidater är det viktigt att ha ett tydligt gemensamt språk. Konsultmässighet är så långt ifrån tydligt som man kan komma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vad ska man då använda istället? Well, det är en icke alldeles trivial fråga. Att ersätta ett flummigt och vagt begrepp med konkreta och specifika ersättare är av naturen svårt, och det kommer alltid att klämmas en del tår i processen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag har dock ett par förslag på saker som man kan utvärdera istället. Det är ingen komplett lista, men jag skulle hellre använda den här listan än att ge mig på att försöka bedöma &amp;quot;konsultmässighet&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Utseende.&lt;/strong&gt; Tror ni att jag skämtar? Gör inte det. Utseendet är viktigt, som jag var inne på i förra bloggposten. Det handlar om att inte sticka ut för mycket på fel sätt, och det handlar om att veta vad man kan utläsa från någons utseende. Det är förstås inte bara om kläder som spelar roll utan även frisyr, hållning, form, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trevlighet.&lt;/strong&gt; Väldigt enkelt. Gillar man personen eller inte? Troligtvis kommer andra att göra en liknande bedömning, och det är viktigt att inte anställa personer som ingen gillar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Affärssinne.&lt;/strong&gt; Oj oj. Här har vi ett potentiellt flumbegrepp igen. Men jag hävdar att det är tillräckligt användbart för att kunna vara med här, samt att det fångar en viktig del av det man brukar mena med konsultmässighet. Det handlar helt enkelt om man har en känsla för att det man levererar ska vara av värde för kunden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sammantaget tror jag att det är viktigt att man inte hymlar med vad man faktiskt bedömer. Det gäller också att veta varför man vill ha anställda med vissa egenskaper. Vad är det som egentligen spelar roll?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fotnot: Jag har inte jobbat jättemycket med rekrytering och jag kommer säkert få anledning att revidera och utveckla ovanstående resonemang framöver. Jag kommer också att återkomma till andra aspekter på rekrytering och konsultrollen, såväl som andra delar av konsultspråket.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Relationer 101</title><id >arelationer1012011-01-14t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/relationer-101"></link><updated >2011-01-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jag och Internet kom till Sverige ungefär samtidigt, för knappa 27 år sedan. Vi har växt upp tillsammans och är en naturlig del av varandras liv. Vi är generationsbröder. Vi förstår varandra. Därtill har jag alltid varit intresserad av datorer, teknik och kommunikation, både privat och yrkesmässigt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En del saker som ter sig självklara för mig verkar helt ha gått andra förbi. Det beror kanske på generationsskillnader, teknikanalfabetism eller bara brist på intresse, men många verkar inte ha reflekterat särskilt mycketöver de många sätt som Internet har förändrat samhället och oss som är en del av det.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bengt Ohlsson har en &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pastan.nu/bloggen/inlagg/3345&quot;&gt;krönika i gårdagens DN&lt;/a&gt; om hur Facebook skapar en illusion av att man är social och att man har låtsasvänner istället för riktiga vänner. Det är sådant som jag vanligtvis skulle låta passera, för det är absolut ingen ny &amp;quot;kritik&amp;quot;. Tvärtom är det i princip den enda sortens kritik som har riktats mot Facebook, borträknat diverse integritetskontroverser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag tror att den här sortens kritik frodas på grund av en ganska basal begreppsförvirring. Kritikerna utgår från att en vänskap på Internet är samma sak som en vänskap var när de växte upp, i den &amp;quot;riktiga&amp;quot; världen. Men att bli vän någon på Facebook är inte samma sak som att vara vänner i verkliga livet. Det liknar faktiskt ingen sorts relation som funnits tidigare i historien, för att det sättet att kommunicera som har växt fram på de sociala medierna liknar inget som tidigare varit möjligt. Allt det här gäller förstås alla sorters sociala medier, men Facebook får utstå mest kritik för att där är begreppsförvirringen som störst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag är vän på Facebook med personer som jag aldrig träffat, som jag träffat bara ett par gånger och de som jag träffar varje dag. Det är folk som jag har mycket gemensamt med, lite gemensamt med och inget gemensamt med. Låt mig ta ett exempel på hur de här relationerna och kommunikationen kan fungera:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I somras skulle jag och en vän (i ordets äldre bemärkelse) åka ut på semester i Europa. Jag skrev ett Facebookinlägg och frågade om någon ville med. En bekant som jag jobbat med året innan svarade att han också tänkt resa i Europa under samma period. Vi slog våra påsar ihop och med varsitt InterRailkort drog vi oss söderut. Under resan uppdaterade jag förstås min omvärld om var vi var och vad vi gjorde, och när jag noterade att det regnade i Prag fick jag ett meddelande från en amerikan som jag träffat ett par gånger i när jag bodde i Australien två år tidigare. Han var i Prag och hälsade på sin faster och vi bestämde oss för att träffas. Efter ett par trevliga dagar tillsammans i Prag for vi vidare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I Facebook-världen skapar man band till folk man annars sedan länge skulle ha glömt bort. Man masskommunicerar. Man har lösa relationer, relationer som skulle ha varit omöjliga utan den sortens kommunikation. Jag hade inte haft en aning om att min vän hade varit intresserad av att följa med ut i Europa, och jag hade inte haft en aning om att amerikanen var i Prag samtidigt som jag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men de lösa relationerna behöver inte leda till fysiska möten.  Även en kommentar här och där, en tumme upp när man gillar något, är en del av de lösa vänskapsband som man nu kan skapa. Dessa relationer annorlunda än vad många är vana vid, och anses därför vara mindre värda. Vissa personer som vi har relationer med på sociala nätverk är sådana som vi inte vill umgås med bortanför datorskärmen, enligt Bengt Ohlsson ett fantastiskt exempel på att allt bara är på låtsas. Men man kan ha ett relevant utbyte, även om det inte tar fysisk form. Och naturligtvis har man inte ens lust att umgås digitalt med alla gamla gymnasiekompisar. Det behöver man förstås inte heller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Den andra delen av kritiken är att facebook tränger ut det &amp;quot;riktiga&amp;quot; umgänget och ersätter det med en illusion. För det första är det att förringa värdet av nätrelationer. Det är förstås upp till var och en att bedöma olika relationer med olika personer, men att säga att alla relationer på nätet är på låtsas är inte seriöst. För det andra håller jag inte med om att fysiska relationer trängs ut. Självklart kan det bli för mycket facebook, men jag tycker generellt att nätvänskaper lever ett symbiotiskt liv med gammaldags relationer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man måste hitta sin egen balans mellan nätrelationer och fysiska relationer, men utan att förringa någon av dem. Om man inte förstår att nya kommunikationssätt skapar nya sorters relationer kommer man, precis som Bengt Ohlsson, att undra hur man kan vara ensam om man har 1000 facebookvänner.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Till den stelbenta byråkratins försvar</title><id >atilldenstelbentabyrakratinsforsvar2011-01-28t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/till-den-stelbenta-byrkratins-frsvar"></link><updated >2011-01-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Det klagas ofta på byråkrati. Det är ju så enkelt att tycka att folk bara skulle använda sitt vanliga sunda förnuft. Jag har tänkt liknande tankar själv, precis som de flesta antar jag, och sådana åsikter är oftast svåra att argumentera mot. Vad då &amp;quot;Nej, jag tycker inte att folk borde använda sina vanliga sunda förnuft&amp;quot;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men ju mer jag tänker på det desto mer tycker jag att det byråkratin behöver är fanatiska tillskyndare. Om folk skulle använda sina &amp;quot;sunda förnuft&amp;quot; skulle det ta hus i helvete kan jag säga. (Se där, ännu ett exempel på &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=136332289764451&amp;set=a.136332286431118.26053.136094543121559&quot;&gt;korrekt användande av citationstecken&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stelbent byråkrati innebär att de som handlägger ärenden, exempelvis på Försäkringskassan, till punkt och pricka följer de regelverk som finns. De senaste åren – ja, så länge mitt unga huvud kan minnas egentligen – har en rad fall uppmärksammats där detta har orsakat individer mer eller mindre omfattande skada. Vem minns till exempel inte Fallet Annica som livade upp veckorna innan valet i höstas? Allt sunt förnuft talar för att man i vissa fall ska kunna kringgå reglerna. Medierna älskar förstås också häxjakter där man kan åberopa sunt förnuft och svartmåla såväl byråkratin som det regelverk som den stödjer sig på.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regelverk som är dåliga ska kritiseras&lt;/strong&gt;. Men byråkratin ska kritiseras endast om den inte gör sitt jobb – alltså om den inte följer reglerna. Hade en proteststorm flugit upp om Annica Holmquist hade fått sjukförsäkring på grund av att någon handläggare kringgått reglerna? I think not. Hade då de felaktiga reglerna ändrats? I think not. Går handläggare runt reglerna kommer våra lagstiftare undan med värdelösa regelverk, och vi får istället ett samhälle där varje enskilt fall avgörs av handläggarens godtycke och det enda man har att luta sig mot är regelverk som kan vara hur otydliga eller orättvisa som helst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men det finns mer. Likhet inför lagen, förutsägbarhet är till exempel saker som brukar tas upp men som jag inte tycker det är värt att orera om just här.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vanligt sunt förnuft är inte vanligt.&lt;/strong&gt; Folk har nog väldigt olika uppfattning om vad sunt förnuft innebär. Det är ett särdeles fluffigt begrepp. I hur många frågor man få samma svar om vad som var sunt om man frågade en vänsterpartist respektive en Sverigedemokrat? Tror ni de skulle göra samma bedömningar om de arbetade som handläggare och kunde tillämpa sitt eget sunda förnuft? Om man skulle uppmuntra en större andel sunt förnuft skulle man överlämna makt åt en hel massa anonyma tjänstemän som skulle kunna agera helt utefter eget tycke. Det skulle i sin tur kräva att deras tycke sammanföll med den linje som regeringen har beslutat om. Alltså skulle det riskera att leda till politisk likriktning och självcensur. Jag har inget till övers för varken (V) eller (SD) men deras sympatisörer måste likväl kunna ta tjänstemannajobb utan att förstöra systemet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stelbent byråkrati en en förutsättning för snabb ärendehantering.&lt;/strong&gt; En kritik som riktas mot byråkrati är att den är långsam. Handläggningstider på X antal månader etc. Enda sättet att få bort den långsamma byråkratin är att göra den så stelbent att den kan automatiseras. Ju fler processer som kan skötas utan inblandning av handläggare, desto mer tid får de till att hantera de ärenden som verkligen behöver en människas uppmärksamhet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Känner inte att jag uttömt ämnet, så jag kanske återkommer. Bite sized snacks är min devis.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >En principsak</title><id >aenprincipsak2011-02-14t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/en-principsak"></link><updated >2011-02-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Roland Poirier Martinsson skriver i senaste Neo om Wikileaks. Han gillar verkligen inte Wikileaks, vilket förstås inte är någon nyhet för oss som sett hans &lt;a href=&quot;http://svtplay.se/v/2262698/gomorron_sverige/debatt_om_wikileaks_publiceringar&quot;&gt;tidigare&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tv4play.se/nyheter_och_debatt/nyhetsmorgon?title=debatt_behandlar_svensk_media_wikileaks_for_okritiskt&amp;videoid=1160831&quot;&gt;debatter&lt;/a&gt; och &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.svd.se/opinion/ledarsidan/moraliskt-moras-under-wikileaks_5804255.svd&quot;&gt;artiklar&lt;/a&gt; i ämnet. Artikeln i Neo har ett antal poänger, av vilka en del kan bortses från utan vidare, som att han anser sig ha rätt för att alla andra debattörer tycker annorlunda, samt att vänstern borde tycka som honom eftersom de är emot yttrandefrihet. Vänsters motstånd mot yttrandefrihet har aldrig varit så starkt som deras aversion mot västvärlden i allmänhet och USA i synnerhet, den röda tråd som kan leda den sämste navigatör rätt i den socialistiska åsiktsdjungeln.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vidare anser RPM att liberaler som försvarar Wikileaks är obegripliga eftersom yttrandefriheten måste ha begränsningar och att det således hör till god liberal tradition att till exempel klassa sådant som kan vara skadligt för rikets säkerhet, individers integritet och säkerhet eller upphovsrättsinnehavares rättigheter, som illegalt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPM diskuterar även det amerikanska lagrummet och kommer fram till att wikileaks verksamhet med största säkerhet är fullkomligt laglig. Han hävdar dock att verksamheten skulle vara åtalbar i Sverige men utan att precisera exakt hur den skulle bryta mot ett av världens starkaste presskydd. Jag lämnar detta åt någon med mer juridiskt kunnande att bedöma. Hur som helst landar han i slutsatsen att Julian Assange bör åtalas, till skillnad mot de som läckte The Pentagon Papers, och till skillnad mot de tidningar som publicerat exakt samma uppgifter som Wikileaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Att RPM vill se Julian Assange skaka galler är ingen nyhet. För att vinna gillande för denna ståndpunkt väljer han (implicit) att anklaga Wikileaks för att själva ha stulit dokumenten de publicerar, vilket inget mig veteligen tyder på att de gjort. Det är av den anledningen Bradley Manning och ingen annan spenderar tjugotre timmar per dygn i isoleringscell utan någon rättegång i sikte.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Och där glider vi in på en annan del av RPM:s argumentation mot Wikileaks, nämligen att det är förkastligt att publicerar sådant som skadar &amp;quot;den demokratiska världen&amp;quot; och &amp;quot;det öppna samhället&amp;quot; istället för diktaturerna som den demokratiska världen för krig mot. Naturligtvis är USA ett mer demokratiskt land än de flesta andra i världen, men det betyder inte att det inte finns oegentligheter som mår bra av att avslöjas. Hade han argumenterat på samma sätt om dokument som visade att USA ljög inför Irakinvasionen? Och vad skiljer den argumentationen från den som diktaturerna själva använder för att stoppa intern kritik?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Min poäng är att den öppna världen måste kunna tåla en mycket hård journalistisk granskning, om den inte gör det är det ett tydligt tecken på att den är på väg bort från öppenheten. Då kan dess företrädare antingen välja att åter gå mot öppenhet eller att ytterligare sluta sig. Till slut handlar det om gränsdragningar, precis som RPM också konstaterar, och om man inte ser en plats för Wikileaks och liknande organisationer (som utan tvekan kommer att ploppa upp såväl till höger som vänster)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man kan vara kritisk mot Wikileaks av många anledningar – deras politiska agenda, deras dysfunktionella organisation och inte minst praktarslet Julian Assange. Men att använda dem som slagträ för att minska press- och yttrandefriheten eller möjligheten för whistleblowers att avslöja missförhållanden är inte önskvärt. Vilka åsikter en nyhetsförmedlare har och hur dessa i så fall gör sin nyhetsvärdering kan man absolut ha åsikter om, och i det avseendet är onekligen Wikileaks klandervärt. Däremot omfattar tryckfriheten även den som har avvikande mening. För det som skiljer Julian Assange och &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentagon_Papers&quot;&gt;Daniel Ellsberg&lt;/a&gt; åt är inte främst deras metoder, utan deras politiska åsikter. Och yttrandefrihetens gränser bör inte gå längs politiska skiljelinjer, som Roland Poirier Martinsson skulle vilja.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Som avslutning vill jag uttrycka en stilla förhoppning att rörelser liknande Wikileaks kan växa upp och sprida ljus över saker som pågår i skuggorna i exempelvis Iran, Kina, Israel, Ryssland etc.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Recension: Samsung Galaxy Ace</title><id >arecensionsamsunggalaxyace2011-02-21t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/recension-samsung-galaxy-ace"></link><updated >2011-02-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jag är en Apple-kille. Inget att sticka under stol med. Jag har två macar och en iPhone. När jag skulle ha en ny jobbtelefon tyckte jag dock att det var dags att besöka Android-världen, för att få lite perspektiv på tillvaron. Valet föll på Samsung Galaxy Ace, en mellanklassmodell som precis börjat landa i svenska butiker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifikationerna är inte överdrivet imponerande men med tanke på priset (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phonehouse.se/Mobiltelefoner/Samsung/Samsung-S5830-Galaxy-Ace&quot;&gt;3299:- hos Phone House&lt;/a&gt;) får den ändå anses prisvärd. 3,5&amp;quot;-skärm på 320x480 pixlar, 800MHz-processor, 5Mpx-kamera med blixt och Android 2.2 Froyo med Samsungs TouchWiz-UI är väl det viktigaste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lådan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Med telefonen följer ett micro-SD-kort på 2 GB med tillhörande adapter, en väggladdare, en USB-kabel och en instruktionsbok. Något headset har Samsung inte kostat på sig. Snålt kan tyckas, men inget jag stör mig på eftersom jag har ett bra Klipsch-headset redan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Utsidan&lt;/h2&gt;   
&lt;p&gt;En av sakerna som lockade hos Galaxy Ace var utseendet. Det är något inspirerat av iPhone 4, med den blanksvarta framsidan och metallbandet som går runt telefonen. Baksidan är gjord av greppvänlig gummiaktig plast med tydlig struktur. Den är lite plastig men känns ändå solid och välbyggd, dock kommer den inte i närheten av iPhone i den deltävlingen. Till och med min gamla 3GS är betydligt mer stabil en Acen. På/av-knappen sitter på högra sidan och volymknapparna på den vänstra. SD-kortet och micro-USB-uttaget sitter bakom varsina små luckor. Jag uppskattar att laddaren går in på ovansidan av telefonen. Det gör det enkelt att använda den även när den är inkopplad. Framsidan har en synlig knapp, som fungerar som hem-knapp, very iPhone-like. Det finns även två touch-knappar – &apos;bakåt&apos; och &apos;alternativ&apos; – som lyser upp när man håller på att klicka runt. Däremot är de inte alltid upplysta när man kan använda sig av dem, vilket är lite förvirrande. Baksidan har förutom kameran även ett par hål för högtalaren. Skärmen är inte särskilt högupplöst, men skäms inte för sig bredvid min iPhone 3GS. Färgerna känns till och med lite klarare på Galaxy Acen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Insidan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, jag har bara iPhone att jämföra med. Har testat lite olika Android-lurar också, men inte tillräckligt länge för att bilda mig en riktig uppfattning om operativsystemet. TouchWiz-gränssnittet känns dock ganska intuitivt och man kommer snabbt igång. Grafiken flyter inte på lika fint som på iPhone – det hackar lite grann när man scrollar runt. Det känns som att hårdvaran är i klenaste laget. Det är dock inte värre än att det ska ses som en kosmetisk miss snarare än en funktionell. Klart bättre än andra Android-lurar jag har testat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag är inte helt såld på upplägget med hemskärmar och &amp;quot;källaren&amp;quot; där alla appar finns, men jag tror nog jag kommer kunna vänja mig vid det också. Det är trevligt att man kan ha widgets på hemskärmen, men det är inte alltid syftet med dem känns alldeles solklart (hur meningsfullt är det t ex att se den senaste tweeten i sin feed?). Hur man ska strukturera hemskärmen är nog något man får pröva sig fram till. Jag passade snabbt på att byta launcher till &lt;a href=&quot;http://jbthemes.com/anderweb/&quot;&gt;ADW.launcher&lt;/a&gt;, som är betydligt mycket snabbare och trevligare än Samsungs orginal. Rekommenderar alla att göra detsamma!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det inbyggda tangentbordet är riktigt bra. Det enda jag stör mig på är att det byter uppsättning när man skiftar mellan gemener och versaler. Jag tappar bort mig bland versalerna. IPhone-lösningen med en &amp;quot;lysande&amp;quot; shift-knapp och ständiga versaler på tangenterna känns mycket smidigare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Android vs. Apple&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Med &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doubletwist.com/&quot;&gt;DoubleTwist&lt;/a&gt; går det smidigt att synka media med sin mac, även över WiFi om man skaffar &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doubletwist.com/airsync/&quot;&gt;AirSync-appen&lt;/a&gt; för 32 kronor. 1-0 till Android där. Applikationsutbudet däremot känns lite skralt på Android. Dels saknas en del lite mer obskyra appar (Funbeat, Viber etc) och dels är de appar som finns ofta lite sämre. Reeder och Twitter for iPhone, som är mina två mest använda appar, har exempelvis inga likvärdiga ersättare på Android (som jag har hittat, men jag har i ärlighetens namn bara letat väldigt kort). I övrigt är inställningsmöjligheterna tilltalande många. Det är bra om man vet hur man vill ha det, men är man ingen power user tror jag nog iOS bjuder på en långt bättre användarupplevelse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frågan är då, är den bättre eller sämre än min iPhone 3GS? Njae, jag väntar med den domen ett tag till. Gissningsvis kommer det fler delar i den här recensionen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS. Klicka på bilden ovan för fler bilder DS.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Att hitta rätt folk</title><id >aatthittarattfolk2011-03-03t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/att-hitta-rtt-folk"></link><updated >2011-03-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;IT-konsultbolagen letar mycket folk. Jakten på talanger bland konsultbolagen är central under perioder då efterfrågan på resurser är stor, som nu, särskilt som det är ganska ont om duktiga it-konsulter. Antalet som utexamineras är ganska litet i förhållande till efterfrågan, och någon existerande överkapacitet att ta av finns det inte heller. Således behöver konsultbolagen hitta på olika sätt att aktivt locka till sig nytt folk. Sådana problem har inte företag som Propellerhead,  Apple och Spotify. De kan nöja sig med att lägga upp en liten blänkare på sin hemsida och får ändå fler sökande än de kan hantera. Ett vanligt tillvägagångssätt är att erbjuda tipspengar. 10 000 om vi anställer någon du tipsat om. 15 000. 20 000! Man antar att personliga nätverk är ett fantastiskt sätt att hitta rätt folk på, och det stämmer säkert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Konsultbolag som implmenterar internsystem för Försäkringskassan kommer aldrig att bli så attraktiva arbetsgivare som exempelvis Twitter och Google, som gör coola tjänster och produkter som folk gillar att använda. Då gäller det att vara proaktiv och spela på de styrkor man faktiskt har. För varken otroligt duktiga medarbetare eller roliga arbetsuppgifter saknas. Det som saknas är ett sätt att kommunicera ut och skapa intresse för detta hos potentiella framtida rekryter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connecta är en av landets större konsultfirmor. De har reklam i alla skåp i omklädningsrummen på SATS träningscenter. Där tror man sig ha hittat rätt målgrupp. Så här kanske tankegångarna gick: Ambitiösa, duktiga människor håller sig i form. Gillar yoga, spinning och drömmer om att bli IT-konsulter. Accenture är världens största konsultbolag och de satsade fram till December 2009 stenhårt på att använda en viss golfspelare i sin reklam (&apos;Go on. Be a Tiger.&apos;). Sedan de kommit fram att hans fru hade anledning att bli lite putt (pun intended) ersattes han i all hast av ansiktslösa koreanska skridskoåkare. Alla företag håller sig framme på arbetsmarknadsdagar och mässor, anordnar aktiviteter och &amp;quot;träffar folk&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alla har sina strategier. Men på nätet är tystnaden öronbedövande. Visst, det finns kanske facebooksidor, kanske en &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.se.capgemini.com/karriarbloggen/&quot;&gt;blogg&lt;/a&gt; som med lite tur uppdateras en gång i månaden, men antagligen mer sällan än så. Sådant skrämmer nog bort fler talanger än det lockar. Vem vill jobba på ett företag som inte bryr sig?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Många konsulter är duktiga och driftiga – de bloggar, twittrar och genererar intresse inom områden där de kan mycket. Men företagen vågar inte utnyttja dessa kanaler. Antagligen är det en ängslighet över varumärket som gör att allt som står på samma skärm som en logotyp måste granskas i flera led. Visst skapar man kontroll, men man förlorar i kommunikation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mitt förslag är enkelt: Uppmuntra, underlätta och belöna digitalt nätverkande. Låt alla anställda som vill blogga, twittra och nätverka i företagets namn (med en liten badge på twitter-avataren t ex). Ha en tydlig men tillåtande policy och uppmuntra ett personligt tilltal. Gör som &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/wired&quot;&gt;Wired&lt;/a&gt; och låt de anställda turas om att ta hand om ett officiellt företagskonto en vecka i taget. Ha ett gäng bloggar där flera anställda hjälper till att skriva inom olika ämnen. Och ge tillbörlig ersättning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det handlar om att så mycket som möjligt exponera de talanger man har på företaget, att lita på att det man gör är intressant och på att man besitter stora mängder kompetens som växer om den får komma ut i luften.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Allt är ett system</title><id >aalltarettsystem2011-03-31t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/allt-r-ett-system"></link><updated >2011-03-31T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jag har en god vän som är föreståndare för en godisaffär. En fantastisk liten butik med väggarna fyllda med olika sorters choklad och karameller. Jag var och hälsade på henne i helgen och en tråkig sak hände. Hon glömde värmefläkten på när vi gick ifrån butiken och godis för £400 förstördes. Fruktansvärt klantigt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eller?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;När vi gick från butiken gick hade de andra två tjejerna som jobbade i butiken släckt, låst, räknat ihop kassan och allt annat som ska göras när man stänger butiken. Utom just att stänga av fläkten då. Det fanns ingenting som påminde min vän om att hon måste komma ihåg att stänga av fläkten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hon blev ett offer för ett dåligt system - ett svåranvänt system, ett system som uppmuntrar till misstag. En rutin för hur saker ska göras, i vilken ordning och av vem, en checklista som man kan pricka av när man gjort det. Enkla saker kan göra stor nytta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag ser det mesta utifrån ett systemperspektiv och ett anvärbarhetsperspektiv. Världen är ett system, vi är dess användare. Jag brukar hävda att trafiken har den mest avancerade och lyckade användbarheten som världen har skådat. Det är ett ofantligt stort och komplext system med många användare som egentligen har otroligt lite information om vad de andra användarna i systemet gör. Några enkla regler gör dock att systemet fungerar. Vi har lärt oss att köra på rätt sida, vi har lärt oss högerregeln och vi har lärt oss några (men långt ifrån alla) symboler som styr systemet. Men givet de enkla reglerna som vem som helst kan lära sig är trafiken väldigt lättanvänd och det är väldigt sällan något går fel. En sak som trafiken är bra på är att ständigt ge vägledning. Det finns alltid en linje på vardera sida om bilen som talar om vad man bör göra. Kommer man till ett ställe där man bör stanna eller sakta ner finns det antagligen både en skylt och färg på gatan som berättar detta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;För mig är det här bara en tankelek, men sätter man sig ner och klurar på detta under en längre tid kan man nog komma fram till något riktigt intressant.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Att leva utan iPhone</title><id >aattlevautaniphone2011-04-18t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/att-leva-utan-iphone"></link><updated >2011-04-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Efter en lite oturlig episod för några veckor sedan har jag levt mitt liv utan vad som i dagligt tal kallas &amp;quot;smartphone&amp;quot;. Här följer några korta tankar om hur detta har påverkat mig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag köpte min iPhone 3GS ganska snart efter att den hade kommit ut, i september 2009. Jag hade just fått jobb och min gamla Nokia hade börjat krångla. Man kan lugnt säga att detta förändrade mitt liv. Inte så fasligt mycket kanske, men ändå märkbart. Den var min kompanjon med vilken jag konsumerade tweets, bloggar, nyheter och musik, spelade spel, mätte löprundor, tog foton, mätte löprundor och checkade in såväl här som där - allt sådant som man inte kan göra med en &amp;quot;vanlig&amp;quot; telefon. Jag var en riktig iPhone-junkie helt enkelt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19 månader efter inköpet rycktes den bort från mig och jag hade att falla tillbaka på en &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gsmarena.com/sony_ericsson_k750-1090.php&quot;&gt;SonyEricsson K750i&lt;/a&gt;, en riktigt bra telefon när den introducerades sex år tidigare. Men våren 2011 går det inte att komma undan att den känns något daterad. Utvecklingen har ju gått snabbare på mobilmarknaden de senaste fem åren än &lt;a href=&quot;http://eldh.blogsome.com/2009/07/09/nokia-6220-classic-vs-nokia-6230/&quot;&gt;de fem föregående&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Så vad gör man då när man vant sig vid att kolla Mail, Twitter, Reeder och Facebook varje tunnelbaneresa, checka in på varje affär och alltsom oftast gå runt med hörlurar i öronen? Det som räddade min psykiska hälsa de första kritiska dagarna var nog att jag tack vare slumpens nycker precis hade köpt sex mycket läsvärda böcker som jag kunde borra ner näsan i på kollektivtrafiken. Att åka buss eller t-bana utan ha något att läsa ser jag fortfarande som helt otänkbart. Hörlurspluggen fick flytta till den lilla iPod Shuffle jag fick när jag började mitt nuvarande jobb. Den stora förändringen var dock att jag började läsa böcker, samt att jag hade lite mer att ta igen på twitter och i rss-läsaren när jag kom hem varje dag, sådant man vanligtvis fixade på vägen om man hade sin iPhone med sig. Jag rensade också ordentligt i rss-listan för att få ned antalet artiklar per dag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dock märkte jag snabbt att mycket av de naturliga mikropauser som man har under en dag — när man väntar på någon eller något, i hissen, på busshållplatsen etc. — som jag tidigare ägnat åt telefonen nu gick åt till att vänta, fundera och studera omgivningen. Onekligen blev jag lite mer medveten om min omgivning, på gott och ont. Ibland är det ju ganska skönt att sjunka in i sig själv. Dock var min flickvän glad att jag inte kunde checka in överallt. Och jag upptäckte till min förvåning att världen inte gick under när jag inte hade kollat min twitter på en dag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det är lite konstigt, tragiskt skulle man kunna tycka, när en förlorad liten pryl leder till en smärre livskris. Nu kanske det inte var riktigt så illa heller, men lite saker satte det hela ändå i perspektiv. En junkie som tar en vit månad kommer onekligen att komma ut på andra sidan med en del nya insikter i bagaget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nu är jag i alla fall med smartphone igen, en ny Samsung Galaxy Ace. Jag hade väntat mig att det skulle vara en ganska stor lättnad att byta bort den gamla Ericsson-luren, men tvärtom kände jag mig besviken första dygnet. Det beror nog till stor del på att det tar ett tag att komma igång med Android. Det är mycket som ska fixas innan man får det som man vill ha det. Dessutom är luren en budgetmodell som inte direkt är blixtsnabb. Men det berodde också på att det inte var särskilt spännande, allt det där som jag brukade hålla på med.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kanske kommer jag ha ett lite mer distansierat förhållande till min telefon framöver. Kanske blir det som förut igen. Något tror jag dock att jag har lärt mig. Oavsett vilket kommer världen att snurra vidare.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >&quot;Vanligt sunt förnuft&quot;</title><id >aquotvanligtsuntfornuftquot2011-05-15t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/vanligt-sunt-frnuft"></link><updated >2011-05-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jag ogillar många saker, men finns det något som får mig att resa ragg lite extra så är det när någon yppar orden &amp;quot;vanligt sunt förnuft&amp;quot;. Inget annat uttryck är samtidigt så fantastiskt innehållslöst, tvetydigt och missvisande.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sunt förnuft&amp;quot; används för att beskriva sådant som man tycker är så självklart att det inte behöver motiveras, förklaras eller diskuteras. Samtidigt används det i stort sett uteslutande för att döma eller nedvärdera någon som saknar detta vanliga sunda förnuft och följaktligen har gjort något som vem som helst hade kunnat lista ut var &amp;quot;rätt&amp;quot;. Om hen bara hade haft lite vanligt sunt förnuft alltså.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alla normala, vettiga människor har sunt förnuft. Om man inte håller med när någon har lagt &amp;quot;sunt-förnuft&amp;quot;-kortet saknar man uppenbarligen en grundläggande mänsklig funktion, man har i ett slag förvandlats från en resonerande individ till ett &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dn.se/ledare/kolumner/vad-ar-en-europe&quot;&gt;hjärndött monster&lt;/a&gt;. Och allt skulle väl kanske vara i sin ordning om det bara var odiskutabla självklarheter som motiverades med det sunda förnuftet. Sådant som bara de mest extrema flashback-foliehattarna kunde få för sig att ifrågasätta. Well, vad tror ni det sunda förnuftet sade om till exempel rättigheter för svarta för 150 år sedan? Hur länge sedan kunde man med sunt förnuft räkna ut att homosexualitet är en sjukdom? Att kvinnor inte skulle få rösta? Vad säger det sunda förnuftet hos människor i Pakistan, Iran, Kina, Italien, Grekland eller USA? Gissningsvis finns en inte obetydlig diskrepans mellan deras uppfattning av sunt och osunt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det sunda förnuftet är en ursäkt för att inte tänka. Det är en hänvisning till gällande normer, moral eller &amp;quot;magkänsla&amp;quot;. Det är ett sätt att säga att man är fullkomligt säker på sin sak men att man inte har en aning om varför man har rätt. Det sunda förnuftet är principlöst, fritt flytande och fördummande. Tänk efter innan du hänvisar till det.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Glädjedödarna</title><id >agladjedodarna2011-07-29t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/gldjeddarna"></link><updated >2011-07-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mattias Svensson tar i den ambitiösa debattboken Glädjedödarna sig an det så kallade förmynderiet. Boken är en kompromisslös uppgörelse med regleringar, förbud, skatter och allt annat som syftar till att styra våra fria val i någon godtycklig riktning. Den tar sin början i hans fars kamp för att driva diskotek, med danstillstånd och alkoholrestriktioner och berättar vidare om moralister i alla dess former – deras mål, medel och metoder. I det stora hela är boken mycket balanserad, välskriven och genomtänkt, och den smular förtjänstfullt sönder många av förmyndarnas argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men när det blir komplicerat gör Svensson det enkelt för sig. Och komplicerat blir det, framförallt när man diskuterar gränserna för det fria valet. På den filosofiskt intressanta frågan om man ska vara tillåten att sälja sig själv som slav landar Svensson i ett kategoriskt &amp;quot;nej&amp;quot;. Det är dock intressant att han inte tar med sig detta ställningstagande till exempelvis debatten om drogförbud. För när man har fastnat i ett missbruk av tunga droger kan man inte anses ha mycket kvar av sin fria vilja - man är fast i missbruket. Istället dividerar han om statistik på hur många som lyckas ta sig ur missbruk, vilket inte är överdrivet många. Hur man ska hantera de som har fastnat i sitt missbruk utan möjlighet att ta sig ur får vi inte några förslag på.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det finns all anledning att vara kritisk till drogpolitiken som den ser ut idag, inte minst det katastrofala kriget mot droger. Däremot kan man inte lämna debatten efter att detta konstaterande. En drogpolitik är och kommer vara nödvändig. I detta sammanhang skulle det vara mycket intressant att diskutera exempelvis tvångsvård, subutexprogram, LVM-hem och andra drogpolitiska åtgärder som faller utanför förbudsfållan. Men det blir säkert tid för den debatten någon annanstans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Den filosofiska frågan om huruvida man ska få sälja sitt fria val lämnar mig dock inte. Det minimala antalet som skulle kunna tänkas göra detta helt öppet är inte problemet. Problemet är att folk via sina val kommer att försätta sig i situationer där deras fria vilja är borta. Såld, sönderknarkad eller vad det vara månde. Kanske av försumbarhet, kanske av okunnighet, kanske av självdestruktivitet. Vad blir då svaret? Förbud eller inte? Mot vad i så fall? Vad det än blir, är det inte enkelt.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Slutet på Photoshop-eran</title><id >aslutetpaphotoshoperan2011-09-13t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/slutet-p-photoshop-eran"></link><updated >2011-09-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Läste &lt;a href=&quot;http://lukesbeard.com/posts/zerply-frontend/&quot;&gt;den här texten av Luke Beard&lt;/a&gt;, om hur han har jobbat när han designar &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zerply.com&quot;&gt;Zerply&lt;/a&gt; — en text som jag i högsta grad rekommenderar för alla med intresse för design eller webutveckling. Och det slog mig att en era i designhistorien är över. Photoshop är dött.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;För bara något år sedan designades hemsidor helt och hållet i Photoshop (eller kanske Illustrator) och sedan fick en kodapa i uppdrag att pixel för pixel överföra .psd-filen till html och css, trots att produkten aldrig varit särskilt väl anpassad för det (försök skapa en animerad .gif i PS på ett smidigt sätt om du kan). Skuggor, knappar, texter, bakgrunder; allt gjordes i Photoshop. Nu kan allt göras med CSS, och vill man göra designer som fungerar för flera plattformar, med olika pixeldensitet, blir pixelkavlande snabbt frustrerande.  En designer som vill göra ett bra jobb måste ha bra koll på CSS och exempelvis jQuery. Framtiden finns i webbläsaren. Den grafiken som finns kvar blir också i större utsträckning vektorbaserad allt eftersom .svg-filer blir mer och mer vanliga, vilket gör att även Illustrator vinner mark mot sin pixelälskande bror.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foton har också varit Photoshops domän i stor utsträckning. Det är nog inte bara en hemmapappa som har tankat ned Photoshop från piratbukten och sedan bara använt det till att beskära bilder. Program som Picasa, iPhoto och även mer seriösa fotohanteringsprogram som Aperture och Adobes eget Lightroom, samt förstås Instagram, Hipstamatic och resten av mobilboomen, har gjort att bara ett tappert fåtal sitter med semesterfotografierna i Photoshop fortfarande.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Självklart kommer Photoshop inte upphöra att existera. Däremot kommer det att återgå till att användas till de saker som det är riktigt bra på: avancerad fotoredigering och avancerad pixelgrafik. Där är det bäst och lär så förbli ett tag till (även om program som &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pixelmator.com&quot;&gt;Pixelmator&lt;/a&gt; och webbaserade alternativ som &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aviary.com/&quot;&gt;aviary&lt;/a&gt; kommer att finna sin plats på marknaden).&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Ajour</title><id >aajour2011-10-24t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/ajour"></link><updated >2011-10-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Alla är journalister&amp;quot;. Det är meningen som har fastnat i folks medvetande efter att &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ajour.se&quot;&gt;Ajour&lt;/a&gt; öppnade dörrarna förra veckan. En ny sorts journalistik, där alla får vara med och skapa, verkar vara idén. Bakom sajten står några sociala medier-veteraner, bland andra Emanuel Karlsten och Damon Rasti.
Jag uppskattar tanken. Där tar dock mitt uppskattande slut. Mer om det snart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Själv har jag kastat ut såväl tv:n som tidningarna och får nu större delen av mitt nyhetsflöde via twitter, facebook, väl valda bloggar och en del från gammelmedias mediasajter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.expressen.se/kultur/1.2595997/hall-i-ratten&quot;&gt;Jan Gradvall kallar&lt;/a&gt; Ajour-gänget för gratisåkare och beklagar den riktiga journalismens nära förestående död. Även &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.expressen.se/ledare/1.2596979/fredrik-krohnman-alla-ar-inte-journalister&quot;&gt;Fredrik Krohnman stämmer in i sågningskören&lt;/a&gt; och hyllar den äkta journalistiken, som står upp för sanning, saklighet och objektivitet, detta alltså veckan efter Aftonbladet hittade på ett regelverk som de sedan påstod att Håkan Juholt hade brutit mot… Jag lämnar öppet för en stunds tystnad medan resterna av glashuset klirrar klart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De bägge herrarna är hur som helst inte ensamma. Ajour verkar inte fått något direkt lysande mottagande. Och kritiken håller ungefär samma ton som herrarna Gradvall och Krohnman slagit an.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journalisternas roll är mångfacetterad, men en stor del består i att vara på rätt ställe, samt att ha kanaler och utrustning för att skicka rapporter från detta ställe. Nu har i princip alla med sig utrustning för att rapportera och till viss del finns även kanalerna - twitter, facebook etc. Däremot är det väldigt svårt för vanligt folk att sålla i den forsande floden av rapporter. Informationen finns, men man kan inte få tag på den. Den kommer för snabbt och den är gömd i en massa irrelevant skräp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag vill hävda att Ajours problem är ett helt annat än vad de flesta av deras kritiker vill göra gällande. Ajour har kanske insett att det finns intressant innehåll i de sociala medierna, men de har inte hittat något sätt att visa upp det innehållet. Istället försöker de skapa nyheter av interna twitter- och kommentarsfältsdiskussioner. Det är så navelskådande att man baxnar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vår tids största fråga är &amp;quot;vad händer?&amp;quot;, vårt intresse ligger i nuet, men vi har inte verktygen för att få svar på frågan. Gammelmedia kommer bara att kunna svara på frågan &amp;quot;vad hände?&amp;quot; och de sociala medierna kommer bara kunna svara om rätt person frågar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dåden i Norge i somras var ett tillfälle då twitter visade sin styrka. Mitt flöde fylldes med information som inte hittade ut i andra medier förrän lång tid senare. Allt från Moderaternas stämma till Lady Gagas frisyrbyten kommenteras på samma sätt på twitter och i bloggar. Snabbt dynamiskt, insiktsfullt, interaktivt och kvalitativt. Frågan är bara hur man gör denna upplevelse tillgänglig för den breda massan, som inte har tid, ork eller lust att följa 200 personer på twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ajour försöker inte svara på den frågan. Ajour är inte till för någon annan än sociala medier-entusiaster. Tyvärr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;För vi behöver fler spelare i medielandskapet. Vi behöver mediekanaler som bryter ny mark, som tänker nytt både journalistiskt och tekniskt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men ge mig en miljon och ett halvår, och jag ska ge er framtidens tidning.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Din senste krönika kan suga en kasse kukar</title><id >adinsenstekronikakansugaenkassekukar2012-01-03t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/din-senste-krnika-kan-suga-en-kasse-kukar"></link><updated >2012-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I mitt twitterflöde dök följande upp för någon dag sedan: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/#!/lisamagnusson/status/152370134835662848&quot;&gt;&apos;facebooks nya &amp;quot;tidslinje&amp;quot; kan f ö också gå och suga en kasse kukar&apos;&lt;/a&gt;. Att folk har starka åsikter om teknik är sannerligen inget ovanligt. Det som däremot är ovanligt är väl formulerad och underbyggd kritik mot tekniken. I 99 fall av 100 stannar det vid just sådana korta, ofta mycket grova, sågningar. Vanligtvis inget man skulle fästa någon särskild vikt vid. Men jag fastnade vid just den här tweeten, som skrevs av en person som jobbar med att formulera åsikter och som sannerligen inte skulle uttrycka sig så om någon text som hon starkt ogillade. Nä, inte ens de som uttryckligen kallar Lisa Magnusson för hora ber hon att suga en endaste liten kuk. Hade uttalandet gällt en text, ett konstverk eller ett musikaliskt verk hade det betraktats som ett mycket grovt, saklöst angrepp. Men nu handlade det om mjukvara och därför höjer ingen ett ögonbryn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det här är ett ganska vanligt problem, och jag skulle vilja hävda att det är en av grundorsakerna till att vi har ganska mycket dåliga system omkring oss. Folk bryr sig helt enkelt inte om att försöka förstå systemen alls, utan agerar som hjärndöda flashbacktroll och kastar ur sig första bästa invektiv. Om vi som faktiskt bygger och designar system stod upp för dem och krävde väl underbyggda argument för varför våra system ska suga påsar med manslemmar skulle vi dels bespara oss en massa skitsnack och dels skulle vi kunna få igång en konstruktiv diskussion om hur den teknik som vi använder dagligen faktiskt fungerar. Men nu förs diskussionen på samma nivå som mellan AFA och svenskarnas parti. Det är inte en särskilt bra miljö.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Så kära mediamänniskor och övriga twitterati, när ni kritiserar teknik, tänk er att ni kritiserar någons senaste krönika. Det sitter människor på andra sidan, inte helt olika er, och försöker göra så bra tekniska lösningar som vi bara kan, som vi hoppas att ni ska tycka om. Precis som ni vill vi höra konstruktiv, sansad kritik på det vi gör. Tänk igenom era argument och formulera er därefter.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Eldhs lag</title><id >aeldhslag2012-02-08t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/eldhs-lag"></link><updated >2012-02-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Då en Usenetdiskussion blir längre, går sannolikheten för att en jämförelse görs som involverar nazister eller Hitler mot ett&amp;quot; - Mike Godwin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Godwins lag är ett välkänt och ständigt aktuellt fenomen. Inte minst en dag som denna, då &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dn.se/kultur-noje/debatt-essa/hatet-som-gor-mig-politiskt-deprimerad&quot;&gt;Maria Sveland satte nytt svenskt Godwin-rekord i dagens DN&lt;/a&gt;, genom att först referera till nazister och sedan referera till Anders Bering Breivik (den &amp;quot;nya Hitler&amp;quot; i Godwin-sammanhang) inte mindre än sju gånger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men det jag  har tänkt på är inversen av Godwins lag, som &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dn.se/debatt/wallenbergs-anda-finns-inte-i-riksdagen&quot;&gt;Carl B Hamilton så vackert exemplifierade igår&lt;/a&gt;, nämligen de fall där debatten i stället för att handla om Hitler slutar i ett &amp;quot;Vad skulle Jesus göra?&amp;quot;. Logiken är den samma: I brist på argument tar man till en känd person med starkt symbolvärde för att få fram en poäng. Istället för Jesus kan man dra till med vilken helgonförklarad person som helst – Nelson Mandela, Moder Teresa, Martin Luther King, Olof Palme eller som Hamilton valde, Raul Wallenberg. Skillnaden är endast att man istället för att smutskasta en meningsmotståndare försöker grorifiera sig själv.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Detta är en styggelse, som måste bekämpas med alla tillgängliga medel. Precis som användande av Hitler- och Breivik-referenser bör diskvalificera gärningsmän från vidare samtal, bör även Jesus-referenserna rensas ut från våra debattsidor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Då en diskussion blir längre, går sannolikheten för att en jämförelse görs som involverar Jesus eller andra helgonfigurer mot ett&amp;quot; - Andreas Eldh&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Det är något skevt med nyheter på nätet.</title><id >adetarnagotskevtmednyheterpanatet2012-04-22t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/det-r-ngot-skevt-med-nyheter-p-ntet"></link><updated >2012-04-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;För några månader sedan startade gruppbloggen Ajour, efter att en hyfsat stor twitterhype hade byggts upp. Det är väl synd att säga att Ajour har levt upp till de stora orden som ackompanjerade lanseringen. Men det som faktiskt hände var att en liten diskussion om journalisters och nyhetsmediers förändrade roll bröt ut. Och jag började fundera på hur mediekonsumtion på internet har sett ut, och hur den kan komma att se ut framöver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I begynnelsen.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionella dagstidningar var tidiga med att starta webbplatser. Först var Aftonbladet, år 1996. Då såg deras hemsida ut &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/19961023235430/http://www.aftonbladet.se/&quot;&gt;så här&lt;/a&gt;. Den observante noterar att det faktiskt inte har hänt särskilt mycket i sajtens struktur eller funktionalitet. Den har växt på bredden i takt med att den normala datorskärmen har blivit större, och nu finns ett kommentarsfält och kanske lite blogglänkar istället för en gästbok. Även annonserna har växt, såväl till storlek som till antal. Har vi tur får vi nu för tiden med ett bildspel eller kanske en filmsnutt i anslutning till artikeln. Men i grunden presenteras nyheterna på samma sätt idag som för sexton år sedan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artikeln, omsluten av stora mängder annonser och puffar för annat material, det mesta helt orelaterat till artikeln jag läser. Det är konceptet som har varit oomstridd standard på webbtidningar de senaste sexton åren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sexton år är väldigt lång tid på internet. För sexton år sedan fanns inte Facebook, Youtube, Google, Twitter, iPhone, Napster, Skype, Blocket… Inget av det vi idag tar för givet på internet var tillgängligt, och många tjänster har kommit och gått. Utvecklingen har gått i en rasande fart. Men nyhetssajterna består. Oförändrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Betyder det att webbtidningarna gjorde allt rätt från början? Njae. Tillåt mig att tvivla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Varför ser det ut som det gör?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sin ställning som ledande medier på internet har de fått till skänks, av urminnes hävd. De har varit överlägsna på innehåll och har haft ensamrätt på presentationen av sitt innehåll De har aldrig behövt konkurrera med struktur. Så länge de uppdaterar detaljer på designen någon gång då och då bryr sig ingen om att det inte sker någon riktig utveckling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ett stort problem som aktivt försämrar webbtidningarna är de betalningsmodeller för annonser som dominerar. De flesta annonser säljs per visning. Det gör att tidningarna klämmer in så många annonser som möjligt på varje sida. Om de istället skulle ha större möjlighet att ta betalt per klick, eller något annat effektmål, skulle allt större incitament uppstå för att visa rätt annonser för rätt personer vid rätt tidpunkt, snarare än att visa så många annonser som möjligt, jämt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Vart är vi på väg?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vill man läsa engelskspråkiga artiklar finns det ganska gott om alternativ. Flipboard, Zite och Google Currents är exempel på tjänster som ger riktigt bra digitala läsupplevelser. Där samsas material från många olika källor, nyhetstidningar, bloggar sociala nätverk – alla får vara med på samma villkor. Sådana tjänster kommer naturligtvis även att anpassas för den svenska marknaden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag är övertygad om att de svenska nyhetsmediernas stålbad inte har börjat än. Än så länge läser de flesta sin papperstidning, men så kommer det inte att se ut om några år. Gigantiska förändringar är på gång och de som nu är herre på täppan kommer att få stora problem att behålla sin ställning. Att klara övergången från papperstidning till digital distribution är ingen liten utmaning. När vi slutar läsa nyheter på papper kommer vi dessutom att ställa radikalt annorlunda krav på läsupplevelsen. Det ska bli spännande att se vilka som klarar av att leva upp till de kraven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Har ni åsikter vill jag gärna höra dem. Förslagsvis på Twitter (@eldh).&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >En gammal mobildesign</title><id >aengammalmobildesign2012-08-13t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/en-gammal-mobildesign"></link><updated >2012-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;När jag gick på gymnasiet fick vi i uppgift att designa en mobiltelefon. De flesta designade mer eller mindre fantasifulla rymdskepp. Detta var år 2002, jag hade precis köpt en &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gsmarena.com/nokia_8210-19.php&quot;&gt;Nokia 8210&lt;/a&gt;, som då var bland det coolaste som fanns. Personligen drömde jag ännu mer om den kromblanka &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gsmarena.com/nokia_8810-20.php&quot;&gt;Nokia 8810&lt;/a&gt; och &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gsmarena.com/sony_cmd_j5-201.php&quot;&gt;Sonys CMD J5&lt;/a&gt; (det här var alltså innan SonyEricsson-tiden).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men jag var redan då en riktig sucker för minimalism och ville designa något väldigt enkelt. Min design blev nästan helt fyrkantig, i matt metall (se bilden ovan). Magistern sågade den totalt, och sa att en mobil måste ha former. Han tyckte också att det var att &amp;quot;smita undan&amp;quot; att göra något med en så enkel design. Jag försökte käfta emot men jag insåg snart att det bara skulle leda till ett IG, så jag ändrade mitt förslag, ritade till en liten bulle runt skärmen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kommer ihåg att jag hoppades att något företag skulle släppa en sådan telefon som den jag hade gjort ursprungligen, något väldigt enkelt och avskalat, för att jag trodde den skule vara väldigt trevlig att använda och för att det skulle ge mig rätt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Av någon anledning börjar jag tänka på den här lilla episoden varje gång jag läser om Apple vs. Samsung. Inte för att min design på något sätt liknar det som Apple skulle komma att släppa fyra år senare, utan för att det enklaste jag kunde tänka mig, det som var alldeles för simplistiskt för min lärare, var så otroligt mycket mer komplicerat än vad det behövde vara. Och för att vi alla var så fast i föreställningen av vad en mobiltelefon var.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >64 män, 17 kvinnor och ett kilo mjöl. </title><id >a64man17kvinnorochettkilomjol2012-10-20t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/64-mn-17-kvinnor-och-ett-kilo-mjl"></link><updated >2012-10-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Isobel Hadley-Kamptz twittrade igår om känsfördelningen på de som talar på internetdagarna. Jämfört med fördelningen bland alla som jobbar inom it-branschen så är andelen kvinnor på Internetdagarnas scen ungefär som man kan förvänta sig, alltså en ganska stor övervikt män.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hadley-Kamptz är vanligtvis rätt klipsk och smart, men begränsar ändå sin rapportering vid att räkna könsorgan. Nå, den analysmetoden i sig är ju inte ovanlig och man kanske inte ska begära mer i 140-teckensvärlden. Men det är så det funkar: Ska man undersöka jämställdhet så räknar man könsfördelning. Så är det bara. För oss som har jobbat inom it ett tag och faktiskt intresserar oss för frågan om varför så få kvinnor söker sig till branschen blir dock en sådan analys bara tröttsamt ytlig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Min första tanke var att det kanske finns något implicit meddelande i den statistiken. En osynlig handlingsplan som är uppenbar för den som räknar. Doktor Jämställdhet preskriberar: &amp;quot;Jaha, 20% kvinnor säger du, då föreskriver vi 20ml tjejer kan-kurser, 4 tabletter lönelyft och 1 rejäl dos positiv särbehandling så ska det där vara löst inom 2 till 3 år.&amp;quot; Är det en kritik av Internetdagarna för att de inte släpper fram tillräckligt med kvinnor? Jag känner att jag borde veta vad som menas men inte sägs. Lika outtalat men, får jag för mig, självklart är orsakerna till det rådande läget. Sexism, grabbig stämning och klanmentalitet. Eller något.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men diskussionen inom branschen har kommit längre och är tack och lov oftast mer explicit. Inte sällan läggs förslag om positiv särbehandling (senast diskuterades det om man skulle vika ett antal platser åt kvinnor innan sthlm.js senaste möte). Och varje gång kommer någon tjej in i diskussionen är säger att hon skulle bli ytterst förolämpad av att få annorlunda behandling på grund av sitt kön. Ofta ansluter folk till bägge lägren, men någon konsensus har jag inte sett tecken på.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oavsett diskussioner, särbehandling används mycket flitigt, såväl vid rekrytering som i andra sammanhang - i få branscher lär det finnas så många &amp;quot;tjejklubbar&amp;quot; som i it-branschen. Jag vågar påstå att en tjej som programmerar kommer alltid gå före en kille med samma, och ofta till och med högre, kompetens i rekryteringssituationer. Många företag har uttalade mål om att öka andelen kvinnor, vilket förstås gör att det blir lite av en huggsexa om de kvinnor som finns i branschen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men det kanske behövs, för att kompensera för all grabbighet som skrämmer bort tjejer. Jag vet inte. Men jag har svårt att tro att tjejer väljer bort programmering på grund av att risken att behöva åka gokart med sina kollegor istället för att ha sing-a-long med Martin Stenmark, eller vad man nu gör på företagsfester i andra brancher. Kanske är det flipperspelet på kontoret som skrämmer bort kvinnorna?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sexism finns inom IT. Absolut. Men värre än i någon annan bransch? Tveksamt. &lt;a href=&quot;http://laurasanders.net/a-primer-on-sexism-in-the-tech-industry-by-an-actual-girl/&quot;&gt;Vissa upplever inget sådant&lt;/a&gt;, andra stöter på såväl gubbfasoner som förutfattade meningar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jag tror knappt att det finns någon i it-branschen som inte vill se att fler tjejer söker sig hit, och jag tror också att företag såväl som individer är mer välkomnande mot kvinnor än i andra branscher. Företagen skriker efter arbetskraft och väldigt få går arbetslösa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Överlag tycker jag att de saker som görs för att locka kvinnor till it-branschen är bra och jag tror att vi är på rätt väg. Det gäller dock att vara försiktig så att man inte stirrar sig blind på vad folk har mellan benen. Om andra saker än folks kompetens får styra har vi tappat det bästa med it-branschen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Det här är ett jättespretigt inlägg. Någon annan gång kanske jag kommer skriva mer strukturerat i ämnet. Det jag egentligen ville ha sagt var att det är hög tid att överge ytliga analyser. Vi kan bättre.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Nexus 4 &amp; switching from iPhone to Android</title><id >anexus4ampswitchingfromiphonetoandroid2013-01-03t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/nexus-4"></link><updated >2013-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;ç«ç»¬„Üˆ”„^•¡@©¶ I&apos;ve been a happy iPhone owner since I got an iPhone 3GS back in 2009. I did switch to Android and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samsung.com/galaxyace/ace_overview.html&quot;&gt;Samsung Galaxy Ace&lt;/a&gt; (running Android 2.3) for a short while, but switched back when the iPhone 4S came out. So, I&apos;m familiar with what Android was a year and a half ago, but I&apos;m heavily invested in the Apple/iOS ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three things has kept me from considering switching to Android so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I hate what handset makers do to the OS, with custom skins, crappy apps that can&apos;t be uninstalled and delayed OS updated. I still would not consider getting any other Android phone than a Nexus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hardware has been far from Apple&apos;s standards. Phones have been too big, too ugly, and felt too cheap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A smooth interface without lag is extremely important on touch devices. Much more so than on normal computers. Android has always had major issues with laggy animations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, I&apos;m been curious of the state of Android and since I&apos;ve had major issues with battery life on my iPhone, when the upportunity came along to try the brand new Nexus 4 with Android 4.2 I was more than happy to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nexus 4 is really good looking. And more importantly, it feels good. It&apos;s nice to hold, with a rubber edge running along the side of the device and a glass back to feels solid. There are no removable parts except for the micro-sim tray, which has a similar construction to that of an iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The front is basically just a big (1280x768, 4.7&amp;quot;) display. A gorgeous display, definitely on par with the iPhone. The speaker is barely visible at the top of the device and there are no hardware buttons. And this has actually been a problem for me. Many times when I pick the device out of my pocket it takes me a while to realize I&apos;m holding it upside down. I suppose I&apos;ll learn eventually to feel the side for the power button, but it has been a bit of an annoyance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot has already been written about the hologram-ish finish on the back. It&apos;s good looking, it feel nice to hold and will probably break if you drop the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&apos;s one physical button on each side of the phone. The one on the left controls volume and the right one is a power switch. On the bottom there&apos;s a micro USB slot, which is quite horrible to use. I really see why Apple went with the reversible Lightning connector instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nexus 4 doesn&apos;t feel as big as I would have expected, probably because it&apos;s a bit slimmer than the iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, a 4.7&amp;quot; screen is too big for me, as I have normal size hands. Reaching the top corners without changing the grip is impossible. I can&apos;t understand why there are no high-end Android phones with smaller screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/nexus/nexus5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nexus 4&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android has come a long way since 2.3, which is the last version I had used. Everything in the OS runs smooth, even though the touch response isn&apos;t as good as on iOS. It&apos;s pretty easy to get stuff on the home screens arranged the way I want it, though I did replace the default launcher with &lt;a href=&quot;http://novalauncher.com&quot;&gt;Nova Launcher&lt;/a&gt;, which provides some more customization options. I also promptly installed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.swiftkey.net/en/&quot;&gt;SwiftKey&lt;/a&gt;, which was the one thing I&apos;ve probably missed the most from Android when I was on iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notification drawer is much better than the one on iOS. I really like the &amp;quot;swipe to dismiss/remove&amp;quot; gesture that is becoming a standard at least on Android. Widgets are also nice, even though I don&apos;t use more than a few, and easy access to common settings is very convenient. But I think I like the most about Android is the possiblity to choose your own default apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I do miss though is the rubber band effect when scrolling at the end of lists, but I suppose the ommision of that is due to Apple&apos;s patents in the area (even though their validity are disputed). Another thing that really bothers me are that the button bar (with home, back and multitasking buttons) move to the other side of the phone when you rotate the screen. There are some other small annoyances, but overall Android feels as good as iOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/nexus/nexus11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nexus 4&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The App problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a phone is nothing without apps. The default apps are nice, and I haven&apos;t replaced that many. Some of them, like Gmail &amp;amp; Chrome, are better than their iOS counterparts. Play Store is quite nice, and it&apos;s awesome to be able to install stuff onto the phone straight from the computer. Also, the new guidelines that came with Android 4.0 are pretty nice, and apps that use them are often a pleasure to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, most apps are laggy and downright ugly. This starts already at the home screen, where a lot of apps (even &amp;quot;big&amp;quot; ones like Path, Flickr and Runkeeper) don&apos;t have icons in the right resolution which leaves them blurry. And even if they have the right resolution many of them are smaller than they should be, and a lot of them are pretty ugly. In general, app icons would benefit from some solid guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And although most of the apps I use frequently on my iPhone have counterparts that are as good (or even better), there are a couple of apps I&apos;ve really come to miss. The most important is Tweetbot. And although there are a bunch of &amp;quot;ok&amp;quot; Android Twitter clients, none of them are even close to being as solid as Tweetbot. Reeder is another app that has no solid replacement. &lt;a href=&quot;http://twentyfivesquares.com/press/&quot;&gt;Press&lt;/a&gt; is beautiful, but lacks some crucial features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so it goes. Some &amp;quot;smaller&amp;quot; apps that I really like, Timehop, Want/Svpply, Skala are iOS only, and some, like Ruzzle, are pretty much unusable on Android.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/nexus/nexus7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nexus 4 &amp;amp; iPhone 4S&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android has caught up with iOS. Maybe it&apos;s already passed it. The problem is neither the apps nor the hardware that comes with it has. The hardware is close, the people that like huge diplays might even prefer the Nexus 4 hardware over an iPhone. But the app ecosystem still has a pretty long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will probably go back to using my iPhone in a couple of weeks, and my next phone will probably be an iPhone, but I&apos;ve come to like the Nexus 4 for its gorgeous display, solid build quality and some of the nice things in Android.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two things are still keeping me from becoming a full-time Android user:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of great apps. The only app I &amp;quot;love&amp;quot; on Android is Chrome. A lot of apps are good, but too many are crap or not availible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want a high-end phone with a smaller display. The 4.7&amp;quot; size which has become standard on Android is simply too big for most people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Apple needs to be on their toes. As mobile OS:es are expected to manage more and more of the things we now do on our computers, the flexibility of Android will be an advantage, and Windows is lurking around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mobile war is still very much ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Who is a designer?</title><id >awhoisadesigner2013-03-26t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/who-is-a-designer"></link><updated >2013-03-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;It&apos;s not just what it looks like and feels like. Design is how it works.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;— Steve Jobs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s a bit of a cliché to start a blog post with a Steve Jobs quote, but this quote really is a good starting point for what I want to say with this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design is how it works. That should mean anyone who takes decisions on how it should work is a designer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spend most of my time writing HTML, CSS and Javascript, so I am what most people refer to as a &amp;quot;web developer&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;front-end developer&amp;quot;. I really don&apos;t like those titles. They imply that what I do is seperate from the work of designers. Well, it&apos;s not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a designer. I decide how things work, I decide how they feel and how they are percieved. Even when I don&apos;t do graphical design or interaction design (sometimes I do that too), many of the decisions I make influence how the user will experience the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;The design/development divide is artifical.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/aral/status/315032456644419584&quot;&gt;Aral Balkan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the manufacturing world, the designers would make sketches, then prototypes, then more prototypes. Then production would start. Not many decisions that influenced the outcome was left to be made after the designer had delivered a final prototype. In print design, the designer makes a design and leaves it to the printer. Not many desicions left there either. If there were details in the production stage that would impact the end product, the designer would have to become familiar with these and make the appropriate decisions beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In digital design, things now work a bit differently. First, what we do is highly interactive, responsive and fluid. &amp;quot;How it works&amp;quot; is just so much more than &amp;quot;how it looks&amp;quot;. Second, we now produce one thing instead a million items based on the same design. We don&apos;t have to decide everything before production starts. So we&apos;re working &amp;quot;agile&amp;quot;, meaning we do things in iterations where we improve our product one small part at the time. It&apos;s a continuous effort where building and designing are intertwined and unseperable. There is no digital equivalent of manufacturing or printing. It&apos;s all just building things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another part of this artificial divide between design and development is that many of today&apos;s designers have very little knowledge of the building blocks of what s/he is designing. Any designer sholuld know the tools of his trade. A web designer who doesn&apos;t know how CSS and Javascript works is like a furniture designer who doesn&apos;t know the properties of different materials or a clothing designer who doesn&apos;t know about fabrics. They will all have a hard time making good design decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The divide exists because we have not adapted the designer role to the digital medium. We need to accept the fact that digital design it a much wider dicipline than it has been in the past. Again, a designer is anyone who makes decisions on how the product should work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This distinction is important, because only when we have decided who can make design desicions can we forcefully pevent the wrong people from doing so. The client&apos;s wife is not a designer. Neither is the project manager, the requirements analyst, the DBA or the test engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are the designers.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Check republic</title><id >acheckrepublic2013-05-06t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/check-republic"></link><updated >2013-05-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I heard about this really cool app framework that was supposed to change the way we make web apps. It is called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meteor.com&quot;&gt;Meteor&lt;/a&gt;, and when I started reading up on it I felt I needed to try it. So I decided to make this little app I&apos;ve had in my head for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I almost never use todo apps for organizing my work. I use them for shopping lists, packing lists, reminders and to store ideas for blog posts. And one thing that annoys me about todo apps is that they assume that I want to do each thing just once. For a lot of use cases, that&apos;s not true. Often you want to do a list of things many time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a href=&quot;http://checkrepublic.meteor.com&quot;&gt;Check Republic&lt;/a&gt;. It&apos;s a simple app for making check lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s really minimalistic, and it&apos;s not feature complete yet, but I like it. I&apos;d love for you to try it and tell me what you think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway. The reason I did this thing was mainly to see if Meteor is anywhere near as awesome as I hoped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meteor is in its early stages, and there are bugs. But it feels like the future. Having the same language for front-end and server is one thing (node will give you that), but with Meteor you have the same API throughout your app, both front-end and server. Meteor handles all the client-server communtication for you, it handles routing, resource bundling and a hell of a lot more. Templating is painless, so is deployment. It feels pretty much like magic. If you&apos;re into web development at all, you should at least look at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://meteor.com/screencast&quot;&gt;screencast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Why you can&apos;t be agile</title><id >awhyyoucan39tbeagile2013-05-11t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/why-you-cant-be-agile"></link><updated >2013-05-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I work as a consultant. It&apos;s been a really good way for me to try different kinds of roles and get to know different organizations. I&apos;ve learned a great deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&apos;ve never really been happy with the way we work in the projects I&apos;ve been in. Even though we have tried to work in an agile way within the team, the organization as a whole hasn&apos;t shared our philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago I joined a new project, and it is quite different from what I&apos;ve experienced before. Pretty much the entire development organization is a textbook example of how to work agile. My team work in a kanban-style way, with little focus on sprints and with continuous integration and deployment. When we have implemented a feature, we release it. When we run out of tasks we estimate new tasks from the backlog and put them up on our board. The team has all the functions needed to take a story from nothing to release – back end devs, front end devs, designers and testers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s pretty great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m not going to go into detail about why working this way is so great, more than to say that we are really productive and we produce high-quality software. That&apos;s for another post. What I want to talk about is what it takes to work this way, and why so many organizations fail in doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Agile starts with sales.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sales people like to promise things. I know, I have been there, and I have made promises to customers without knowing if our developers could commit to them. If you work with B2B at all, you have probably experienced this. Sales guys committing to delivering a fixed set of features on a fixed date. And thus preventing the organization from being agile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same thing often happen with internal projects, because of the way most companies are organized – separate units with separate budgets. This effectively makes internal projects equivalent to any other B2B project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, why is &apos;fixed scope, fixed time&apos; so hard to combine with agile?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, being agile is being adaptive to change. And when things change in a project with fixed scope and timeframe, the only variable you have left is quality. And there are few things creative people like designers and developers hate more than being forced to produce crappy things. Things will change in the project. Requirements will be misunderstood or conflicting. The scope you agree to is never what the customer wants in the end. The more you try to specify things, the more problems you will face when implementing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, by setting fixed scope and time you take ownership of the development process. You have committed to things that are not in your hands, but in the hands of the development teams. And a development team without a sense of ownership will have no motivation to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to think of it this way: Bugs exists not just in code, but also in requirement documents, in wireframes, in graphic design specifications and every other artifact you produce. Agile is about producing less of these bug-ridden artifacts and minimize impact of errors that occur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way to making your organization more agile starts with letting go of the detailed specifications. Agree to high level goals, and agree to a process where the development teams have control, where changes can be made easily and where a working system is most valued. Don&apos;t fool yourself into thinking that you are agile just because your teams have scrum boards. You&apos;re agile when you can easily adapt to change and when you allow your organization to constantly improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People love to make great things, and they will if they are given the means.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Buying things</title><id >abuyingthings2013-06-01t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/buying-things"></link><updated >2013-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We live in a society built around buying things. This is a good thing, since it allows us to specialize, to do something that we like and that we are good at. But it also means that we have to decide what to buy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am price aware. I dislike spending too much money on things. I buy a lot of used things, and I get most of my clothes from the outlet section on &lt;a href=&quot;http://asos.com&quot;&gt;ASOS&lt;/a&gt;. However, I&apos;ve recently come to realize something:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I have never regretted buying something that was really expensive.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I don&apos;t mean that last beer on the overpriced club. I mean those things where you actually take time to consider the options and in the end decide on the pricier, better, alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You won&apos;t miss money you have spent on something good. You will, however, miss money you spent on something that&apos;s not good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a philosophy to this. Dustin Curtis &lt;a href=&quot;http://dcurt.is/the-best&quot;&gt;wrote about&lt;/a&gt; how he, after selling all his belongings, decided to only buy the very best things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem, of course, is that it takes a lot of time and effort to find the best things. Cutting though endless layers of marketing speak and misguiding information to find that golden nugget is not something everyone can do all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think it&apos;s a good thing to try to buy things of great quality, things made with love, things that will last. If they feel expensive, it&apos;s hopefully because they are that much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If whatever you are buying is important to you, then buying the best will be worth it. If it&apos;s not that important, don&apos;t buy it at all.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Theming with SASS</title><id >athemingwithsass2013-06-20t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/theming-with-sass"></link><updated >2013-06-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At my current project I&apos;m helping &lt;a href=&quot;http://kambi.com&quot;&gt;Kambi&lt;/a&gt; build their responsive sports betting client (an in-depth look at the project can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.14islands.com/post/52546836134/betting-on-responsive&quot;&gt;in this post&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a whole bunch of different themes for different customers of the app. As functionality (and associated styles) were added to the app and the number of customers grew, we wanted to find an efficient way of structuring our themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me just say, before I get more into the specifics of our app, that we pretty much follow the tips about SASS theming outlined in &lt;a href=&quot;http://mikefowler.me/thoughts/efficient-theming-with-sass/&quot;&gt;this post by Mike Folwer&lt;/a&gt;. My main focus will be on the problems facing a large app, with many themes and a lot of styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The old stuff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The codebase had recently been converted to &lt;em&gt;Sass&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;LESS&lt;/em&gt;. The code structure was based on a &amp;quot;css mindset&amp;quot;. We hardly used variables, mixins, extends or functions, and all of the theming was done with normal css overrides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the file structure we had (some things are ommited for clarity):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;common
- module1.scss
- module2.scss
- …etc
theme
- overwrite.scss
- paint.scss
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the base styling was divided by module in the &lt;em&gt;common&lt;/em&gt; folder and each theme had overrides for all color declarations – background color, text color, shadows etc. – in &lt;em&gt;paint.scss&lt;/em&gt; and any non-color overrides was put in &lt;em&gt;overwrite.scss&lt;/em&gt;. The downside of this was that we had to overwrite most of the color declarations in the app for each new theme. It was also very hard to maintain. When we added a new feature or changed the structure of the html, every theme had to be seperately updated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall structure of the css was also really bad, with selectors that was way too specific and complicated and a lot of redundant code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had to get away from this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New thinking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all we had to set up some ground rules. In order to keep the theming process from becoming to complicated we needed to limit &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; theming could be done. This is a tricky decision. If you limit theming too much all themes will look pretty much the same, which will not sit well with our customers. If you allow the theming to be too loose you will end up with a hard-to-maintain mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SASS has some awesome features to use for theming, like variables, mixins and color functions. We decided to go full-on with variables. All the colors used in the css should be set using variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new structure is pretty close to what we had before, but with a few notable changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;common
- variables.scss
- module1.scss
- module2.scss
- …etc
theme
- variables.scss
- overwrite.scss
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;commons/variables.scss&lt;/em&gt; uses the !default keyword for every variable, whichmeans we can overwrite variables anywhere without causing problems with inherited values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if this is in our common &lt;em&gt;variables.scss&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$some-color: #fff !default;
$some-other-color: $some-color !default;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we can put the following in our theme &lt;em&gt;variables.scss&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$some-color: #aaa;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which will give the value &lt;strong&gt;#aaa&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;$some-other-color&lt;/strong&gt;, just like we want to. But we can also set &lt;strong&gt;$some-other-color&lt;/strong&gt; to something else in the theme variables file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This allows us to set a few brand specific colors that cascade through our theming files and have all colors used in the app to be calculated via Sass functions. Pretty neat, and this is probably more or less how we will make themes in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existing themes were not easily translated into the new format and we have spent &lt;em&gt;A LOT&lt;/em&gt; of time setting variable values. There are some 700 variables in the main variables file, and each theme overrides between ten and thirty variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this setup, we have a much more scalable architecture, refactoring is a lot easier, and it&apos;s easier to make the themes consistant. If we want to make changes to the html or selectors we just have to update stuff in one place. When we add something new we make sure to inherit variable values so that no theme-specific updates will have to be made. And all this without actually sacrificing any theming flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will help us a lot when we add functionality to the app and making new themes will be as easy as setting a handfull of variable values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The app is live on a bunch of places, for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://mobile.888sport.com/en/offering.htm&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://touch.unibet.com/client-start/sportsbook&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any questions or suggestions are more than welcome. Just contact me on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/eldh&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >The future of photography</title><id >athefutureofphotography2013-08-11t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/photography"></link><updated >2013-08-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I label myself an &amp;quot;enthusiast&amp;quot; photographer. I know basic things about optics and how a camera works, I understand the concepts of aperture, ISO and shutter speed and I spend some time and some on my interest. I enjoy the art of photography, and I admire those who master it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago I got my hands on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://camerapedia.wikia.com/wiki/Contax_RTS&quot;&gt;Contax RTS&lt;/a&gt; that my grandfather used, and I&apos;ve been using it this summer. It&apos;s a magnificant camera, with a couple of very nice lenses to go with it (Zeiss 50/1.7, Zeiss 28/2.8 and Yashica 135/2.8 are the ones I&apos;ve used most). Compared to the old Canon 450d the photos I took with the Contax, on real film, just had so much more soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m also a smartphone and internet junkie. I use VSCO Cam, Instagram, Facebook, Twitter, Path and I will probably use whatever the hot new thing is six months from now. Naturally I want to post photos now and again. Preferrably beautiful photos that give life to the moments I want to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And shooting with film is kinda slow. The time from shutter to screen is at least one week. As much as I love shooting on film, I realized I needed a proper digital camera. So I bought the Sony NEX-7 and a couple of lenses – 50mm, 16mm, fisheye adapter and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mirrorlessworld.com/?p=6265&quot;&gt;Lens Turbo&lt;/a&gt; to fit my old Contax Lenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the NEX-7 is a great camera. It&apos;s light and small, controls are pretty great, build quality is good and it looks nice. It takes great photos, and even though they don&apos;t quite have the character you get from film, they still have plenty of life in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&apos;m not completely satisfied. Digital photography should be so much simpler than this. I don&apos;t want to pop out my SD card to transfer pictures to my computer, I don&apos;t want to be stuck in Aperture just to share photos, and I don&apos;t want to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smartphone cameras will never completely replace real cameras. Most people won&apos;t need a dedicated camera, but some people like to take really good photos, and for that they will always need cameras. But the photos need to be set free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&apos;s how I would like my photo workflow to be: Take photo -&amp;gt; unlock iPhone -&amp;gt; open photo app -&amp;gt; select photo -&amp;gt; make adjustments/apply filters -&amp;gt; post. If I don&apos;t want to post it directly it should end up in my photo stream so I can process it later, on any device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today&apos;s cameras still come from a pre-2007 world where people &lt;em&gt;don&apos;t&lt;/em&gt; carry around a high-end computing device. The Galaxy cameras from Samsung are an interesting idea, but I think you don&apos;t need to slap a phone on the back of every camera, because every camera user has a phone in thier pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/sony-alpha-nex-6&quot;&gt;NEX-6&lt;/a&gt;, Sony has at least added wi-fi and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eye.fi/products/mobi&quot;&gt;Eye-fi Mobi&lt;/a&gt; is an interesting concept, but both these seem a bit too clunky for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These baby-steps are in the right direction. But I want to see better integration with photo services, and I think the winner in the digital camera race is whoever decides to become king of the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Smashing Conference</title><id >asmashingconference2013-09-17t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/smashing-conference"></link><updated >2013-09-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was at this year&apos;s Smashing Conference in Freiburg, Germany. I had an amazing couple of days listening and talking to some of the worlds best web people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some of the things that stuck with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Performance as design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big topic was performance. Websites are growing, and the average site is now around 1.5 MB. We are also seeing increasing use of JavaScript on scroll and touch events, which comes at a performance cost and can result in a bad experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performance really matters. It&apos;s one of the key factors that determine how people use and experience the thing you are building, which of course also has a big business impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Death to comps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The design process was a big talking point. The rise of responsive design has led to new ways of leading the design process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One technique more commonly used is &amp;quot;designing in the browser&amp;quot; (or &amp;quot;deciding in the browser&amp;quot;), meaning more of the design process takes place in the browser rather than in Photoshop or in sketch books. This is because of the increasing complexity of web layouts, with fluid, responsive layouts, animations and more interactivity makes it hard to test in a meaningful and efficient way using traditional tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another talking point was &amp;quot;atomic design&amp;quot;, and the trend towards designing smaller elements and modules rather then designing full pages. For agencies this might be a significant change, since it means the deliverables will change from being some sort of full page comp (either hi-fidelity made in Photoshop or a low-fidelity wireframe) to being something like style tiles, design guide or a fully coded site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Process/people design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building on these changes to the design process, a lot or focus was put on the communication during the process, where it is becoming more common to deliberately create assets that steer the conversations with clients and stakeholders in the most productive direction. It&apos;s simply put about having the right conversations at the right moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make this happen it is important to have the right kinds of design assets as a base for discussion – and often the right choice is to use something more lo-fi than you would usually do. Sometimes it might be a good idea to base the discussion on something other than the thing you are working on, to be able to focus more on feel and inspirations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Microsoft launched their new responsive &lt;a href=&quot;http://microsoft.com&quot;&gt;microsoft.com&lt;/a&gt; many people were surprised that a company like that could pull that kind of project. Obviously it had required impressive communication skills from the design team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Details of responsive design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last years&apos; conference focused a lot on responsive design. This year the focus partly shifted towards other topics, and partly moved to the finer details of designing responsive sites, such as responsive images, modular design and responsive typography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The things that were not there&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some things were, surprisingly or not, absent from the discussions at Smashing Conf. First of all, there was – thankfully – almost no talk about the battle between flat and skeumorphic design that has been raging in the design community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was also surprisingly little talk about animations and movement in design. I am thinking this is still a small topic, but one that will continue to gain momentum as the web becomes a more advanced application environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More about the conference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke Wroblewski took notes during most of the talks. &lt;a href=&quot;https://kippt.com/eldh/smashing-conference-lukes-notes&quot;&gt;Check them out here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elisabeth Irgens also did some amazing sketch notes, which you can find &lt;a href=&quot;https://kippt.com/eldh/smashing-conference-sketchnotes&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least: Many thanks to my travel companions David, Hjörtur and Anders for making this trip so much better than I could have hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Immediate feedback</title><id >aimmediatefeedback2013-10-14t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/immediate-feedback"></link><updated >2013-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I re-watched &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/36579366&quot;&gt;Bret Victor&apos;s talk &amp;quot;Invention on principle&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; last night. And it got me thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not yet familiar with &lt;a href=&quot;http://worrydream.com&quot;&gt;Bret Victor&lt;/a&gt; I envy you, because you have a couple of really mind-blowing moments ahead of you as you look through his work. He is one of the greatest minds of our time. (By the way, dont&apos; miss &lt;a href=&quot;http://worrydream.com/cv/bret_victor_resume.pdf&quot;&gt;his CV&lt;/a&gt;. It&apos;s unreal.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principle he lives by is that &lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;creators need imediate connection to what they create&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;, and based on this principle he has come up with a number of tools that create that kind of connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hated Java development because the connection between the tool (the code) and what I created (the system) was too slow This makes creating things hard, unless you already know what you are doing, which would mean all of the creativity was gone from the creation process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web front-end development is nicer in that way. There&apos;s still not an immediate connection between the coding and the output but at least there are no 20 minute compiles to sit through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the lack of tools that give us that sought after immediate connection to what we make have helped create the divide between designers and developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we think of design as &amp;quot;deciding how thinks should work&amp;quot; and development as &amp;quot;making things work as they should&amp;quot; then having design and development as two seperate roles makes it impossible to have an immediate connection between the creator and the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the creative parts in the process of making stuff, deciding as you make is the only real way produce good results. Having that immediate connection makes you try things you wouldn&apos;t have tried and think thoughts you wouldn&apos;t have thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a utopic process the feedback loop is infinitely short. We&apos;ll never get to that point but I think fully merging the design tasks into the development process will be a natural next step in improving how we create digital products. This will require different processe and better tools, but I think we have been going in the right direction for quite some time now. Both our processes and our tools are improving in a direction towards more immediate feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as our &lt;a href=&quot;http://sokolovstas.github.io/SublimeWebInspector/&quot;&gt;tools keep improving&lt;/a&gt; and we start using more agile ways of working, more and more people will become able to take on both the developer and designer roles. I think that&apos;s a really good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Pencils and oil paintings</title><id >apencilsandoilpaintings2013-10-26t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/pencils-and-oil-paintings"></link><updated >2013-10-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Imagine drawing with a pencil and instead of the lines on the paper appearing instantly as you drew them you had to wait five seconds, put away the pencil and flip your sketchbook to see the result of what you just drew. If you wanted to change or add something you would have to flip the sketchbook back again, pick up the pencil and draw some more. Then repeat the whole thing agian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That would be frustrating, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, that&apos;s pretty much what working with web coding has been like. Write some code, save the code, switch to the browser, reload the browser, look at the page, switch back to the editor, write more code…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web sites we used to make were like pencil sketches. And there are tools (Photoshop for example) that are really great for creating sketches like these. It&apos;s like using a real pencil. After you had made a sketch you just needed someone to copy it using the time-shifted code pencil so that it became a website. And for someone with the coding chops that&apos;s not too difficult, if you know exactly how it should look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But these days, the web sites we are building are more like oil paintings. Much more complex than pencil sketches, with color and structure that you can&apos;t communicate through a pencil sketch. So no matter how nice that Photoshop pencil sketch is, there&apos;s still plenty of work left for the guy making the oil painting. And he still only has time-shifted brushes and pencils to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing with code is hard. You basically have to become &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3vAnuBtyEYE&quot;&gt;Cypher from The Matrix&lt;/a&gt; to be able to design properly &amp;quot;in the browser&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously that&apos;s ridiculous and quite naturally people have been working hard to make better tools for us struggling front-end artists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there are two ways we can improve the tool set here. Either we can make the switch out the pencil for something more like real paint and brushes and we can make the time-shifted code brushes less time shifted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adobe are with their &lt;a href=&quot;http://html.adobe.com/edge/&quot;&gt;Edge&lt;/a&gt; line of tools doing both of these things. &lt;a href=&quot;http://html.adobe.com/edge/code&quot;&gt;Edge Code&lt;/a&gt;, built from the open source editor Brackets, aims to connect the code editor to your browser. Changes made to CSS are instantly updated in the browser, without you even having to save. HTML changes requires a file save, but the page is still automatically updated. Edge Code still has some way to go but it&apos;s a promising project. And still, for someone who doesn&apos;t know their code already, using it as a design tool will be like drawing with blindfolds on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://html.adobe.com/edge/reflow&quot;&gt;Edge Reflow&lt;/a&gt; comes from the other direction, aiming to extend Photoshop and to help create responsive web designs. It allows you to make responsive layouts pretty quickly if you have a Photoshop file to start from, and it will keep assets created in Photoshop in sync with the Edge Reflow layout. You can also export a &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; web page to view in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it&apos;s not more than a set of colored pencils. There&apos;s no support for interactivity. No hover states, no touch feedback, nothing at all more than just static layouts. It adds another dimension to Photoshop mockups&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other tools, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.divshot.com/&quot;&gt;Divshot&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://webflow.com/&quot;&gt;Webflow&lt;/a&gt;, are attempts to remove the coding blindfolds and make the web pages as editable as the code itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of projects that aim to improve the coding workflow as well. &lt;a href=&quot;http://mixture.io/&quot;&gt;Mixture&lt;/a&gt; for example provides a toolkit to help fix many of the problems with coding, for example it automatically loads all your saved changes into any connected browser (on any device). Neat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is the holy grail of web design tools? Well, to go back to the painting metaphor, we want brushes and colors that are not time-shifted, that give us immediate feedback without limiting what we can produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter how good tools like Edge Reflow become, we still have to translate their output to &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; web stuff. We would – at best – be back where we were in the &amp;quot;good old days&amp;quot;. But I think it&apos;s unrealistic to expect them to do anything but play catch-up with web technologies, and that means they will always be limiting what we can create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coding tools on the other hand will always be able to produce whatever the underlying technologies allow. That&apos;s where the potential is. If we can make coding tools that give us good enough feedback on what we are doing then they can be used to create things in a whole new way.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Moving on</title><id >amovingon2013-11-14t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/moving-on"></link><updated >2013-11-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow is my last day as a consultant. On Monday I will start working as a designer for &lt;a href=&quot;http://quinyx.com&quot;&gt;Quinyx&lt;/a&gt;, a company that makes Workforce Management software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My career began at a tech startup in Stockholm. We made advanced storage and backup software and I learned so much from my time there. I got the chance to do everything from interaction design to testing, from sales to web development, and I really enjoyed the process of building something. However, the company failed and I decided to start working as a consultant. After all, that&apos;s what most of my friends from university was doing and they seemed to like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then I&apos;ve been working as a consultant, getting thrown into different projects, mostly doing code monkey stuff, producing the kind of horrible enterprise software that I was pretty sure every user was going to hate. Actually I still don&apos;t know what any of the users think – user feedback never made it all the way back to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a consultant, I&apos;ve been in all sorts of projects in all sorts of organizations and I&apos;ve learned from all of them. Some projects have been fun, some have been boring. But none of them have been mine. I have always been building someone else&apos;s thing. I have never been responsible, and I&apos;ve never been on a project long enough to see it through. You rarely get bored as a consultant, but you never become attached to something either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might be naïve, but I hope working at a product company will give me a chance to do something about that. I&apos;m hoping to get an opportunity to build something great, iterate on it and live with it. And more than that, I hope to help make peoples lives a bit easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am really excited about the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >A year of progress</title><id >aayearofprogress2014-01-01t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/2013-a-year-of-progress"></link><updated >2014-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You know all those profile and presentation texts you have to write. For every new service you write another one. Somewhere, I don&apos;t remember where, I wrote &amp;quot;I live for progress&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year was a year of progress for me. During the last 12 months I have had the fortune of working with a lot of fun stuff and learn from amazing people. For that I am truly grateful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After working on a couple of projects that never made it to the public during 2012 I was lucky enough to build real stuff last year; stuff that people use and enjoy, now and hopefully for many years to come. I&apos;ve learnt so much from this and I hope it has prepared me for what&apos;s to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new year will incredibly exciting. I am building new things with new colleagues, and I think we can accomplish some pretty great things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last couple of years of my career has been mostly about writing code and I&apos;ve never really been comfortable with that. Code is never more than means to an end. I don&apos;t care about code. I care about making stuff that help people. Tools that are better than the ones we use today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think people need progress. We are constantly improving everything around us, like we have been since the dawn of time. The history of mankind is one of trying to make things better. Progress is a natural thing, something we take for granted. But it doesn&apos;t just happen. It requires people to put their hard work, focus, patience and talent to good use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making things is exciting. Let&apos;s make some awesome things this year.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Finding a process</title><id >afindingaprocess2014-01-06t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/finding-a-process"></link><updated >2014-01-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think a lot about process these days. Since we started making stuff for screens, design and development have pretty much been seperate diciplines. &lt;a href=&quot;http://eldh.co/who-is-a-designer&quot;&gt;I&apos;ve talked about this before&lt;/a&gt; and I have been thinking a lot on how to evolve the modern development process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most processes I&apos;ve seen have more or less completely seperated &amp;quot;design&amp;quot; from the rest of the development. Now I am a part of the organization for development of frontend stuff at Quinyx and we want to take a different approach. Our team is growing, so our process will likely gradually become more formalized and stale than it has been so far. I have set up a few principles to guide us on our journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design is how it works&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We care about design. But we have a holistic view of what design is. The things we often refer to as design – layout, interactions and graphics – are important. But so is performance, reliability, accessability and copy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design is not how it looks on paper, how it is simulated in a prototype or how it is explained in a breif. Design is how it works for the user. This means we avoid using deliverables that might give a false picture of how the product will look and work. We prefer usable prototypes over static mockups, real implementations over Photoshop comps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We want to be agile&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing &amp;quot;design&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;development&amp;quot; in seperate steps means it&apos;s hard to be agile. It means you create deliverables and lead times between the different stages. When you work on a short project, that approach might make sense and when you work in an agancy/client setup, there might be business reasons for such way of working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you are building a complex product that is going to live for a long time and continuously evolve, being able to &lt;em&gt;improve what already exists&lt;/em&gt; in an efficient way is really smart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means we want to have a process where the time between an idea and a tested implementation of that idea is really short. If that means skipping steps like detailed wireframes and graphical mockups – so be it. If we like how it works, we can take more time to polish it afterwards. If we don&apos;t, we just try the next idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our only deliverable is a working product. Anything else that we produce in the process needs to be properly motivated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good domain understanding is the key to taking the right decisions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good understanding our users and the problems that they face is essential in helping us take the right design decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We work in a pretty complex domain, and dogfooding isn&apos;t really a way to gain real insight for us (even though we do use our own product to some extent). This means we have to spend a good deal of time on making sure we have a &lt;em&gt;shared&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt; understanding and vocabulary to describe the domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short feedback loops are essential&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design is about understanding the problem, but it&apos;s also about exploring solutions, about discovery. It&apos;s about trying things to see how they work. We try to make it easy to explore new ideas, to be creative. This echoes both in our choice of tools and in the culture we try to build, where we focus on communication, collaboration and good feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope these guidelines will make things a bit easier for us when making decisions about how we do things. We&apos;re pretty happy with it so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a later post, I will share some details on how the process works and on the tools we use.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Redefining design</title><id >aredefiningdesign2014-07-16t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/redefining-design"></link><updated >2014-07-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve long felt that the &lt;a href=&quot;/who-is-a-designer/&quot;&gt;seperation between design and development&lt;/a&gt; has existed mainly because creating &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; things was too hard. Digital things used to be so hard to make that we had to make blueprints, sketches, prototypes, mockups and all these other things to communicate what we wanted to build, before we even started writing code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only did that approach come with a whole set of problems, but our tools has radically improved so building things has become easier. And the things we build have become more complex, making it harder to create designs for them. The cost of design has gone up and the cost of development has gone down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, last week I stumbled across &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@trevorconnolly/the-post-psd-era-doesnt-want-to-kill-designers-4281d505fd9a&quot;&gt;another post&lt;/a&gt; about the &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bradfrostweb.com/blog/post/the-post-psd-era/&quot;&gt;Post-PSD era of design&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, the term that Brad Frost popularized last year, and something that &lt;a href=&quot;http://eldh.co/slutet-p-photoshop-eran/&quot;&gt;I wrote about back in 2011&lt;/a&gt; (in Swedish, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/translate?hl=en&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;sl=auto&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;u=http%253A%252F%252Feldh.co%252Fslutet-p-photoshop-eran%252F&quot;&gt;google translation here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post contained Google&apos;s definition of design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;A plan or drawing produced to show the look and function or workings of a building, garment, or other object before it is made.&amp;quot;
&lt;em&gt;— Google&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Before.&lt;/em&gt; That&apos;s the word that struck me as odd. I&apos;ve been working the last six months creating a new system and &lt;a href=&quot;http://eldh.co/finding-a-process&quot;&gt;trying to find a process&lt;/a&gt; that allows us to work in a nice agile way. We build by iterating. Build, improve, refine. Build, improve, refine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if all we do is a continuous &lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt; cycle and design is what&apos;s done before we build, what in our process is actually &lt;em&gt;design&lt;/em&gt;? What is it that we need to do &lt;em&gt;before we make&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, agile works because in the digital world changing things is cheap. But of course some things are more expensive than others. To minimize the risk of having to change expensive things, we need to identify which parts are expensive and then we need to make sure we get them right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My view is that for anyone who is creating a non-trivial system, domain modeling is the most expensive part of the creation process. For others, information architecture might be the most expensive part. Things that we perhaps usually think of as &lt;em&gt;requirements&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is that the expensive part, the part you really should do &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; you build, is probably not what you think of as design. Layout, interactions, copy, typography, iconography, graphics and motion are all important parts of what the final product will be and we cannot do without them. But for any project that&apos;s bigger than a marketing page, those things are relatively cheap, and more importantly they are easier and more natural to integrate into the normal build cycle of the agile process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question we really need to ask before we start building is not &lt;em&gt;What should it look like?&lt;/em&gt; but rather &lt;em&gt;What is it and which things does it represent?&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For us, design as defined by Google, is something quite different from what we normally think of as design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not just a question of semantics. It&apos;s a matter of knowing where we should spend our time, what we should make sure to get right on the first pass and which things we can iteratively improve. It&apos;s about defining a workflow and a process that helps us create better things.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >Women in tech</title><id >awomenintech2014-09-19t00:00:00+02:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/women-in-tech"></link><updated >2014-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A pretty common topic in the tech industry is &amp;quot;women&amp;quot;. I think it&apos;s necessary to talk about women in tech and I was really glad that &lt;a href=&quot;https://nordicjs.com&quot;&gt;Nordic.js&lt;/a&gt; had &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Bougie&quot;&gt;Caroline Drucker&lt;/a&gt; give a kinda Feminism 101 talk at the conference (&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@bougie/notes-on-im-a-feminist-and-so-can-you-7b9c278a0b7c&quot;&gt;Here are Caroline&apos;s notes from the talk, together with a video recording.&lt;/a&gt;). It was a really good talk, and I think we need to continue the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s get one thing out of the way first: I don&apos;t consider myself a feminist. Not because I oppose women’s rights or don&apos;t believe our society has a lot of problems when it comes to gender equality. I don&apos;t. We do. But. I believe in equal rights and equal opportunities but I don&apos;t believe that achieving those will mean that we always get equal outcome. Also, in Sweden the feminist movement has largely become synonymous with far-left socialists that I just don&apos;t want to get associated with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that is not important. Let&apos;s not let labels draw our eyes from the problem at hand. Actually, I think we are facing two different problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women don&apos;t get into the tech industry. They choose other paths in life and the tech industry becomes male dominated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women and other minorities in tech are treated badly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first of these problems will take years to tackle, and is much bigger than just our little industry. We can do a lot of stuff now to get girls and women interested in tech. But we can&apos;t expect to fix it overnight, since any real solution requires women to choose different paths early in life than they do today and have been doing for some time. The tech industry will continue to be male dominated for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still want to list some things that we should try to do in order to, eventually, make the situation better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get coding into schools. Estonian kids start coding in first grade. So should kids in all countries. Being able to talk to computers is going to be an essential skill in the twenty-first century and it&apos;s going to make kids understand more about what the tech industry is about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make it easier to tell computers how to do advanced things (what we now know as &amp;quot;coding&amp;quot;). We need to make creative tools that are easier to use so that we can lower the barrier to get into the tech industry and make it accessible to more people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a role model, and help showcase other role models. We need to show what we can do and why we love it, to help young people realise that you don&apos;t have to be in one specific way to work in tech. We need to show our diversity, both in terms of gender, race, skill sets and personality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second problem should be possible to fix much sooner. And much of what Drucker mentioned during her talk is stuff that addresses the second problem. Specifically, she mentioned 10 steps we can take to make things better:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Listen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amplify&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chose your words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use your voice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Question your culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demand adult HR&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be an example&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be human&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these I find somewhat problematic. Not because they are wrong per se, but for two other reasons. First, because they because I think they are vague and easy to misunderstand. Secondly, I think we should focus not on counteraction but on elimination of discrimination and underrepresentation. I believe affirmative action is counter-productive and gives a false sense of acheivment. Those are just minor comments. Do these things and you&apos;ll be fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do however have a couple of guidelines of my own that I try to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep things professional. Work is work. The fantastic thing about our industry is that pretty much all of us love what we do. We have chosen to do THIS among the many other things we could have done. Treat people as professionals who share your love for tech and keep it at that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be curious. Don&apos;t be afraid to ask if you don&apos;t know or don&apos;t understand. Asking and listening will help you understand people and become more empathic. Let people tell their story.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are all individuals. We have all done different journeys and we all have different experiences, interests and skill sets. Don&apos;t treat everyone the same, but treat everyone as adults, and treat them with respect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speak up. When people make mistakes, initiate a discussion about how to do things in a better way. I think nobody wants to be an asshole, and in every other aspect our industry takes pride in learning from our mistakes. This should be no different. Embrace mistakes and help the people around you improve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would love to see more thoughts on this subject. Ideas need to be bounced. I don&apos;t think there&apos;s a quick fix. Utopia doesn&apos;t exist and we&apos;re only human. But almost all of us want the same thing here. Let&apos;s make try to make it better together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok. So when are we done?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will never be done. We won&apos;t wake up one day having fixed all the problems. We&apos;re going to have to make this, the constant struggle to improve, a part of what we do. Just like we do with most of the problems we face on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry ><title >The Zone</title><id >athezone2015-01-25t00:00:00+01:00</id><link href="http://eldh.co/the-zone"></link><updated >2015-01-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have always worked in offices. For most part, I&apos;ve appreciated the benefits of being at the same physical location as the rest of your team. But this winter has forced me to work from home quite a bit and it has been quite an eye-opener.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started working from the couch, I thought I would have trouble keeping focused with all the distractions around me. I thought it would be hard to keep the dicipline. I had made sure to load up a bunch of tasks that I could take care of without interacting too much with my team, but still my expectations were pretty low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to find that the days just flew by, and I felt really productive. Apparently I didn&apos;t suck as much at concentrating as I did when I was trying to write my thesis. And with no one there to pull me into meetings, ask questions or just talk loudly I could really focus on what I was supposed to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I came back it became more obvious that I wasn&apos;t as productive at work as I was at home. Of course, I&apos;m not the first to experience this (I bought Rework when it came out). And I still think there is a lot of benefits to working in an office. Getting a lot of work done is not one of them though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought it shouldn&apos;t be impossible to change that so I gave it some thought and I realised that it in order to reduce distractions, we would have to have some formal guidelines in place. I call it “The Zone”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The rules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A person decides if and when he is in the zone, and responsible for letting others know.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No one engages in a conversation with someone who is in the Zone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People in the Zone are online and responsive on Hipchat/Slack/Hangouts/Whatever.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emails are responded to at least twice daily, morning and afternoon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone can join the Zone, but the whole company has to respect the rules of the Zone when communicating with its members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;FAQ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Should The Zone a physical area?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
No. The thought behind the zone is that it should work wherever you are, and in teams where only a few people are in The Zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you know who is in the zone?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We use headphones. You could try signs, stickers or funny hats. The important thing is the rules are agreed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Should we communicate less?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
No! The goal of The Zone is to enable communication that minimizes disturbances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&apos;t mind being disturbed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I do. I will try to disturb you from time to time and you can try not to disturb me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does it work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We&apos;ve done this for a couple of weeks and it&apos;s been working out pretty well. Only a few team members wanted to be in the Zone, but everyone knows and respects the rules. It&apos;s still harder to stay focused than it is at home, but our current office setup really is the worst ever — our team is in the middle of an open space with prople running by all the time. I expect things to improve a lot when we move to a new space next month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Feedback&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;d like to hear thoughts on how other people have solved this problem. Talk to me on &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/eldh&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>